<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: azure key vault | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/azure-key-vault/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-30T00:02:07+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expiry Notification for Azure Key Vault Keys and Secrets]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/expiry-notification-for-azure-key-vault-keys-and-secrets/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/expiry-notification-for-azure-key-vault-keys-and-secrets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I came across this <a href="https://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/azure/en-US/90d4b814-f025-42a0-acac-b8c8bf9d8cf8/alert-or-event-on-secret-expiry?forum=AzureKeyVault">question</a> in Azure Key Vault forums looking for options to get notified when Key or Secrets in vault nears expiry. It&rsquo;s useful to know when Object&rsquo;s (Keys/Secrets) near expiry, to take necessary action. I decided to explore on my proposed solution of having a scheduled custom PowerShell script to notify when a key is about to expire. In this post, we will see how to get all objects nearing expiry and scheduling this using Azure Runbook to run daily.</p>

<h3>Getting Expiring Objects</h3>

<p>Both Keys and Secrets can be set with an Expiry date. The expiry date can be set when creating the Object or can be set on an existing Object. This can be set from the UI or using PowerShell scripts (setting the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn868045.aspx">-Expires attribute</a>).</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Azure Key Vault - Set Key Expiry" src="/images/vaultexpiry_key.png"/></p>

<p>Key Vault (at the time of writing) throws an <a href="https://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/azure/en-US/c0d8953a-c117-4ca4-ad3d-e5d2b1868f9e/get-operation-not-permitted-for-some-of-the-secret-in-my-vault?forum=AzureKeyVault">exception</a> when an expired key is accessed over the API. Also, it does not provide any notification whenever a key/secret is about to expire. The last thing you want is your application go down because of an expired object in the vault. With the Get and List access on the vault, we can retrieve all the keys and secrets in the vault and loop through the elements to see objects that are nearing expiry.</p>

<p>The PowerShell script takes the Vault Name, number of days before with alert should be raised and flags to indicate whether all versions of keys/secrets should be checked for expiry. The full script is available <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/Blog/blob/master/KeyVaultExpiryAlerter/Expiry%20Alert.ps1">here</a>.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">$VaultName = ''
$IncludeAllKeyVersions = $true
$IncludeAllSecretVersions = $true
$AlertBeforeDays = 3
</code></pre>

<p>All keys and secrets are converted into a common object model, which contains just the Identifier, Name, Version and the Expiry Date if it has one.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">Function New-KeyVaultObject
{
    param
    (
        [string]$Id,
        [string]$Name,
        [string]$Version,
        [System.Nullable[DateTime]]$Expires
    )

    $server = New-Object -TypeName PSObject
    $server | Add-Member -MemberType NoteProperty -Name Id -Value $Id
    $server | Add-Member -MemberType NoteProperty -Name Name -Value $Name
    $server | Add-Member -MemberType NoteProperty -Name Version -Value $Version
    $server | Add-Member -MemberType NoteProperty -Name Expires -Value $Expires

    return $server
}
</code></pre>

<p>Depending on the flag set for retrieving all key/secret version, it fetches objects from the vault and returns in the common object model above.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">function Get-AzureKeyVaultObjectKeys
{
  param
  (
   [string]$VaultName,
   [bool]$IncludeAllVersions
  )

  $vaultObjects = [System.Collections.ArrayList]@()
  $allKeys = Get-AzureKeyVaultKey -VaultName $VaultName
  foreach ($key in $allKeys) {
    if($IncludeAllVersions){
     $allSecretVersion = Get-AzureKeyVaultKey -VaultName $VaultName -IncludeVersions -Name $key.Name
     foreach($key in $allSecretVersion){
         $vaultObject = New-KeyVaultObject -Id $key.Id -Name $key.Name -Version $key.Version -Expires $key.Expires
         $vaultObjects.Add($vaultObject)
     }

    } else {
      $vaultObject = New-KeyVaultObject -Id $key.Id -Name $key.Name -Version $key.Version -Expires $key.Expires
      $vaultObjects.Add($vaultObject)
    }
  }

  return $vaultObjects
}

function Get-AzureKeyVaultObjectSecrets
{
  param
  (
   [string]$VaultName,
   [bool]$IncludeAllVersions
  )

  $vaultObjects = [System.Collections.ArrayList]@()
  $allSecrets = Get-AzureKeyVaultSecret -VaultName $VaultName
  foreach ($secret in $allSecrets) {
    if($IncludeAllVersions){
     $allSecretVersion = Get-AzureKeyVaultSecret -VaultName $VaultName -IncludeVersions -Name $secret.Name
     foreach($secret in $allSecretVersion){
         $vaultObject = New-KeyVaultObject -Id $secret.Id -Name $secret.Name -Version $secret.Version -Expires $secret.Expires
         $vaultObjects.Add($vaultObject)
     }

    } else {
      $vaultObject = New-KeyVaultObject -Id $secret.Id -Name $secret.Name -Version $secret.Version -Expires $secret.Expires
      $vaultObjects.Add($vaultObject)
    }
  }

  return $vaultObjects
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now that we have all the keys and secrets we want to check for expiry all we need to know is if there are any keys that are expiring in the upcoming days.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">$allKeyVaultObjects = [System.Collections.ArrayList]@()
$allKeyVaultObjects.AddRange((Get-AzureKeyVaultObjectKeys -VaultName $VaultName -IncludeAllVersions $IncludeAllKeyVersions))
$allKeyVaultObjects.AddRange((Get-AzureKeyVaultObjectSecrets -VaultName $VaultName -IncludeAllVersions $IncludeAllSecretVersions))

# Get expired Objects
$today = (Get-Date).Date
$expiredKeyVaultObjects = [System.Collections.ArrayList]@()
foreach($vaultObject in $allKeyVaultObjects){
if($vaultObject.Expires -and $vaultObject.Expires.AddDays(-$AlertBeforeDays).Date -lt $today)
{
  # add to expiry list
  $expiredKeyVaultObjects.Add($vaultObject) | Out-Null
  Write-Output "Expiring" $vaultObject.Id

}

# Pass to Alerter $expiredKeyVaultObjects
}
</code></pre>

<h3>Scheduling Expiry Notification using Azure Runbook</h3>

<p>You can either run this manually every time you want to get a list of objects that are expired or nearing expiry. Alternatively, you can set up a scheduled task to run the script at a set frequency. Since you are already on Azure, you can try <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/services/automation/">Azure Automation</a> and schedule the task for you. A Runbook in Azure Automation account can be granted access to the key vault. The Automation account should have &lsquo;Run as account&rsquo; setup and the service principal created for it can be used to assign Access Policies to access the vault. Check out the <a href="/blog/accessing-azure-key-vault-from-azure-runbook">Accessing Azure Key Vault From Azure Runbook</a> post for a step by step instruction on how to setup runbook to access key vault. You can then <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/documentation/articles/automation-scheduling-a-runbook/">schedule the runbook</a> to execute at fixed time intervals. Feel free to modify the script to send email notifications or push notification or any other that matches your need.</p>

<p>Generally, it is a good practice to rotate your keys and secrets once in a while. Use the expiry attribute to set the expiry and force yourself to keep your sensitive configurations fresh. It&rsquo;s likely that such a notification feature will be built into the key vault. But till then Hope this helps to keep track of keys or secrets that are nearing expiry within the vault and take the necessary action to renew them. The full script is available <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/Blog/blob/master/KeyVaultExpiryAlerter/Expiry%20Alert.ps1">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessing Azure Key Vault From Azure Runbook]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/accessing-azure-key-vault-from-azure-runbook/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/accessing-azure-key-vault-from-azure-runbook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Azure Automation is a new service in Azure that allows you to automate your Azure management tasks and to orchestrate actions across external systems from right within Azure. If you are new to Azure Automation, get started <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/azure-automation-runbook-management/">here</a>. Runbooks live within the Azure Automation account and can execute PowerShell scripts. In this post, I will walk you through on how to use Key Vault from an Azure Automation Runbook.</p>

<p>To create a Runbook go to &lsquo;Add a Runbook&rsquo; under  Automation Account, Runbooks as shown in the image below. Once created you can author your PowerShell script there.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Azure Automation Create a Runbook" src="/images/runbook_create.png"/></p>

<p>In this example I will get all the Keys from an existing key vault, using the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn868053.aspx">Get-AzureKeyVaultKey</a> cmdlet. This returns all the key for the given key vault.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">Get-AzureKeyVaultKey -VaultName YoutubeVault
</code></pre>

<p>If we are to run this script now, it will fail for many reasons - we do not have the key vault cmdlets imported in the runbook nor have we given access to the automation account to access the keys in the vault. Running it gives me the below error.</p>

<p><span style='color:red'><em>Get-AzureKeyVaultKey : The term &lsquo;Get-AzureKeyVaultKey&rsquo; is not recognized as the name of a cmdlet, function script, file, or operable program. Check the spelling of the name, or if a path was included, verify that the path is correct and try again </em></span>.</p>

<p>Under &lsquo;Assets&rsquo; from the Azure Automation account Resources section select &lsquo;Modules&rsquo; (as shown in the image below) to add in Modules to the runbook. To execute key vault cmdlets in the runbook, we need to add <em>AzureRM.profile</em> and AzureRM.key vault. Search for this under &lsquo;Browse Gallery&rsquo; and import.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Azure Runbook Add KeyVault Module" src="/images/runbook_add_Module.png"/></p>

<p>To give Runbook access to the keys in the vault, it needs to be specified in the Access Policies of the key vault. The &lsquo;Run As Accounts&rsquo; feature will create a new service principal user in Azure Active Directory and assign the Contributor role to this user at the subscription. The &lsquo;Application ID&rsquo; from creating the run as account is used to assign Access Policies for the key vault. In this example, I give the &lsquo;list&rsquo; and &lsquo;get&rsquo; PermissionToKeys.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Azure Automation Runbook, set run as account" src="/images/runbook_run_as_accounts.png"/></p>

<p>You can use the <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/documentation/articles/automation-sec-configure-azure-runas-account/#sample-code-to-authenticate-with-resource-manager-resources">sample code below</a>, taken from the AzureAutomationTutorialScript example runbook, to authenticate using the Run As account to manage Resource Manager resources with your runbooks. The <em>AzureRunAsConnection</em> is a connection asset automatically created when we created &lsquo;run as accounts&rsquo; above. This can be found under Assets -> Connections. After the authentication code, I run the same code above to get all the keys from the vault.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">$connectionName = "AzureRunAsConnection"
try
{
    # Get the connection "AzureRunAsConnection "
    $servicePrincipalConnection=Get-AutomationConnection -Name $connectionName         

    "Logging in to Azure..."
    Add-AzureRmAccount `
        -ServicePrincipal `
        -TenantId $servicePrincipalConnection.TenantId `
        -ApplicationId $servicePrincipalConnection.ApplicationId `
        -CertificateThumbprint $servicePrincipalConnection.CertificateThumbprint 
}
catch {
    if (!$servicePrincipalConnection)
    {
        $ErrorMessage = "Connection $connectionName not found."
        throw $ErrorMessage
    } else{
        Write-Error -Message $_.Exception
        throw $_.Exception
    }
}

Get-AzureKeyVaultKey -VaultName YoutubeVault
</code></pre>

<p>On execution, the Runbook can connect to the key vault and retrieve all the keys. Based on the permissions set on the vault you can perform different actions on the key vault. This helps in automating a lot of tasks that otherwise needs to be done manually. Hope this helps you connect Runbooks with Key Vault.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Azure Key Vault: Digital Signatures and Offline Verification]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-digital-signatures-and-offline-verification/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-digital-signatures-and-offline-verification</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Digital Signature is a mechanism to ensure the validity of a digital document or message. Digital signatures use <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-azure-key-vault/">asymmetric cryptography</a> - uses a public and private key pair.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>A valid <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_signature">digital signature</a> gives a recipient reason to believe that the message was created by a known sender (authentication), that the sender cannot deny having sent the message (non-repudiation), and that the message was not altered in transit (integrity)</em></p></blockquote>

<p>The below diagram shows the overview of the different steps involved in the Digital Signature process. We generate a hash of the data that we need to protect and encrypt the hash value using a private key pair. This signed hash is sent along with the original data. The receiver generates a hash of the data received and also decrypts the attached signature using the public key. If both the hashes are same, the signature is valid, and the document has not been tampered with.</p>

<p><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Digital_Signature_diagram.svg"><img class="center" alt="Azure Key Vault - Verify Signature Offline" src="/images/signing_verification.png"/></a></p>

<p>Azure Key Vault supports sign and verify operations and can be used to implement Digital Signatures. In this post, we will explore how to sign and verify a message using Key Vault. Verifying the hash locally is the recommended approach as per the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/azure/dn903623.aspx#BKMK_KeyOperations">documentation</a> and we will explore how this can be achieved.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Verification of signed hashes is supported as a convenience operation for applications that may not have access to [public] key material; it is recommended that, for best application performance, verify operations are performed locally.</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>Signing Data</h3>

<p>Sign and Verify operations on Key Vault are allowed only on hashed data. So the application calling these API methods should locally hash the data before invoking the method. The algorithm property value passed to the Key Vault Client API depends on the hashing algorithm used to hash the data. Below are the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/library/en-us/Mt149357.aspx">supported algorithms</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><em>RS256: RSASSA-PKCS-v1_5 using SHA-256. The application supplied digest value must be computed using SHA-256 and must be 32 bytes in length.</em></li>
<li><em>RS384: RSASSA-PKCS-v1_5 using SHA-384. The application supplied digest value must be computed using SHA-384 and must be 48 bytes in length.</em></li>
<li><em>RS512: RSASSA-PKCS-v1_5 using SHA-512. The application supplied digest value must be computed using SHA-512 and must be 64 bytes in length.</em></li>
<li><em>RSNULL: See [RFC2437], a specialized use-case to enable certain TLS scenarios.</em></li>
</ul>


<p>The below code sample uses SHA-256 hashing algorithm to hash and sign the data.</p>

<pre><code class="csharp">var textToEncrypt = "This is a test message";
var byteData = Encoding.Unicode.GetBytes(textToEncrypt);
var hasher = new SHA256CryptoServiceProvider();
var digest = hasher.ComputeHash(byteData);
var signedResult = await keyVaultClient
    .SignAsync(keyIdentifier, JsonWebKeySignatureAlgorithm.RS256, digest);
</code></pre>

<h3>Verify Online</h3>

<p>To verify a signature online, the keyVaultClient supports a <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/microsoft.azure.keyvault.keyvaultclient.verifyasync.aspx">Verify method</a>. It takes the key identifier, algorithm, digest and signature to verify if the signature is valid for the given digest.</p>

<pre><code class="csharp">var isVerified = await keyVaultClient
    .VerifyAsync(keyIdentifier, JsonWebKeySignatureAlgorithm.RS256, digest, signedResult.Result);
</code></pre>

<h3>Verify Offline</h3>

<p>To Verify offline, we need access to the public portion of the key used to sign the data. The client application that needs to verify signatures can connect to the vault and get the key details or use a public key shared out of band. The <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/authenticating-a-client-application-with-azure-key-vault/">AD application used to authenticate</a> with the key vault should have Get access for retrieving the public key from the vault. Get access can be set using the PermissionToKeys switch when registering the AD application with the key vault. Assuming we have access to the public key as a JSON string, we can use the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.security.cryptography.rsacryptoserviceprovider(v=vs.110).aspx">RSACryptoServiceProvider</a> to verify the signature offline.</p>

<pre><code class="csharp">var key = JsonConvert.DeserializeObject&lt;JsonWebKey&gt;(jsonWebKey);
var rsa = new RSACryptoServiceProvider();
var p = new RSAParameters() { Modulus = key.N, Exponent = key.E };
rsa.ImportParameters(p);
isVerified = rsa.VerifyHash(digest, "Sha256", signedResult.Result);
</code></pre>

<p>The signature verification succeeds if the message and the signature were not tampered. If either of message or signature were  modified then the signature validation fails.</p>

<p>You can get the sample code <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/Blog/tree/master/VerifySignatureOffline">here</a>. Hope this helps you to implement Digital Signatures using Key Vault.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Key Vault Through Azure Portal]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/managing-key-vault-through-azure-portal/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/managing-key-vault-through-azure-portal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You can now manage Key Vault through the Azure portal. Prior to this the Key Vault&rsquo;s were managed either using <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-the-deprecation-of-switch-azuremode-affects-azure-key-vault/">Powershell</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/managing-azure-key-vault-using-azure-resource-manager-arm-templates/">ARM Templates</a> or <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/managing-azure-key-vault-over-the-rest-api/">REST API</a>. Managing key Vault is now easy and user-friendly for the nontechnical people. In this post, I will walk through the new features in Azure Portal to manage key vault.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>If you find any difference between what you see in the portal versus those in the screenshots below, it&rsquo;s likely that the portal is updated</em></p></blockquote>

<p>In the new Azure portal search for &lsquo;key vault&rsquo; to access this new feature. Or you can go to &lsquo;More Services&rsquo; and scroll down to &lsquo;Security + Identity&rsquo; section in the menu. Selecting Key Vault takes you to all the available Key Vaults under your subscription. You can further filter the Vault&rsquo;s list by the vault name using the filter box or based on your subscriptions.</p>

<p><img  alt="Key Vault in Azure Portal" src="/images/keyvaultportal_menu_option.png"/></p>

<h4><strong>Creating Key Vault</strong></h4>

<p>To create a new Key Vault select the &lsquo;Create&rsquo; option. By entering the Vault Name, Subscription, Resource Group and Location you can create a new Key Vault.</p>

<p><img  alt="Create Key Vault in Azure Portal" src="/images/keyvaultportal_create_key_vault.png"/></p>

<p>The pricing tier defaults to Standard and it does not support HSM backed keys. This means you will be only able to create Software keys. You can select the  Premium pricing tier if you need HSM backed keys. By default the login with which you create the subscription with gets granted access to the vault and is added to the access policies. You can grant additional applications or users access and control the permissions. Below I am adding in an AD application.</p>

<p><img  alt="Key Vault Add Access Policy" src="/images/keyvaultportal_access_policy.png"/></p>

<p>You can specify the Key Permissions and the Secret Permissions that the ServicePrincipal.</p>

<p><img  alt="Access Policy set Secret Permissions" src="/images/keyvaultportal_secretpermissions.png"/></p>

<h4><strong>Keys and Secrets</strong></h4>

<p>Once the Vault is created you can add in Keys and Secrets into the vault. This can be done by selecting the Vault that was just created from the Vaults list. From here you can manage different aspects of the Vault and also manage Keys and Secrets.</p>

<p><img  alt="Access Policy set Secret Permissions" src="/images/keyvaultportal_keyvault.png"/></p>

<p>The Azure Portal experience of Key Vault is good. It covers most of the functionalities needed when using a Key Vault. How do you find the new UI experience?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keeping Sensitive Configuration Data Out of Source Control]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/keeping-sensitive-configuration-data-out-of-source-control/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/keeping-sensitive-configuration-data-out-of-source-control</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most applications today deals with some form of sensitive information. The most commonly seen are database connection strings, API keys, token etc. The web.config seems the best place to have these values, but it definitely is not. In most cases it gets pushed into the source control systems as well. If it is a private repository then you at least have one level of security on top of it. It still exposes sensitive information to anyone who has access to the repository. It’s worse when the <a href="http://www.internetnews.com/blog/skerner/github-search-exposes-passwords.html">repository is public</a>.</p>

<p><img alt="Keep sensitive data out of source control" src="/images/sensitivedata_source_control.png" /></p>

<p>There are different ways you can  avoid pushing sensitive data into source control. In this post, I will explore options that I am familiar with.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Use configuration files as template definitions for the configuration data your application requires. Have the actual values stored elsewhere</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>Azure App Settings</h3>

<p>If you are deploying your application as a Web App on Azure, you can store <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/windows-azure-web-sites-how-application-strings-and-connection-strings-work/">application settings and connection strings in Azure</a>. At runtime, Windows Azure Web Sites automatically retrieves these values for you and makes them available to code running in your website. This removes the need for having sensitive data in the configuration file.</p>

<p><img alt="Azure App Settings and Connection Strings" src="/images/sensitiveData_azure_app_settings.png" /></p>

<h3>Release Management Tools</h3>

<p>Release management tools like Octopus Deploy, Microsoft Release Management, that performs configuration transformation. It supports creating different environments (development, production) and corresponding configurations. On creating a package for an environment, it applies the corresponding environment configurations</p>

<p><img alt="Release Management Tools - Octopus Deploy" src="/images/sensitiveData_releaseManagement_tool_octopus.png" /></p>

<p>Packaging embeds the configuration value into the configuration file. This makes it available to anyone who has access to the host systems.</p>

<h3>Azure Key Vault</h3>

<p>Azure Key Vault acts as a centralized repository for all sensitive information. Key vault stores cryptographic keys and Secrets and makes them available over a HTTP Api. The objects (keys and secrets) in key vault has unique identifier to retrieve them. Check <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-in-a-real-world-application/">Azure Key Vault in real world application</a> for more details on how to achieve this. A client application can <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/authenticating-a-client-application-with-azure-key-vault/">authenticate with Azure Key Vault using a ClientID/secret or ClientID/certificate</a>. Using certificate to authenticate is the preferred approach. To get Keys/Secret from key vault all you need is the AD Application Id, the client secret or certificate identifier and the key/secret names. The certificate itself can be deployed separately into the application host.</p>

<pre><code class="XML">&lt;appSettings&gt;
  &lt;add key="KeyVaultUrl" value="https://testvaultrahul.vault.azure.net"/&gt;
  &lt;add key="ADApplicationId" value="" /&gt;
  &lt;add key="ADCertificateThumbprint" value="" /&gt;
  &lt;add key="DbConnectionString" value="SqlConnectionString"/&gt;
  &lt;add key ="ApiToken" value="ApiToken/cfedea84815e4ca8bc19cf8eb943ee13"/&gt;
&lt;/appSettings&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>If you are using the &lsquo;client secret&rsquo; to authenticate then the configuration file will have the Secret. In either cases, you should follow either of the previous approaches to keep the Application Id and authentication information out of configuration. The advantage of using <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/azure-key-vault/">Key Vault</a> is that it is a centralized  repository for all your sensitive data, across different applications. You can also restrict access permissions per application.</p>

<p>These are some approaches to keep sensitive information out of source control. What approach do you use? Irrespective of the approach you use, make sure that you don’t check them in!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
