<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: speaking | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/speaking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-29T04:51:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thanks to Everyone Who Attended Our Talk at Microsoft India, Hyderabad]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/thanks-to-everyone-who-attended-our-talk-at-microsoft-india-hyderabad/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-18T00:22:37+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/thanks-to-everyone-who-attended-our-talk-at-microsoft-india-hyderabad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to everyone who attended our(<a href="https://twitter.com/techgd">Gautam</a> and mine) talk on Getting Started with Windows Phone and Store application on June 18, Tuesday as part of the Readiness training at Microsoft. Special thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/vamsitp">Vamsi</a> for assisting us throughout. I hope you all enjoyed the session as much as we did. Here are some follow up information that might help you on the way forward. Since the intended audience are from testing and UX the follow up material is more aligned towards that.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>In case you would like to have a deeper understanding on the MVVM pattern, and how it helps us, the below links should be useful</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/dn463790.aspx">Writing a Testable Presentation Layer with MVVM</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/events/TechDays/Techdays-2014-the-Netherlands/Using-MVVM-So-You-Can-Write-Better-Code-and-Less-Code">Using MVVM So You Can Write Better Code and Less Code</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/events/MIX/MIX11/OPN03">Deep Dive MVVM</a></p></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>MVVM is also helpful in Unit Testing improving the overall maintainability of the code too.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/Build/2012/3-017">Unit Testing Windows Store Apps</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Check out how you can create automated tests and also on the Coded UI support</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/events/TechEd/NorthAmerica/2014/DEV-B347#fbid=">Automated Testing of XAML-Based Windows Phone Applications</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/events/Build/2013/3-323">Automated Testing of XAML-Based Windows Store Apps</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/visualstudioalm/archive/2014/04/05/using-coded-ui-to-test-xaml-based-windows-phone-apps.aspx">Using Coded UI to test XAML-based Windows Phone apps</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/cdndevs/archive/2014/05/05/save-time-money-and-your-sanity-coded-ui-testing-for-the-windows-phone-part-1.aspx">Save Time, Money, and Your Sanity: Coded UI Testing for the Windows Phone</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/visualstudioalm/archive/2013/06/26/using-coded-ui-to-test-xaml-based-windows-store-apps.aspx">Using Coded UI to test XAML-based Windows Store apps</a></p></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Look into the tools and ways to analyze and improve performance</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/MIX/MIX11/DVC01">Analyzing and Improving Windows Phone Application Performance</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/Build/2014/3-578">Diagnosing Issues in Windows Phone XAML Apps Using Visual Studio</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/Build/2014/4-557">How to Analyze Performance Issues in Your Windows and Windows Phone Apps</a></p></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>See how app crashes information can be tracked from a deployed app and how it can used and inferred upon to fix  issues. This is very important so that you can improve on the app reliability and performance for further updates.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/Build/2014/3-657">Avoiding Windows Store App Failures</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Learn about the security features and how it is important</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/Build/2014/2-531">New Security Features for Windows Phone</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/TechEd/NorthAmerica/2014/WIN-B357#fbid=">Windows Phone 8.1 Security and Management: The Right Choice for the Enterprise!</a></p></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Stay in touch. You can find the presentation slides <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/Speaking/tree/master/Windows%20Phone%20And%20Store%20Apps">here</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thanks to Everyone Who Attended My First Public Talk At C#Corner Hyderabad UG]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/thanks-to-everyone-who-attended-my-first-public-talk-at-ccorner-hyderabad-ug/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-03T06:39:27+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/thanks-to-everyone-who-attended-my-first-public-talk-at-ccorner-hyderabad-ug</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to everyone who attended <a href="http://www.c-sharpcorner.com/Events/64/">my very first public talk</a>, at the <a href="http://www.c-sharpcorner.com/">C#Corner</a> <a href="http://www.c-sharpcorner.com/Chapters/6/hyderabad-chapter.aspx">Hyderabad Chapter User Group(UG)</a> on February 1, Saturday on Windows Phone Development. Summary of the event is available <a href="http://www.c-sharpcorner.com/UploadFile/subhendude/C-Sharp-corner-hyderabad-user-group-meet-1-february-2014-offici/">here</a>. It was a very good experience speaking for the first time in front of a large audience, and from my side felt it went well. Here&rsquo;s some follow up information on the talk and also the code samples and presentations used.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>There might be a lot of you who would be planning to get started with phone development or yet in the dilema of whether or not to - <em><strong>&lsquo;Don&rsquo;t think much and just start <a href="http://developer.windowsphone.com/en-us">getting your hands dirty</a></strong></em>&rsquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>If your current project/work does not demand you to use whatever we have got started with it, develop a simple application on your free time/weekends. You would get lot of app ideas at <a href="http://www.dvlup.com/SignIn">DVLUP</a> and may even get rewarded if you crack some of their challenges - <em><strong>Stay motivated.</strong></em></p></li>
<li><p>Make sure whatever you develop is always properly backed up and stored - <em><strong>Use a source control</strong></em>.
<a href="http://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-online-overview-vs#SKUDetailList_1">Visual Studio Online</a> or <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a> are great free services that could get you started with.</p></li>
<li><p>Learn more about <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tag/mvvm/">MVVM</a>.The mvvm toolkit that we were using at the demo is <a href="http://mvvmlight.codeplex.com/">MVVM Light</a>. There are a couple of videos in <a href="http://mvvmlight.codeplex.com/">there</a> that will help you get started with it. <a href="http://compositewpf.codeplex.com/">Prism</a> is also another alternative that we had talked about. - <em><strong>Reuse across platforms</strong></em></p></li>
<li><p>As we had discussed, Getting Started in Windows Phone Development means you have acquired the same skills to Get Started on Windows 8 application too - <em><strong>Get started <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-in/windows/apps/br211386.aspx">here</a></strong></em>.</p></li>
<li><p>There are a lot of applications that are waiting to be developed for Windows phone and Windows 8 for which people are even ready to pay you. So if you want to earn out of your side projects, then try looking for projects in freelancing communities - <a href="https://www.odesk.com/">ODesk</a>, <a href="http://www.freelancer.in/">Freelancer</a>, <a href="https://www.elance.com/">Elance</a> are some to get you started - <em><strong>Earn while you Learn</strong></em></p></li>
</ul>


<p>Feel free to get in touch in case you need any help while on your Windows phone journey.</p>

<p>The samples and presentation slides is available in the event summary above or <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/Speaking/tree/master/Getting%20Started%20with%20Windows%20Phone%208%20App%20Development">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
