<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-07T00:01:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working Effectively Under Constraints]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/working-effectively-under-constraints/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/working-effectively-under-constraints</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At times you might be working in environments where there are a lot of restrictions on the tools that you can use, the process that you need to follow, etc. Under these circumstances, it is essential that we stick to some core and fundamental principles and practices that we as an industry have adopted. We need to make sure that we have that in place no matter what the restrictions imposed are. Below are a few of the restrictions that I along with my team had to face at one of the clients and what we did to keep ourselves on top of it and still deliver at a higher speed.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/working_constraints.png" alt="Working under Constraints." title="Working under Constraints. Image Source - https://www.saba.com/blog/how-to-master-employee-engagement-constraints"></p>

<blockquote><p><em>The issues discussed might or might not immediately relate to you, the important thing is your attitude towards such issues and finding ways around your constraints, keeping yourself productive on the long run.</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>No Build Deploy Pipeline</h3>

<p>When I joined the project, it amazed that we were still building/packaging the application from a local developer system and manually deploying this to the various environments (Dev, Test, UAT, and PROD).</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Whenever a release was to be made one of the developers was to pause his current work, switch to the appropriate branch for the release, make sure he had the latest code base, build with the correct configuration to generate a package.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>This might sound an outdated practice (as it did to me) but here I am at a client, in the year 2018 and it&rsquo;s still happening. What surprised me, even more, was that the team did have access to an <a href="https://octopus.com/">Octopus</a> server (backed by a <a href="https://jenkins.io/">Jenkins</a> build server) but since the <strong>deployment server did not have access to UAT/PROD servers</strong> they chose not to use it. You bet this was the first thing I was keen on fixing, as generating a release package from my local system would be the last thing that I want to do.</p>

<p>After a quick chat with the team, we decided on the below.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Set up build/deploy pipeline up to Test environment.</strong> This would allow seamless integration while we are developing features and get it out for testing. Since we had access till the Test environment, this was hardly an hours work to get it all working.</p></li>
<li><p>Since we did not have access to UAT/PROD and the process required us to hand over a deployment package to the concerned team, we <strong>set up a &lsquo;Packaging Project&rsquo; in Octopus.</strong> This project basically unzips the selected build package into our Dev environment server, applies the configuration transforms and zips up the folder into a deployment package. With this, we are now able to create a deployment package for any given build and for any environment. We are also having discussions to enable access to UAT/PROD servers for the deployment servers so that we can deploy automatically, all the way to production.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>No longer was the process dependent on a developer or a developer machine and was completely automated. For those reading this and in a similar situation but who does not have access to a build/deploy system like Jenkins/Octopus I would basically set up a simple script to pull down the source given a commit hash/branch/tfs label and perform a build and package independent of the working directory of the developer. This script could run on a shared server (if you have access to one) or worst on a developer&rsquo;s machine/VM. The fundamental thing that we are trying to achieve is to decouple it from the current working folder on a developer machine and the manual steps involved in generating a package. As long as you have an automated way to create a package irrespective of what tools/systems you use we should be safe and sound.</p>

<h3>Out of Sync SQL and Code Artifacts</h3>

<p>The application is heavily dependent on Stored Procedures for pulling/pushing data out of the SQL Server Database. Yes, you heard it right, Stored Procedures and ones with business logic in them, which is what makes it actually worse. Looking at how the Stored Procedures were maintained I could see that the team started off with good intentions using <a href="https://dbup.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">DbUp</a> but soon moved away from it. When I joined the process was to share SQL artifacts as attachments in the <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">Jira</a> story/bug. The Db Administrator (DBA) would then pull that out and manage them separately in a source control repository that was not the same as the application code base.</p>

<p>There was not much information on why this was the case, but the primary reason that they moved away from DbUp was that there was no visibility of the SQL scripts when running updates as it was an executable file that was the output of the DbUp project. Also, there were poor development/deployment practices that led to the ad-hoc execution of scripts in environments without actually updating the source control. This soon put the DBA out of control, and the only way to gain control back was to maintain it separately.</p>

<p>Again we decided to have a quick chat with the team along with the DBA on how to improve the current process, as it was getting harder to track application package versions and the associated scripts to go with that package.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>DbUp by default embeds the SQL artifacts into the executable which removes all visibility into the actual scripts. However, this behaviour is configurable using <a href="https://dbup.readthedocs.io/en/latest/more-info/script-providers/">ScriptProviders</a>. By using the <strong>FileSystemScriptProvider, we can specify the folder from which to load the SQL scripts</strong>. Configuring the msbuild to copy out all the folder files to the output and including them into the final package was an easy change. This provided the DBA with the actual SQL artifacts, and he could review them quickly. We also started a <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/code-review/">code review</a> process and began including the DBA for any changes related to SQL artifacts. This gave even more visibility to the DBA and helped catch issues right at the time of development.</p></li>
<li><p>With automated build/deploy till Test environment in place, we <strong>no longer had to make ad-hoc changes</strong> to the databases, and everything was pushed through the source control as it was faster and more comfortable.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>With this few tweaks we were now in a much better state, and there was a one to one trackability between source code and SQL artifacts. It all lived as part of one package, traceable all the way to the source code commit tag auto-generated by the build system.</p>

<h3>Not Invented Here Syndrome</h3>

<p>With the kind of restrictions you have seen till now, you can guess the approach towards third party services and off-the-shelf products. Most of the things are still done in-house (including trying to replicate a service bus). The problem with this approach is that there is a limit as to which you can go doing that after which you probably lose out on your team or the code takes over you where you just cannot maintain it. When starting out on a new project and when the code base is still small building your own mechanisms might seem to work well. But once past that point, you no longer want to continue down the path but invest in industry proven tools. These include logging servers, service-bus/queues (if you need one), email services (especially if you want to track and do statistics on top of the emails send out).</p>

<p>Biggest challenge introducing this is mostly not cost related (as there are a lot of really affordable services for every business)it&rsquo;s mostly the fear of unknown and lack of interest to venture out into unfamiliar territory. The reasons might vary for you, but try to understand the core reason that is hindering the change.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>One technique that worked to get over the fear of the unknown was to introduce this slowly into the system, one at a time, giving enough time for people to get used to the change.</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://getseq.net/">Seq</a> was one of the first things that we had proposed and long waiting in the wish list. The team was using <a href="https://serilog.net/">Serilog</a> to log, and all the logs were stored in SQL table making it really hard to query and monitor the logs. The infrastructure team did not want to install Seq as it was all new to them and were not sure about the additional task for managing a Seq instance. So we suggested to them to just have it on the development server and to get familiar with the application first. After a couple of days, the business was seeing a benefit with increased visibility into the logs and infrastructure team was also happy with the increased visibility into the logs. Even before a week, they were happy to install one for the test environment as well. At the time of writing we are looking at getting a Seq instance on the UAT server and soon to have a production instance as well. Getting the interested stakeholders to have a feel of the application and slowly introducing the change is a great way to get buy-in.</p>

<p>Now we are trying to push for a service bus!</p>

<h3>Build Server without NuGet access</h3>

<p>The build server we were using was in-house hosted, and the box that it ran did not have internet access. This meant that you cannot have any external package dependencies that can be pulled at build time. We chose to include the package references along with the source code, which is anyways what <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/checking-in-package-dependencies-into-source-control/">I tend to prefer more</a>. All our third-party libraries were pushed along with the source code repository, so the build machine had all the required dependencies and did not have to have internet connectivity to make a build.</p>

<p>Those are just a subset of the issues that we had to run into and bet you there were so many smaller ones. At times problems are not technical in nature, but more about communication and how effectively you are able to get all the people involved to get along with each other.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Any journey to advancement is about valuing the people around you, understanding them and taking them along with the change. It&rsquo;s a journey that the team needs to make together and not a solo one.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Different people have different experiences, pain points, concerns and targets to check off. So as a team you need to understand what works for everyone and come to a collective agreement. Just getting all of the concerned parties into a room and having a healthy discussion (mainly by not being prescriptive but descriptive of the issues that you are facing) solves most of the problems.</p>

<p>Do you work in a similar environment? What challenges do you face at work? Sound off in the comments!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Subresource Integrity (SRI)]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/subresource-integrity-sri/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/subresource-integrity-sri</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This article is part of a series of articles - <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/ok-i-have-got-https-what-next/">Ok I have got HTTPS! What Next?</a>. In this post, we explore how to use Subresource Integrity and the issues it solves.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Security/Subresource_Integrity">Subresource Integrity (SRI)</a> is a security feature that enables browsers to verify that files they fetch (for example, from a CDN) are delivered without unexpected manipulation. It works by allowing you to provide a cryptographic hash that a fetched file must match.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/sri.png" class="center" alt="Subresource integrity" /></p>

<p>Using the integrity attribute on <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/script">script</a> and <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/link">link</a> element enables browsers to verify externally linked files before loading them. The integrity attribute takes a base64-encoded hash prefixed the corresponding hash algorithm prefix(at present sha256,sha3384, sha512), as shown in the example below.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Integrity attribute as part of the script tag</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">script</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">src</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/redux/4.0.0/redux.js&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">integrity</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;sha256-KLkq+W1kKUA6iR5s5Xa/tdzU0yAmXNu7qIGKR/PBoUE=&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">crossorigin</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;anonymous&quot;</span> <span class="o">/&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Generating SRI Hash</h3>

<p>To generate the SRI hash for files that are accessible over a URL, you can use <a href="https://www.srihash.org/">srihash.org</a> or <a href="https://allyoucan.cloud/tools/srigenerator/">srigenerator</a> depending on what hash algorithm version you want. If you&rsquo;re going to generate it on your local files, you can use OpenSSL command-line tool (which should be part of your git bash shell if you are looking around for it, like I did)</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>openssl dgst -sha256 -binary FILENAME.js <span class="p">|</span> openssl base64 -A
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Third-Party Libraries</h3>

<p>For third-party libraries (js and CSS) referred via CDN, you can grab the script/link element along with the integrity attribute from the CDN sites. Here is an example below from <a href="https://cdnjs.com/">cdnjs</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/sri_redux.png" alt="Generate script tag along with SRI Hash" class="center" /></p>

<p>When referring third party libraries via CDN its <a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/CDNsFailButYourScriptsDontHaveToFallbackFromCDNToLocalJQuery.aspx">good to fall back to a local copy</a>. In cases where the CDN is unreachable or the integrity check fails it can fall back to a local copy. I chose to include the integrity attribute on the fallback copy as well.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">script</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">window</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">jQuery</span> <span class="o">||</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">write</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;&lt;script src=&quot;/javascripts/libs/jquery/jquery-2.0.3.min.js&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; integrity=&quot;sha256-ruuHogwePywKZ7bI1vHGGs7ScbBLhkNUcSSeRjhSUko=&quot;&gt;\x3C/script&gt;&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/script&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Application Specific Files</h3>

<p>For application specific javascript files, you need to generate the hash everytime you modify it. You could look at integrating this with your build pipeline to make it seamless. You can use the OpenSSL command line tool as shown above to generate the hash during your application build process.</p>

<h3>Inline JavaScript</h3>

<p><em>The <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/scripting.html#attr-script-integrity">integrity</a> attribute must not be specified when embedding a module script or when the src attribute is not specified.</em> This means that SRI cannot be used for inline javascript. Even though inline javascript should be avoided, there still are scenarios where you might use that or have dynamically generated javascript. In these cases, we can use <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/Content-Security-Policy/script-src">nonce</a> attribute on script tag and whitelist that nonce in the <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/http-content-security-policy-csp/">CSP Headers</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>nonce-&lt;base64-value></strong> <br/>
<em>A whitelist for specific inline scripts using a cryptographic nonce (number used once). The server must generate a unique nonce value each time it transmits a policy. It is critical to provide an unguessable nonce, as bypassing a resource’s policy is otherwise trivial. See unsafe inline script for example. Specifying nonce makes a modern browser ignore &lsquo;unsafe-inline&rsquo; which could still be set for older browsers without nonce support.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>For the jquery fallback above we need a nonce attribute since this is loaded inline.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Nonce attribute</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">script</span> <span class="nx">nonce</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;anF1ZXJ5ZmFsbGJhY2s=&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">window</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">jQuery</span> <span class="o">||</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">write</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;&lt;script src=&quot;/javascripts/libs/jquery/jquery-2.0.3.min.js&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; integrity=&quot;sha256-ruuHogwePywKZ7bI1vHGGs7ScbBLhkNUcSSeRjhSUko=&quot;&gt;\x3C/script&gt;&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/script&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>We can then specify this nonce on the CSP headers for the script-src. The nonce value can be anything that is base64 encoded.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Web.config CSP header</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;add</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;Content-Security-Policy&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;default-src</span> <span class="err">&#39;self&#39;;script-src</span> <span class="err">c.disquscdn.com</span> <span class="err">&#39;self&#39;</span> <span class="err">&#39;</span><span class="na">nonce-anF1ZXJ5ZmFsbGJhY2s=</span><span class="s">&#39; &#39;</span><span class="err">nonce-ZGlzcXVzc2NyaXB0&#39;;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Using nonce allows us to get away with having an inline script. However, this should be avoided if possible. As you may have noticed, by having a nonce on the attribute does not validate the script contents of the associated tag. It executes anything that is within that tag. So if you have dynamic content within the script block, this can be used to your disadvantage by attackers. So use it only if it&rsquo;s absolutely necessary. However, having the nonce attribute for those cases is better so that you can limit inline javascript to those specific script tags.</p>

<h3>Browser Support</h3>

<p><a href="https://caniuse.com/#search=sri">Check if</a> your browser supports Subresource Integrity. Compared to a while back most of the browsers now support SRI.</p>

<p><a href="https://caniuse.com/#search=sri">
  <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/sri_browser.png" alt="SRI Browser Support" class="center" />
</a></p>

<p>Using SRI, we can make sure that the dependencies that we have are loaded are as expected and not modified in flight or at source by a malicious attacker. There is always a risk that you need to be willing to take when including external dependencies as they could be already having a threat embedded at the time of hash generation. For popular libraries, this is less likely. For those unpopular ones, it&rsquo;s always a good idea to take a quick look at the code to ensure it&rsquo;s not malicious. Using some tools to assist you with this is also a good idea, which we will look into in a separate article.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enable Cross-Origin Requests (CORS) in ASP.Net Web API Using CorsOptions]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/enable-cross-origin-requests-cors-in-asp-dot-net-web-api-using-corsoptions/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/enable-cross-origin-requests-cors-in-asp-dot-net-web-api-using-corsoptions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was setting up an API at one of the client&rsquo;s place recently and found that currently, they allow any origin to hit their API by setting the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn450212(v=vs.113).aspx">CorsOptions.AllowAll</a> options. In this post, we will look at how to set the CORS options and restrict it to only the domains that you want your API to be accessed from.</p>

<h3>What is Cross-Origin Resource Sharing (CORS)</h3>

<p>Cross-Origin Resource Sharing is a way to relax the browsers <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Security/Same-origin_policy">Same-Origin Policy</a> whereby to tell a browser to let a web application running at one origin (domain) have permission to access selected resources from a server at a different origin. By specifying the CORS header you instruct the browser to allow all allowed domains to access your resource. Most of the time for the API endpoints you want to be explicit on the hosts that can access your API. By setting CORS, you are only restricting/allowing cross-domain access originating from a browser. <strong>Setting CORS should not be mistaken for a Security feature</strong> whereby you are restricting access from any other sources. Any requests that are formed outside of the browser like using Postman, Fiddler, etc. can still make to your API and you need appropriate authorization/authentication to make sure you are not exposing data to unintended people.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/cors.png" alt="Cross-Origin Request" class="center" ></p>

<h3>Enabling in Web API</h3>

<p>In Web API there are multiple ways that you can set CORS.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/Microsoft.Owin.Cors/">Microsoft.Owin.Cors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/Microsoft.AspNet.WebApi.Cors">Microsoft.AspNet.WebApi.Cors</a><br/>
<em>This adds <em>System.Web.Http.Cors.dll</em> assembly to your project so can be a bit of confusion if you are looking around for the DLL in the solution</em></li>
</ul>


<p>In the below snippet I am using the <em>Microsoft.Owin.Cors</em> pipeline to setup CORS for the API. The code first reads the application configuration file to get a list of semicolon (;) separated hostnames which are added to the list of allowed origins in the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/previous-versions/aspnet/web-frameworks/dn726408(v=vs.118)">CorsPolicy</a>. By setting the corsOptions with <em>UseCors</em> extension method, the policy gets applied to all the requests coming through the website.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='csharp'><span class='line'><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">allowedOriginsConfig</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">ConfigurationManager</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">AppSettings</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s">&quot;origins&quot;</span><span class="p">];</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">allowedOrigins</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">allowedOriginsConfig</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Split</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">new</span><span class="p">[]</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s">&quot;;&quot;</span> <span class="p">},</span> <span class="n">StringSplitOptions</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">RemoveEmptyEntries</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">corsPolicy</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="n">CorsPolicy</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">AllowAnyHeader</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">true</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">AllowAnyMethod</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">true</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">SupportsCredentials</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">true</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">foreach</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">origin</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="n">allowedOrigins</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">corsPolicy</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Origins</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Add</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">origin</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">policyProvider</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="n">CorsPolicyProvider</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">PolicyResolver</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">context</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">=&gt;</span> <span class="n">Task</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">FromResult</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">corsPolicy</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">corsOptions</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="n">CorsOptions</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">PolicyProvider</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">policyProvider</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">UseCors</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">corsOptions</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Setting Multiple CORS Policy</h3>

<p>If you want to have different CORS policies based on different Controllers/route path, you can use the <em>Map</em> function to set up the CorsOptions for specific route paths. In the below example we apply a different CorsOptions to all routes that match <em>&lsquo;/api/SpecificController&rsquo;</em> and defaults to another for all other requests.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='csharp'><span class='line'><span class="n">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Map</span><span class="p">(</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="s">&quot;/api/SpecificController&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">appbuilder</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">=&gt;</span> <span class="n">appbuilder</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">UseCors</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">corsOptions2</span><span class="p">));</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">...</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">UseCors</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">corsOptions1</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>CORS ≠ Security</h3>

<p>CORS is a way to relax the Cross-Origin Policy and in no way should be seen as a security feature. By setting CORS headers what we are saying is to allow all the additional domains in the headers also to be able to access the resource from a browser environment. However setting this, does not restrict access to your API&rsquo;s from other sources like Postman, Fiddler or from any non-browser environments. Even within browser environments, older versions of Flash allows modifying and spoofing of request headers. Ensure that you are using CORS for the correct reasons and not assume that it is providing you security against unauthorized access.</p>

<p>Hope this allows you to setup CORS on your API&rsquo;s!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTTP Content Security Policy (CSP)]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/http-content-security-policy-csp/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/http-content-security-policy-csp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This article is part of a series of articles - <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/ok-i-have-got-https-what-next/">Ok I have got HTTPS! What Next?</a>. In this post, we explore how to use HSTS security header and the issues it solves.</em></p>

<p>Content Security Policy (CSP) is a security response header or a <meta> element that instructs the browser, sources of information that it should trust for our website. A browser that supports CSP&rsquo;s then treats this list specified as a whitelist and only allows resources to be loaded only for those sources. CSP&rsquo;s allow you to specify source locations for a variety of resource types which are referred to as <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/Fetch_directive">fetch directives</a>(e.g. _script-src, img-src,style-src* etc).</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/content-security-policy.png" alt="Content Security Policy"  class="center" /></p>

<p>CSP is an added layer of security that helps to detect and mitigate certain types of attacks, including Cross Site Scripting (XSS) and data injection attacks. These attacks are used for everything from data theft to site defacement or distribution of malware.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Example</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='text'><span class='line'>Content-Security-Policy: default-src &#39;self&#39; *.rahulpnath.com
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Setting CSP Headers</h3>

<p><strong>Web Server Configuration</strong></p>

<p>CSP&rsquo;s can be set via the configuration file of your web server host if you want to specify it as part of the header. In my case I use Azure Web App, so all I need to do is add in a web.config file to my root with the header values. Below is an example which specified CSP headers (including Report Only) and <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/http-strict-transport-security-sts-or-hsts/">STS headers</a>.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Web.config Sample</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;configuration&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;system.webServer&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;httpProtocol&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;customHeaders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;Content-Security-Policy&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;upgrade-insecure-requests;&quot;</span><span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;Content-Security-Policy-Report-Only&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;default-src &#39;none&#39;;report-uri https://rahulpnath.report-uri.com/r/d/csp/reportOnly&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;Strict-Transport-Security&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;max-age=31536000; includeSubDomains; preload&quot;</span><span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;/customHeaders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;/httpProtocol&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    ...
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><strong>Using Fiddler</strong></p>

<p>However if all you want is to play around with the CSP header and don&rsquo;t have access to your Web server or the configuration file, you can still test these headers. You can inject in the headers into the response using a <a href="blog/fiddler-free-web-debugging-proxy/">Web Proxy like Fiddler</a></p>

<p>To modify the request/response in-flight you can use one of the most powerful feature in Fiddler - <a href="https://www.telerik.com/blogs/understanding-fiddlerscript">Fiddler Script</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Fiddler Script allows you to enhance Fiddler’s UI, add new features, and modify requests and responses “on the fly” to introduce any behavior you’d like.</p></blockquote>

<p>Using the below script, we can inject &lsquo;Content-Security-Policy&rsquo; header whenever the request matches a specific criteria.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/https_csp_fiddler_script.png" alt="Fiddler Script to update CSP"  class="center" /></p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Fiddler Script - Inject CSP Header</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">oSession</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">HostnameIs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;rahulpnath.com&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">oSession</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">oResponse</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">headers</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s2">&quot;Content-Security-Policy&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="s2">&quot;default-src &#39;none&#39;; img-src &#39;self&#39;;script-src &#39;self&#39;;style-src &#39;self&#39;&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>By injecting these headers, we can play around with the CSP headers for the webiste without affecting other users. Once you have the CSP rules that cater to your site you can commit this to the actual website. Even with all the CSP headers set, you can additionally set the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/Content-Security-Policy/report-to">report-to</a> (or deprecated <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/Content-Security-Policy/report-uri">report-uri</a>) directive on the policy to capture any policies that you may have missed.</p>

<h3>Content-Security-Policy-Report-Only</h3>

<p>The <em>Content-Security-Policy_Report-Only</em> header allows to test the header settings without any impact and also to capture any CSP headers that you might have missed on your website. The browser uses this for reporting purposes only and does not enforce the policies. We can specify a report endpoint to which the browser will send any CSP violations as a JSON object.</p>

<p>Below is an example of a CSP violation POST request send from the browser to the report URL that I had specified for this blog. I am using an endpoint from the <a href="https://report-uri.com/">Report URI</a> service (more on this later)</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Example</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='json'><span class='line'><span class="err">POST</span> <span class="err">https://rahulpnath.report-uri.com/r/d/csp/reportOnly</span> <span class="err">HTTP/</span><span class="mf">1.1</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&quot;csp-report&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;document-uri&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;https://www.rahulpnath.com/&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;referrer&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;violated-directive&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;img-src&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;effective-directive&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;img-src&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;original-policy&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;default-src &#39;none&#39;;report-uri https://rahulpnath.report-uri.com/r/d/csp/reportOnly&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;disposition&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;report&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;blocked-uri&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;https://www.rahulpnath.com/apple-touch-icon-120x120.png&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;line-number&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">29</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;source-file&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;https://www.rahulpnath.com/&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;status-code&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nt">&quot;script-sample&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Generating CSP Policies</h3>

<p>Coming up with the CSP policies for your site can be a bit tricky as there are a lot of options and directives involved. Your site might also be pulling in dependencies from a variety of sources. Setting CSP policies is also an excellent time to review your application dependencies and manage them correctly. For e.g., if you have a javascript file from an untrusted source, etc. There are a few ways by which you can go about generating CSP policies. Below are two ways I found useful and easy to get started.</p>

<p><strong>Using Fiddler</strong></p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/david-risney/CSP-Fiddler-Extension">CSP Fiddler Extension</a> is a Fiddler extension that helps you produce a strong CSP for a web page (or website). Install the extension and with Fiddler running navigate to your web pages using a browser that supports CSP.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The extension adds mock Content-Security-Policy-Report-Only headers to servers&#8217; responses and uses the report-uri <a href="https://fiddlercsp.deletethis.net/unsafe-inline.">https://fiddlercsp.deletethis.net/unsafe-inline.</a> The extension then listens to the specified report-uri and generates a CSP based on the gathered information</em></p></blockquote>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/https_csp_fiddler_rule_collector.png" class="center" alt="Fiddler CSP Rule Collector" /></p>

<p><strong>Using Report URI</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://report-uri.com/">ReportURI</a> is a real-time security reporting tool which can be used to collect various metrics about your website. One of the features it provides is giving a nice little wizard interface for creating your CSP headers. <a href="https://report-uri.com/#prices">Pricing</a> is usage based and provides the first 10000 reports of the month free (which is what I am using for this blog).</p>

<p>ReportURI gives a dashboard summarizing the various stats of your site and also provides features to explore these in detail.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/csp_report_uri_dashboard.png" alt="Report Uri Dashboard" class="center" /></p>

<p>One of the cool features is the <a href="https://scotthelme.co.uk/report-uri-csp-wizard/">CSP Wizard</a> which as the name suggests, provides a wizard-like UI to build out CSP&rsquo;s for the site. The websites need to be configured to report CSP errors to a specific endpoint on your ReportURI endpoint (as shown below). The header value can be set either on CSP header or the Report Only header.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>You can find your report URL from the Setup tab on Report URI. Make sure you use the URL under the options Report Type: CSP and Report Disposition: <strong>Wizard</strong></em></p></blockquote>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='text'><span class='line'>Content-Security-Policy-Report-Only: default-src &#39;none&#39;;report-uri https://&lt;subdomain&gt;.report-uri.com/r/d/csp/wizard
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Once all configured and reports start coming in you can use the Wizard to pick and choose what sources you need to whitelist for your website. You might see a lot of unwanted sources and entries in the wizard as it just reflects what is reported to it. You need to filter it out manually and build the list.</p>

<p>Once you have the CSP&rsquo;s set you can check out if your site does the Harlem Shake by pressing F12 and running the below script. Though this is not any sort of test, it is a fun exercise to do.</p>

<div class="alert alert-warning">
<b>Copy pasting scripts from unknown source is not at all recommended and is one of the most powerful ways that an attacker can get access to your account.</b> Having a well defined CSP prevents such script attacks as well on your sites. Don&#8217;t be suprised if your banking site also shakes to the tune of the script below. 
</div>


<p><em>That said do give the below script a try! I did go through the code pasted below and it is not malicious. All it does modify your dom elements and plays a music. The original source is available below but I do not control it and it could have change since the time of writing.</em></p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Harlem Shake - F12 on Browser tab and run below script (Check your Volume)</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="c1">//Source: http://pastebin.com/aJna4paJ</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">javascript</span><span class="o">:</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">c</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">createElement</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;link&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">setAttribute</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;type&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s2">&quot;text/css&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">setAttribute</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;rel&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s2">&quot;stylesheet&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">setAttribute</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;href&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">f</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">setAttribute</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;class&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">l</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">appendChild</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">)}</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">h</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">getElementsByClassName</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">l</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">++</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">removeChild</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="p">])}}</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">p</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">createElement</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;div&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">setAttribute</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;class&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">a</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">appendChild</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="nx">setTimeout</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">removeChild</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">)},</span><span class="mi">100</span><span class="p">)}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="k">return</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nx">height</span><span class="o">:</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">offsetHeight</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">width</span><span class="o">:</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">offsetWidth</span><span class="p">}}</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">v</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">s</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">height</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">height</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">n</span><span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">width</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">width</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">r</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">m</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">n</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">while</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">!!</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="nx">n</span><span class="o">+=</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">offsetTop</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">offsetParent</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">n</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">g</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">documentElement</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">!!</span><span class="nb">window</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">innerWidth</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="k">return</span> <span class="nb">window</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">innerHeight</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="k">else</span> <span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">&amp;&amp;!</span><span class="nb">isNaN</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">clientHeight</span><span class="p">)){</span><span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">clientHeight</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">y</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">window</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">pageYOffset</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="k">return</span> <span class="nb">window</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">pageYOffset</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="k">return</span> <span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">max</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">documentElement</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">scrollTop</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">scrollTop</span><span class="p">)}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">E</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">m</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">&gt;=</span><span class="nx">w</span><span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">&lt;=</span><span class="nx">b</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">w</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">S</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">createElement</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;audio&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">setAttribute</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;class&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">l</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">src</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">loop</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="kc">false</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">addEventListener</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;canplay&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="nx">setTimeout</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="nx">x</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">k</span><span class="p">)},</span><span class="mi">500</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">setTimeout</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="nx">N</span><span class="p">();</span><span class="nx">p</span><span class="p">();</span><span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">O</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">++</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="nx">T</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">O</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">])}},</span><span class="mi">15500</span><span class="p">)},</span><span class="kc">true</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">addEventListener</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;ended&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="nx">N</span><span class="p">();</span><span class="nx">h</span><span class="p">()},</span><span class="kc">true</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">innerHTML</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot; &lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, it is because your browser does not support the audio element. We recommend that you get a new browser.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">appendChild</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">play</span><span class="p">()}</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">x</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">className</span><span class="o">+=</span><span class="s2">&quot; &quot;</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="s2">&quot; &quot;</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">o</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">T</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">className</span><span class="o">+=</span><span class="s2">&quot; &quot;</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="s2">&quot; &quot;</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">floor</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">random</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="nx">u</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">)]}</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">N</span><span class="p">(){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">getElementsByClassName</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">new</span> <span class="nb">RegExp</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;\\b&quot;</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="s2">&quot;\\b&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">n</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">n</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">;){</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">n</span><span class="p">].</span><span class="nx">className</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">n</span><span class="p">].</span><span class="nx">className</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">replace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">t</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s2">&quot;&quot;</span><span class="p">)}}</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">e</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">30</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">t</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">30</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">n</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">350</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">r</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">350</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">i</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;//s3.amazonaws.com/moovweb-marketing/playground/harlem-shake.mp3&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">s</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;mw-harlem_shake_me&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">o</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;im_first&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">u</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s2">&quot;im_drunk&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s2">&quot;im_baked&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s2">&quot;im_trippin&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s2">&quot;im_blown&quot;</span><span class="p">];</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">a</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;mw-strobe_light&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">f</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;//s3.amazonaws.com/moovweb-marketing/playground/harlem-shake-style.css&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">l</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;mw_added_css&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">b</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">g</span><span class="p">();</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">w</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">y</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">C</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">getElementsByTagName</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;*&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">k</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">L</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">L</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">C</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">L</span><span class="o">++</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">A</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">C</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">L</span><span class="p">];</span><span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">v</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">A</span><span class="p">)){</span><span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">E</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">A</span><span class="p">)){</span><span class="nx">k</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">A</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="k">break</span><span class="p">}}}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">A</span><span class="o">===</span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="nx">console</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">warn</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;Could not find a node of the right size. Please try a different page.&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="k">return</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="nx">c</span><span class="p">();</span><span class="nx">S</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">O</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">[];</span><span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">L</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">L</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">C</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">L</span><span class="o">++</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">A</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">C</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">L</span><span class="p">];</span><span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">v</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">A</span><span class="p">)){</span><span class="nx">O</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">push</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">A</span><span class="p">)}}})()</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>I am still playing around with the CSP headers for this blog and currently testing it out using the ReportOnly header along with ReportURI. Hope this helps you to start putting the correct CSP headers for your site as well!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTTP Strict Transport Security (STS or HSTS)]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/http-strict-transport-security-sts-or-hsts/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/http-strict-transport-security-sts-or-hsts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This article is part of a series of articles - <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/ok-i-have-got-https-what-next/">Ok I have got HTTPS! What Next?</a>. In this post, we explore how to use HSTS security header and the issues it solves.</em></p>

<p>When you enter a domain name in the browser without specifying the protocol (HTTP or HTTPS) the browser by default sends the first request over HTTP. For a server that supports only HTTPS, when it sees such a request, it redirects the request over to HTTPS. The server responds to the client with a <em>302 Redirect</em>, redirecting the client to HTTPS, from which on the browser starts requesting over HTTPS. As you can see here, the very first request that the client makes is over an insecure channel (HTTP), so is also vulnerable to attacks. You could be prone to man-in-the-middle (MITM) attack, and someone could spoof that request and point you to a different site, inject malicious scripts, etc. <strong>The first insecure HTTP request is made everytime you enter the domain name in the browser or make an explicit call over HTTP.</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/hsts_tofu.png" alt="Trust on First Use" class="center"></p>

<blockquote><p><em>The HTTP <strong>Strict-Transport-Security</strong> response header (often abbreviated as HSTS) lets a website tell browsers that it should only be accessed using HTTPS, instead of using HTTP</em></p></blockquote>

<p>By using the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/Strict-Transport-Security">HTTP Strict Transport Security</a> (HSTS) header on your response headers, you are instructing the browser to make calls over HTTPS instead of HTTP for your site.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Syntax</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='text'><span class='line'>Strict-Transport-Security: max-age=&lt;expire-time&gt;
</span><span class='line'>Strict-Transport-Security: max-age=&lt;expire-time&gt;; includeSubDomains
</span><span class='line'>Strict-Transport-Security: max-age=&lt;expire-time&gt;; preload
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>There are a few directives that you can set on the header which determines how the browser uses the header. By just setting the header with a <em>max-age</em> (required) directive, you tell the browser the <em>time in seconds that the browser should remember that a site is only to be accessed using HTTPS</em>. By default, the setting affects only the current subdomain. Additionally, you can set the <em>includeSubDomains</em> directive to apply this rule to all subdomain of the site. <strong>Before including all subdomains make sure those are served over HTTPS as well so that you do end up blocking your other sites on the same domain (if any).</strong></p>

<p>As you can see with the HSTS header specified, the browser now only makes one insecure request (the one that it makes everytime the cache expires or the very first request). Once it has established a successful connection with the server, all further requests are over HTTPS for the <em>max_age</em> (cache expiry) set. <strong>With the HSTS header the surface area of the attack gets reduced to just one request as compared to all initial requests going over HTTP (when we did not have the HSTS header).</strong></p>

<p>To verify the HSTS header setting has been applied for your website open your browser in Incognito/In-Private browsing mode. It is to make sure that the browser acts as if it is seeing the site for the very first time (as HSTS header caches do not get shared across regular/incognito sessions)</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The HSTS header settings do not get shared across between the regular and incognito browsing session (at least in Chrome and think this is the same for other browsers as well).</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Open the Developer tools window and monitor the Network requests made by the browser. Request your website over HTTP (either explicitly or just entering the domain name) in this case my blog <a href="http://rahulpnath.com">http://rahulpnath.com</a>. As you can see the very first request go over HTTP and the server returns a <em>301 Moved Permanently</em> status with the https version of the site. For any subsequent requests over HTTP, the browser returns a <em>307 Internal Redirect</em>. This redirect happens within the boundary of your browser and redirects to the HTTPS site. You can use <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/fiddler-free-web-debugging-proxy/">Fiddler</a> to verify that this request does not cross the browser boundary. (The request does not get to Fiddler.)</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/hsts_without_preload.png" alt="HSTS without preload" class ="center" /></p>

<p>We could still argue that there is still a potential threat with the very first request sent over HTTP which is still vulnerable to MITM attack. To solve that we can use the <em>preload</em> directive and submit out domain to an <a href="https://hstspreload.org/">HSTS Preload list</a>, which when successfully added, propagates to the source code of Browsers.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Most major browsers (Chrome, Firefox, Opera, Safari, IE 11 and Edge) also have HSTS preload lists based on the Chrome list.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>The Browsers hardcode these domains from the preload approved list into their source code (e.g., here is <a href="https://chromium.googlesource.com/chromium/src/net/+/master/http/transport_security_state_static.json">Chrome&rsquo;s list</a>) and gets shipped with their releases. You can check for the preloaded site in the browser as well. Again for chrome navigate to <em>chrome://net-internals/#hsts</em> and query for the HSTS domain.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/hsts_preload_static_json.png" alt="HSTS preloaded site hardcoded" class ="center" /></p>

<p>If STS is not set at all or you have not made the very first request to the server (when preload is false) querying for the domain returns &lsquo;Not Found.&rsquo; Below are two variations that you can see depending on whether you have <em>preload</em> set or not. The <em>dynamic_*_*</em> indicates that STS is set after the first load of the site and the <em>static_*_*</em> indicates that it is set from the preload list.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>If you are wondering why this blog does not have _static_*_*</em> set it is because the preload list that it is part of has not yet made into a stable version of Chrome. However, the preload site does show that it is currently preloaded (probably in a beta version at the time of writing)._</p></blockquote>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/chrome_hsts_preload.png" alt="Verifying HSTS preload" class ="center" /></p>

<p>With the preload set and your domain hardcoded into the preload list and available as part of the browser version you are on, any request made over HTTP is redirected internally (307) to HTTPS without even going to the server. It means <strong>we have entirely got rid of the first untrusted HTTP request.</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/hsts_internal_redirect_scott.png" alt="HSTS preload request flow" class ="center" /></p>

<p>Have you already got HSTS set on your site?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ok I Have Got HTTPS! What Next?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/ok-i-have-got-https-what-next/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/ok-i-have-got-https-what-next</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Security is of more and more a concern these days and we <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/https-for-free-and-why-you-should-care/">saw why it&rsquo;s important to move on to HTTPs</a>. Hope you have already moved on to HTTPS, If not right now is a perfect time - this is one of the things that you should not be putting off for later. Also, do check out the <a href="https://httpsiseasy.com/">HTTPS is Easy</a> series by Troy Hunt on how simple it is to get onboard with HTTPS. Most of the things mentioned here, I started exploring after getting introduced to it by <a href="https://scotthelme.co.uk/">Scott Helme</a> and <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/">Troy Hunt</a> at the <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/ndc-security-2018-overview-and-key-takeaways/">NDC Security conference</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://securityheaders.com/?q=rahulpnath.com&followRedirects=on">
    <img
        src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/https_next.png"
        alt="Security Report Summary from SecurityHeaders.com"
        class="center" />
</a></p>

<p>Once you have moved on to HTTPS you might be thinking is that it? Or is there still more that I need to be doing? An excellent place to start is <a href="https://securityheaders.com/">SecurityHeaders.com</a>, which analyses security headers on your website and provides a rating score for the site. The site also gives a short description of the various headers, appropriate links to explore more about them. Some of the headers are easy to add and immediately provides added security to your website.</p>

<div class="alert alert-warning">
Just because you have an A+ Rating (or a good rating) does not mean that your site is not vulnerable to any attacks. These are just some guidelines to help you along the way to tighten up your website security.
</div>


<blockquote><p><em>I have been trying to walk the talk here - implementing these headers one by one on this blog as and when I am writing this</em></p></blockquote>

<p>In this post will walk through some of the headers that I added to this blog. I am planning to write this as a multi-series article, with each article specific to a header/other feature, why I added it and how I went about adding and verifying it.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/http-strict-transport-security-sts-or-hsts">HTTP Strict-Transport-Security (HSTS/STS)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/http-content-security-policy-csp/">Content-Security-Policy (CSP)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/subresource-integrity-sri/">Subresource Integrity</a></li>
<li>Development Tools</li>
</ul>


<p>I will be updating the links to the relevant posts here as I publish them and will add to the list as and when I come across new topics. One of the tricky thing with security is that very often something new comes up. The best we can do is to proactively do things that we can do to support and protect ourselves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Kumon Books - Creative Workbooks]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/kumon-books-creative-workbooks/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/kumon-books-creative-workbooks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s always hard to keep young minds engaged and fresh. As a parent, it is good to have a few different options to keep your child engaged and also at the same time help them learn. Activity books are a great way of keeping kids involved and help them develop the skills that they need in their lives.</p>

<p><a href="http://kumonbooks.com/">Kumon Books</a> offer a wide variety of books for different <a href="http://kumonbooks.com/books/by-grade/">age groups</a> and <a href="http://kumonbooks.com/books/by-subject/basic/">subjects</a>. The books follow a progression and are meant to be used in the sequence to helps kids progress by building on previous skills. The <a href="http://kumonbooks.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2015-Workbook-Chart.pdf">workbook chart</a> helps if you are new to Kumon Books. You can also choose by your <a href="http://kumonbooks.com/books/by-grade/">kids age</a> if you don&rsquo;t find the chart useful.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/kumon_books.png" alt="center" alt="Kumon Books" /></p>

<p>The books cover a variety of activities like coloring, cutting paper, folding, pasting stickers, reading, writing, maths, etc. Each book easily introduces the concept and makes your child repeat it over and over again until it becomes clear to them before moving to advanced skills. Activity books like cutting, folding, paste, etc. are intended to be used once but for the other ones like writing, reading, math, etc. you can get your child to use a pencil and erase it off if you want them to refresh on the skills sometimes.</p>

<p>We have got books across most of the activities for Gautham and found it valuable. The books have helped him learn to read, write, cut, paint, etc. and highly recommend to others. These books also give an excellent way to interact with your child and help him learn and grow.</p>

<p>Your local bookstore or online stores should be having these books. Google should be of help otherwise. Hope you find it useful!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Your Postman API Specs]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/manage-your-postman-api-specs/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/manage-your-postman-api-specs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the previous post, we explored how to use <a href="Automated%20API%20Testing%20Using%20Postman%20Collection%20Runner">Postman for testing API endpoints</a>. Postman is an excellent tool to manage API specs as well, so that you can try API requests individually to see how things are working. It also acts as documentation for all your API endpoints and serves as a good starting point for someone new to the team. When it comes to managing the API specs for your application, there are a few options that we have and let&rsquo;s explore what they are.</p>

<h3>Organizing API Specs</h3>

<p>Postman supports the concept of <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/docs/v6/postman/collections/creating_collections">Collections</a>, which are nothing but a Folder to group of saved API requests/Specs. Collections support nesting which means you can add Folders within a collection to further group them. As you can see below the <em>MyApplication</em> and <em>Postman Echo</em> are collections, and there are subfolders inside them which in turn contains API requests. The multi-level hierarchy helps you to organize your requests the way you want to.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/postman_collections.png" alt="Postman Collections" class ="center"></p>

<h3>Sharing API Specs</h3>

<p>Any Collection that you create in Postman is automatically synced to Postman Cloud if you are logged in with an account. It allows you to share collections through a link. With <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/pricing">paid version of Postman</a> you get to create <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/workspaces">team workspaces</a>, which means a team can collaborate on the shared versions. It allows easy sharing of specs across your team and manages them in a centralized place.</p>

<p>However, if you are not logged in or don&rsquo;t have a paid version of Postman, you can maintain the specs along with your Source Code. Postman allows you to <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/docs/v6/postman/collections/sharing_collections#sharing-as-a-file">export Collections and share specs as a JSON file</a>. You can then check this file into your source code repository. Other team members can Import the exported file to get the latest specs. The only disadvantage with this is that you need to make sure to export/import every time you/other team members make a change to the JSON file. However, I have seen this approach work well in teams and one way we made sure that the JSON file was up to date is to have to update the API spec as a Work Item and which required to be <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/code-review/">peer reviewed</a>(through Pull Requests)</p>

<h3>Managing Environments</h3>

<p>Typically any application/API would be deployed to multiple environments (like localhost, Development, Testing, Production, etc.) and you would want to switch between these environments to test your API endpoints seamlessly. Postman makes this easy by using the <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/docs/v6/postman/environments_and_globals/manage_environments">Environment Feature</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/postman_environment.png" alt="Postman Environment" class="center" /></p>

<p>Again as with Collections, Environments are also synced to Postman Cloud when you are logged in. It makes all your environments available to all your team seamlessly. However, if you are not logged in you can again export the environments as a JSON file and then share that out of band (in a secure manner as this might have sensitive information like tokens, keys, etc.) with your team.</p>

<h3>Publishing API Specs</h3>

<p>Postman allows you to <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/docs/v6/postman/api_documentation/publishing_public_docs">publish API specs</a> (even to a custom URL), which can act like your API Documentation. You can publish it per environments and also easily execute them. Publishing is available only if you log in to an account as it requires the API Specs and environment details in the first place.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/postman_published.png" alt="Postman Published" class="center" /></p>

<h3>Security Considerations</h3>

<p>When using the sync feature of Postman (logged in to the application with Postman account), it is <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/docs/v6/postman_for_publishers/run_button/security">recommended</a> that you do not have any sensitive information (like passwords/tokens) as part of the API request spec/Collection. These should be extracted out as Environment variables and stored as part of the appropriate environment.</p>

<p>If you are logged in, all the data that you add to it is automatically synced, which means it will be living in Postman&rsquo;s cloud server. This might not be a desirable option for every company but looks like there is no option to turn sync off at the Collection level. The only way to not sync collections is to not log into an account in Postman.</p>

<div class="alert alert-warning">
    <i>
    If you are logged into Postman then any collection that you create is automatically synced to Postman server. Only way to <a href="https://support.getpostman.com/hc/en-us/articles/203492852-How-do-I-disable-Sync-">prevent sync</a> is not to log in
    </i>
</div>


<p>We have seen the options by which you can share API collections and environments amongst your team even if you are logged in. However, one thing to be aware of is if any of your team members are logged into Postman and imports a collection shared via Repository/out of band methods, it will be synced to Postman server. So at the organization/team level, you would need ways to prevent this from happening if it is essential for you. Best is to have your API&rsquo;s designed in such a way that you do not have to expose such sensitive information, which anyways is a better practice.</p>

<p>Hope this allows to manage your API specs better!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automated API Testing Using Postman Collection Runner]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/automated-api-testing-using-postman-collection-runner/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/automated-api-testing-using-postman-collection-runner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back we looked at how we can use <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/postman-chaining-requests-to-speed-up-manual-api-tests/">Postman to chain multiple requests to speed up out Manual API Testing</a>. For those who are not familiar with <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/">Postman</a>, it is an application that assists in API testing and development, which I see as sitting a level top of a tool like <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/fiddler-free-web-debugging-proxy/">Fiddler</a>.</p>

<p>In this post, we will see how we can use Postman to test some basic CRUD operations over an API using a feature called <a href="http://blog.getpostman.com/2016/11/22/postmans-new-collection-runner/">Postman Runner</a>. Using this still involves some manual intervention. However, we can automate them using a combination of different tools.</p>

<h3>Setting Up the API</h3>

<p>To start with I create a simple API endpoint using the out of the box Web API project from Visual Studio 2017. It is a Values Controller which stores key-value pairs to which you can send GET, POST, DELETE requests. Below is the API implementation. It is a simple in-memory implementation and does not use any persistent store. However, the tests would not change much even if the store was to be persistent. The importance here is not in the implementation of the API, but how you can use Postman to add some quick tests.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>ValuesController</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='csharp'><span class='line'><span class="k">public</span> <span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">ValuesController</span> <span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">ApiController</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">static</span> <span class="n">Dictionary</span><span class="p">&lt;</span><span class="kt">int</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">string</span><span class="p">&gt;</span> <span class="n">values</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="n">Dictionary</span><span class="p">&lt;</span><span class="kt">int</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">string</span><span class="p">&gt;();</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">public</span> <span class="n">IEnumerable</span><span class="p">&lt;</span><span class="kt">string</span><span class="p">&gt;</span> <span class="n">Get</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">values</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Values</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">public</span> <span class="n">IHttpActionResult</span> <span class="nf">Get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">id</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">values</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ContainsKey</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nf">Ok</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">values</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">]);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nf">NotFound</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">public</span> <span class="n">IHttpActionResult</span> <span class="nf">Post</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">FromBody</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="kt">string</span> <span class="k">value</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">values</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">value</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nf">Ok</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">public</span> <span class="n">IHttpActionResult</span> <span class="nf">Delete</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">id</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(!</span><span class="n">values</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ContainsKey</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nf">NotFound</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">values</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Remove</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nf">Ok</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Setting Up Postman</h3>

<p>To start with we will create a new Collection in Postman to hold our tests for the Values Controller - I have named it &lsquo;<em>Values CRUD - Test</em>&rsquo;. The collection is a container for all the API requests that we are going to write. First, we will add all the request definitions into postman which we can later reorder for the tests.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/postman_request.png" alt="Postman Request" class="center" /></p>

<blockquote><p>The <em><strong>/</strong></em> in the URL are parameters defined as part of the selected Environment. Environments in Postman allow you to switch between different application environments like Development, Test, Production. You can configure different values for each environment and Postman will send the requests as per the configuration.</p></blockquote>

<p>Below are the environment variables for my local environment. You can define as many environments as you want and switch between them.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/postman_environment.png" alt="Postman Environment" class="center" /></p>

<p>Now that I have all the request definitions for the API added let&rsquo;s add some tests to verify our API functionality.</p>

<h3>Writing The First Test</h3>

<p>Postman allows executing scripts before and after running API requests. We did see this in the <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/postman-chaining-requests-to-speed-up-manual-api-tests/">API Chaining post</a> where we grabbed the <em>messageId</em> from the POST request and added it to the environment variable for use in the subsequent requests. Similarly, we can also add scripts to verify that the API request returns expected results, status code, etc.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s first write a simple test on our GET API request that it returns a 200 OK response when called. The below test uses the <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/docs/v6/postman/scripts/postman_sandbox_api_reference">Postmans PM API</a> to assert that status code of the response is 200. Check the <em><a href="https://www.getpostman.com/docs/v6/postman/scripts/postman_sandbox_api_reference#response-assertion-api-in-test-scripts">Response Assertion API in test scripts</a></em> to see the other assertion options available like <em>pm.response.to.have.status</em>. The tests are under the Tests section similar to where wrote the scripts to chain API requests. When executing the API request, the Tests tab shows the successful test run for the particular request.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>200 Status Code</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">pm</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">test</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;Status code is 200&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">pm</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">response</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">to</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">have</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">status</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">200</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/postman_tests.png" alt="Postman Tests" class="center" /></p>

<p>Similarly, you can also write <em>Pre-request Script</em> to set variables or perform any other operation. Below I am setting the <em>Value</em> environment variable to &ldquo;Test&rdquo;. You could generate a random value here or set a random id, or set an identifier that does not already exists. It&rsquo;s test/application specific, so leave it you to decide what works best for you.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Pre-request Script.</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">pm</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">environment</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;Value&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Test&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Collection Runner</h3>

<p>The collection runner allows you to manage multiple API requests and run them as a set. Once completed it shows a summary of all the tests included within each request and details of tests that passed/failed in the run. You can target the Runner to run against your environment of choice.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/postman_collection_runner.png" alt="Postman Collection Runner" class="center" /></p>

<p>Running these tests still involves some manual effort of selecting environments and running them. However using <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/newman">Newman</a>, you can run Postman Collections from the command line, which means even in your build pipeline.</p>

<p>Using Postman, we can quickly test our API&rsquo;s across multiple environments. The Collection Runner also shows an excellent visual summary of the tests and helps us in API development. However, I found these tests to violate the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%27t_repeat_yourself">DRY principle</a>. You need to repeat the same API request structure if you have to use them in a different context. Like in the example above I had to create two <em>Get Value By Id</em> requests to test for the value existing and also for when it does not exists. You could use some conditional looping inside the scripts, but then that makes your tests complicated and gets into the loop of how to test your tests. Postman does allow you to export the API request to the language of your choice. So once you have the basic schema, you can export them and write tests that compose them. I find Postman tests and the Runner a quick way to start testing your API endpoints and then for more complicated cases use a stronger programming language. Having the tests in Postman also allows us to have an API spec in place and can be useful to play around with the API.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Reading Eggs - Learning To Read Can Be Easy And Fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/reading-eggs-learning-to-read-can-be-easy-and-fun/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/reading-eggs-learning-to-read-can-be-easy-and-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of months back Gautham (my son) started playing <a href="https://readingeggs.com.au/">Reading Eggs</a>. We started off initially with a free trial after it being recommended by our friend <a href="https://www.facebook.com/asha.maria.90">Asha</a>. We got a 21-day extended trial in addition to the initial 21 days free trial (i.e a total of 42 days), which helped a lot with confirming that Gautham was to use this app. We noticed that he was reading small words quite comfortably and he grew an interest to read various things around. We took an annual subscription and feels totally worth it.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/readingEggs_Levels.jpg" alt="Reading Eggs Levels" ></p>

<blockquote><p>Using the five essential keys to reading success, the program unlocks all aspects of learning to read for your child.</p>

<ul>
<li>The lessons use colourful animation, fun characters, songs, and rewards to keep children motivated.</li>
<li>The program is completely interactive to keep children on task.</li>
<li>When children start the program, they can complete a placement quiz to ensure they are starting at the correct reading level.</li>
<li>Parents can access detailed progress reports as well as hundreds of full-colour downloadable activity sheets that correspond with the lessons in the program.</li>
<li>The program includes over 2000 online books for kids – each ending with a comprehension quiz that assesses your child’s understanding.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Each level explores different letters/word combinations and has a knowledge quiz at the end of it to pass to the next level. <em>The program unlocks all aspects of learning to read for your child, focusing on a core curriculum of phonics and phonemic awareness, sight words, vocabulary, comprehension, and reading for meaning.</em></p>

<p>Do give the app a try if you have kids at home!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/exploring-azurekeyvaultconfigbuilder/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/exploring-azurekeyvaultconfigbuilder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last weekend, I was playing around with <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-as-a-connected-service-in-visual-studio-2017/">Visual Studio Connected Services support for Azure Key Vault</a>. The new feature allows seamless integration of ASP.NET Web applications with Azure Key Vault, making it as simple as using the ConfigurationManager to retrieve the Secrets from the Key Vault - just like you would retrieve it from the config file.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder_config.png" class="center" ></p>

<p>In this post, we will look detailed into the <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders/tree/master/src/Azure">AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder</a> class that allows the seamless integration provided by Connected Services. As we saw in the previous post when you add <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-as-a-connected-service-in-visual-studio-2017/">Key Vault as a Connected Service</a>, it modifies the applications configuration file to add in the AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder references.</p>

<div class="alert alert-warning">
Make sure to update the <b><i>Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.Azure</i></b> and <b><i>Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.Base</i></b> Nuget packages to the latest version.
</div>


<h3>Loading Connection String and App Settings</h3>

<p>The AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder can be specified on both <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms228154.aspx">appsettings</a> and <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bf7sd233(v=vs.100).aspx">connectionString</a> element using the <em>configBuilders</em> attribute.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Configuration File</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'> <span class="nt">&lt;appSettings</span> <span class="na">configBuilders=</span><span class="s">&quot;AzureKeyVault&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'> ...
</span><span class='line'> <span class="nt">&lt;/appSettings&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="nt">&lt;connectionStrings</span> <span class="na">configBuilders=</span><span class="s">&quot;AzureKeyVault&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'> ...
</span><span class='line'> <span class="nt">&lt;/connectionStrings&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Accessing Multiple Key Vaults</h3>

<p>The configBuilders element supports comma-separated list of builders. Using this feature, we can specify multiple Vaults as a source for our secrets. Note how we pass in <em>&lsquo;keyVault1,keyVault2&rsquo;</em> to configBuilders option below.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Configuration File</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;configBuilders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;builders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;add</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault1&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="na">vaultName=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault1&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&quot;Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder, Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.Azure, Version=1.0.0.0, Culture=neutral&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;add</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault2&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="na">vaultName=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault2&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&quot;Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder, Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.Azure, Version=1.0.0.0, Culture=neutral&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;/builders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;/configBuilders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;appSettings</span> <span class="na">configBuilders=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault1,keyVault2&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  ...
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;/appSettings&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If the same key has a value in multiple sources, then the value from the last builder in the list takes precedence. (But I assume you would not need that feature!)</p>

<h3>Modes</h3>

<p>All config builders have the options of setting a <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders#mode">mode</a>, which allows three options.</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li><p><em>Strict</em> - This is the default. In this mode, the config builder will only operate on well-known key/value-centric configuration sections. It will enumerate each key in the section, and if a matching key is found in the external source, it will replace the value in the resulting config section with the value from the external source.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Greedy</em> - This mode is closely related to Strict mode, but instead of being limited to keys that already exist in the original configuration, the config builders will dump all key/value pairs from the external source into the resulting config section.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Expand</em> - This last mode operates on the raw XML before it gets parsed into a config section object. It can be thought of as a simple expansion of tokens in a string. Any part of the raw XML string that matches the pattern ${token} is a candidate for token expansion. If no corresponding value is found in the external source, then the token is left alone.</p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>In short when set to <em>Strict</em> it matches the names in configuration file to Secrets in the Vault&rsquo;s configured. If it does not find corresponding Secret it ignores that key. When set to <em>Greedy</em>, irrespective of what keys are there in the configuration file, it makes all the secrets available in the Vaults specified via Configuration. <strong>This to me sounds like magic and would not prefer to do in an application that I build.</strong></p>

<h3>Greedy Mode Filtering and Formatting Secrets</h3>

<p>When using Greedy mode, we can filter on the list of keys that are made available by using the <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders#prefix">prefix</a> option. Only Secret Names starting with the prefix is made available in the configuration. The other secrets are ignored. This feature can be used in conjunction with <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders#stripprefix">stripPrefix</a> option. When stripPrefix is set to true (defaults to false), the Secret is made available in the configuration after stripping off the prefix.</p>

<p>For e.g. if we have a Secret with the name <em>connectionString-MyConnection</em>, having the below configuration will add the connection string with name <em>MyConnection</em>.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Configuration File</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;add</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault1&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="na">vaultName=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault1&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="na">prefix=</span><span class="s">&quot;connectionString-&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="na">stripPrefix=</span><span class="s">&quot;true&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&quot;Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder, Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.Azure, Version=1.0.0.0, Culture=neutral&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='csharp'><span class='line'><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">connectionString</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">ConfigurationManager</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ConnectionStrings</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s">&quot;MyConnection&quot;</span><span class="p">];</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><em>Use prefix and stripPrefix in conjunction with the Greedy mode. For keys mentioned in the config it will try to match it with the prefix appended to the key name</em></p>

<h3>Preloading Secrets</h3>

<p>By default, the Key Vault Config Builder is set to preload the available Secrets in key vault. By doing this the config builder knows the list of configuration values that the key vault can resolve. For preloading the Secrets, the config builder uses the <em>List</em> call on Secrets. If you don&rsquo;t have list access on Secrets you can turn this feature off using the <em>preloadSecretNames</em> configuration option. At the time of writing the config builder version (1.0.1) throws an exception when preloading Secrets in turned on and List policy is not available on the Vault. I have raised a <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders/pull/24">PR to fix</a> this issue, which if accepted would no longer throw the exception and would invalidate this configuration option.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Configuration File</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;builders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;add</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault1&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="na">preloadSecretNames=</span><span class="s">&quot;false&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="na">vaultName=</span><span class="s">&quot;keyVault1&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Authentication Modes</h3>

<p>The connectionString attribute allows you to specify the authentication mechanism with Key Vault. By default when using the Connected Service to create the key vault it adds the Visual Studio user to the access policies of the Key Vault. When connecting it uses the same. But this does not help you in a large team scenario. Most likely the Vault will be created under your organization subscription and you might want to share the same vault between all developers in the team. You could add the users individually and give them the appropriate access policies, but this might soon become cumbersome for a large team. Instead of using the <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/authenticating-a-client-application-with-azure-key-vault/">Client Id/Secret or Certificate</a> authentication along with <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/authenticating-with-azure-key-vault-using-managed-service-identity/">Managed Service Identity</a> configuration for localhost works the best. The configuration provider will then use the <em>AzureServicesAuthConnectionString</em> value from environment variable to connect to the key vault.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Local System</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='text'><span class='line'>Set AzureServicesAuthConnectionString Environment variable
</span><span class='line'>RunAs=App;AppId=AppId;TenantId=TenantId;AppKey=Secret.
</span><span class='line'>Or
</span><span class='line'>RunAs=App;AppId=AppId;TenantId=TenantId;CertificateThumbprint=Thumbprint;CertificateStoreLocation=CurrentUser
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>As you can see the AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder does provide good integration with Key Vault and makes using the Key Vault seamless. It does have a few issues, especially around <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders/issues/20">handling different Secret versions</a>, which might be fixed in future releases.</p>

<p><em>PS: At the time of writing there were a few issues that I had found while playing around. You can follow up on the individual issues on <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;q=is%3Aissue+author%3Arahulpnath+">Github</a>. Fingers crossed hope at least one of my PR&rsquo;s makes its way through to master!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Azure Key Vault As A Connected Service in Visual Studio 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-as-a-connected-service-in-visual-studio-2017/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-as-a-connected-service-in-visual-studio-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Visual Studio (VS) now supports adding <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/azure-key-vault/">Azure Key Vault</a> as a <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/key-vault/vs-key-vault-add-connected-service">Connected Service</a>, for Web Projects ( ASP.NET Core or any ASP.NET project). Enabling this from the Connected Service makes it easier for you to get started with Azure Key Vault. Below are the prerequisites to use the Connected Service feature</p>

<blockquote><p><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/key-vault/vs-key-vault-add-connected-service#prerequisites">Prerequisites</a></p>

<ul>
<li>An Azure subscription. If you do not have one, you can sign up for a free account.</li>
<li>Visual Studio 2017 version 15.7 with the Web Development workload installed. Download it now.</li>
<li>An ASP.NET 4.7.1 or ASP.NET Core 2.0 web project open.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p><img class =" center" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/keyVault_connectedService.png" alt="Visual Studio, Azure Key Vault Connected Services" /></p>

<p>When selecting &lsquo;Secure Secrets with Azure Key Vault&rsquo; option from the list of Connected Services provided it takes you to a new page within Visual Studio with your Azure Subscription associated with Visual Studio Account and gives you the ability to add a Key Vault to it. VS does generate some defaults for the Vault Name, Resource Group, Location and the Pricing Tier which you can edit as per your requirement. Once you confirm to the <em>Add</em> the Key Vault, VS provisions the Key Vault with the selected configuration and modifies some things in your project.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/key-vault/vs-key-vault-aspnet-what-happened">Changes Made to your ASP.NET project</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/key-vault/vs-key-vault-aspnet-core-what-happened">Changes made to your ASP.NET Core project</a></li>
</ul>


<p><img class =" center" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/keyVault_connectedService_createKeyVault.png" alt="Visual Studio, Azure Key Vault Connected Services" /></p>

<p>In short, VS adds</p>

<ul>
<li>a bunch of NuGet packages to access Azure Key Vault</li>
<li>Adds in the Keyvault Url details</li>
<li>In ASP.NET Web project VS modifies the configuration file to add in the AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder as shown below.</li>
</ul>


<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Web.config</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;configuration&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;configSections&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;section</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;configBuilders&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&quot;System.Configuration.ConfigurationBuildersSection, System.Configuration, Version=4.0.0.0, Culture=neutral, PublicKeyToken=b03f5f7f11d50a3a&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="na">restartOnExternalChanges=</span><span class="s">&quot;false&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="na">requirePermission=</span><span class="s">&quot;false&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/configSections&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;configBuilders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;builders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;add</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">&quot;AzureKeyVault&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="na">vaultName=</span><span class="s">&quot;webapplication-47-dev-kv&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&quot;Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder, Microsoft.Configuration.ConfigurationBuilders.Azure, Version=1.0.0.0, Culture=neutral&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="na">vaultUri=</span><span class="s">&quot;https://WebApplication-47-dev-kv.vault.azure.net&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/builders&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/configBuilders&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>To start using Azure Key Vault from your application we first need to add some Secrets to the Key Vault created by Visual Studio. You can add a secret to the portal using multiple ways, the most straightforward being <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/managing-key-vault-through-azure-portal/">using the Azure Portal</a>. Once you add the Secret to the Key Vault, update the configuration file with the Secret names. Below is how you would do for an ASP.NET Web Project. (<em>MySecret</em> and <em>VersionedSecret</em> keys)</p>

<div class="alert alert-warning">
Make sure to add <b>configBuilders=&#8221;AzureKeyVault&#8221;</b> to the appSettings tag. This tells the Configuraion Manager to use the configured AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder
</div>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='xml'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;appSettings</span> <span class="na">configBuilders=</span><span class="s">&quot;AzureKeyVault&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">key=</span><span class="s">&quot;webpages:Version&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;3.0.0.0&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">key=</span><span class="s">&quot;webpages:Enabled&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;false&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">key=</span><span class="s">&quot;ClientValidationEnabled&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;true&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">key=</span><span class="s">&quot;UnobtrusiveJavaScriptEnabled&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;true&quot;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">key=</span><span class="s">&quot;MySecret&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;dummy1&quot;</span><span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&lt;add</span> <span class="na">key=</span><span class="s">&quot;VersionedSecret&quot;</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">&quot;dummy2&quot;</span><span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/appSettings&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The values <em>dummy*</em> are just dummy values and will be overridden at runtime from the Secret Values created in the Key Vault. If the Secret with the corresponding name does not exist in Key Vault, then the <em>dummy</em> values will be used.</p>

<h3>Authentication</h3>

<p>When VS creates the Vault, it adds in the user logged into VS to the Access Policies list. When running the application, the AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder uses the same details to authenticate with the Key Vault.</p>

<blockquote><p>If you are not logged in as the same user or not logged in at all the provider will not be able to authenticate with the Key Vault and will fallback to use the dummy values in the configuration file. Alternatively you could specify <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/key-vault/service-to-service-authentication#connection-string-support">connection option avaiable for AzureServiceTokenProvider</a></p></blockquote>

<p><img class =" center" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/keyVault_connectedService_AccessPolicies.png" alt="Visual Studio, Azure Key Vault Connected Services" /></p>

<h3>Secrets and Versioning</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders/tree/master/src/Azure">AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder</a> requests to get all the Secrets in the Key Vault at application startup using the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/rest/api/keyvault/getsecrets/getsecrets">Secrets endoint</a>. This call returns all the Secrets in the Key Vault. For whatever keys in the AppSettings that has a match with a Secret in the vault, a request is made to get the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/rest/api/keyvault/getsecret/getsecret">Secret details</a>, which returns the actual Secret value for the keys. Below are the traces of the calls going out captured using <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/fiddler-free-web-debugging-proxy/">Fiddler</a>.</p>

<p><img class =" center" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/keyVault_connectedService_requests.png" alt="AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder Fiddler Traces " /></p>

<p>It looks like at the moment the AzureKeyVaultConfigBuilder get only the latest version of the Secrets. As you can tell from one of my Secret names (VersionedSecret), I have created two versions for the Secret, and the config builder picks the latest version. I don&rsquo;t see a way right now whereby I can specify a specific secret version.</p>

<p>The Visual Studio Connected Services makes it easy to get started with Azure Key Vault and move your secrets to a more secure store, than having it around in your <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/keeping-sensitive-configuration-data-out-of-source-control/">configuration files</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Prettier - An Opinionated Code Formatter]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/prettier-an-opinionated-code-formatter/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/prettier-an-opinionated-code-formatter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Code Formatting is an essential aspect of writing code, and I did write about this a while back on <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/introducing-code-formatting-into-a-large-codebase/">introducing code formatting into a large code base</a>. It&rsquo;s not about what all rules you and your team use, it&rsquo;s about sticking with the conventions and using them consistently. Code Formatting rules are best when applied automatically, and the developer does not need to do anything in particular about it.</p>

<p><a href="https://prettier.io/">Prettier</a> is an opinionated code formatter, which supports multiple languages and editors and easy to get started. Getting set up is as easy as just installing the <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/install.html">prettier package using yarn/npm</a>. There are multiple points at which you can integrate Prettier - <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/editors.html">in your editor</a>, <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/precommit.html">pre-commit hook</a> or <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/cli.html#list-different">CI environments</a>.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zgWBAKZvdFQ" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Most of the IDE&rsquo;s have plugins for Prettier which makes it easy to get it into the code right from the beginning. You might need to update your IDE settings to run prettier when you save a file. For VS Code I have to set editor.formatOnSave to true to turn on this behaviour.</p>

<p>As the title says, Prettier is opinionated, which is useful in many ways and removes much time wasted on unnecessary discussions. However, it does provide some <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/configuration.html">configuration options</a>. Check if it provides enough for you to call a meeting to decide on one of them :).</p>

<p>Write prettier code!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Check If You Have Been Hacked!]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/check-if-you-have-been-hacked/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/check-if-you-have-been-hacked</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/password_manager.jpg" alt ="https://pixabay.com/en/data-security-keyboard-computer-1590455/" class="center" /></p>

<p>With more and more data breaches happening it is possible that your personal information and passwords are already compromised. If you have been lazy and reusing passwords (just like me until a while back) across multiple sites then it is good to check if your password is already compromised. It necessarily need not be one of your social media account or bank account that needs to be compromised for an attacker to get your credentials. If you have been reusing passwords across sites, it might be that one site where security is not given much importance for that gets breached, exposing your credentials to the attacker or anyone who has the breached data. Often hackers use this information to try and enumerate other sites, social network, bank logins to try and login assuming the behaviour of password reuse.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Check your <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/">email</a> or <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/Passwords">password</a> to see if any has been part of a data breach.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>To check if you have been part of a data breach you can use the service <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/">haveibeenpwned</a>. If you have been part of any data breaches, then it will show you the details. In addition to that, you can also use the <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/Passwords">Pwned Passwords</a> list to check if the password that you use has been part of any data breaches. It&rsquo;s good to change your password if you find yours in there. If you are worried about entering your password in haveibeenpwned site, the good thing is that it uses <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/ive-just-launched-pwned-passwords-version-2/">k-anonymity model</a>, which means that your full password is not sent across the wire.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<ul>
<li>Update your passwords on all sites that you use if you have been reusing passwords. If you don&rsquo;t have much time to do this in one shot, you can do this incrementally as and when you next visit them.</li>
<li>Make sure you have unique passwords for each of the site. <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/only-secure-password-is-one-you-cant/">A good password is one that you cannot remember</a>. So if you are not using a <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/password-manager-get-one-if-you-havent-already/">Password Manager</a> it&rsquo;s a good idea to start using. If you don&rsquo;t want to spend money on a password manager, you can always use a <a href="https://www.lastpass.com/password-generator">random password generator</a> to generate one for you. Remembering that password might be hard, you could either write it down or save it in the browser (not that I am recommending it over getting a Password Manager, but better than reusing passwords).</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NDC Security 2018 - Overview and Key Takeaways]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/ndc-security-2018-overview-and-key-takeaways/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/ndc-security-2018-overview-and-key-takeaways</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While in Sydney I was lucky enough to have attended the <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/ndc-sydney/">first</a> and <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/ndc-sydney-2017/">second</a> NDC Conferences. After moving up to Brisbane, did not think I could attend one of these soon. However, then comes a nice shorter version of NDC specific to Security - <a href="https://ndcsecurity.com.au/">NDC Security</a>. As the name suggests, this conference is particular to security-related topics with a 2-day workshop and 1-day conference, as was held in Gold Coast, Queensland.</p>

<h3>The Workshop</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/">Troy Hunt</a> and <a href="https://scotthelme.co.uk/">Scott Helme</a> ran <a href="https://ndcsecurity.com.au/workshops/">two workshops</a> and I attended <a href="https://ndcsecurity.com.au/workshop/hack-yourself-first-how-to-go-on-the-cyber-offence/">Hack Yourself First</a> by Troy. The workshop covers a wide range of topics and is perfect for anyone who is into web development. The best thing is that you only need to have a browser and <a href="https://www.telerik.com/download/fiddler">Fiddler</a>/<a href="https://www.charlesproxy.com/download/">Charles Proxy</a> (depending on whether you are on Windows or Mac land). One of the interesting thing about the workshop is that it puts you first into the hackers perspective and forces you to exploit existing vulnerabilities in the <a href="http://hackyourselffirst.troyhunt.com/">sample site</a> designed specifically for this. Once you can do this, we then look at ways of protecting ourselves against such exploits and other mechanisms involved.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/ndc_security_hyf.jpg" class="center" alt="Hack yourself first, Troy Hunt"></p>

<p>The workshop highlights how easy it is to find and exploit vulnerabilities in applications. Some tools detect vulnerabilities and exploit them for you if you input a few details to them. You necessarily need not know the vulnerabilities itself or how exactly to exploit them. Such tools make it easy for people to use them on any website that is out there on the web. Combined with the power of search engines it makes it quite easy to make your site vulnerabilities to be easily discoverable.</p>

<h3>The Conference</h3>

<p>There were <a href="https://ndcsecurity.com.au/agenda/">six talks</a> in total and below are the ones that I found interesting.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://ndcsecurity.com.au/talk/csp-xxp-sts-pkp-caa-etc-omg-wtf-bbq/">Scott Helme Talk: CSP XXP STS PKP CAA ETC OMG WTF BBQ…</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ndcsecurity.com.au/talk/dependable-dependencies/">Talk: Dependable Dependencies</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ndcsecurity.com.au/talk/everything-is-cyber-broken/">Everything is Cyber-broken</a></li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/ndc_security_conference.jpg" class="center" alt="NDC Securtiy, 2018 - Conference"></p>

<p>The whole web is on a journey towards making it more secure. So it is an excellent time to <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/https-for-free-and-why-you-should-care/">move on to HTTPS</a> if you are not already. Even after enabling HTTPS, it is a good idea to make sure you have got all the appropriate <a href="https://securityheaders.com/">security headers</a> set. Making sure that the libraries that you depend on are patched and updated is equally essential.
There are incidents of massive data breaches because of vulnerabilities in third-party libraries and not keeping them updated.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Functionality need not be the only reason to upgrade third-party libraries. There might be security vulnerabilities that are getting patched which is an equally good reason to update dependent packages</em></p></blockquote>

<p>The harder thing is to keep track of the vulnerabilities that are getting reported and always checking back with your application&rsquo;s dependencies. There is a wide range of tools that help make this easy and seamlessly integrate within the development workflow. It can be included as early as when a developer intends to include a library into the source code, or in the build pipeline or even for sites that are up and running. The earlier such issues get detected in the software development lifecycle, the less costly and impact it has on time and cost.</p>

<h4><strong>Tools</strong></h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://sonarwhal.com/scanner/">Sonarwhal</a></li>
<li><a href="https://snyk.io/">Snyk</a></li>
<li><a href="https://retirejs.github.io/retire.js/">Retire.js</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.netsparker.com/">Netsparker</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.owasp.org/index.php/OWASP_Zed_Attack_Proxy_Project">OWASP Zed Attack Proxy Project</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/troys-ultimate-list-of-security-links/">Ultimate List of Security Links</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The conference ended with a good discussion between Troy and Scott on how everything is Cyber broken. It touches upon the value of Extended Validation (EV) Certificate and how CA&rsquo;s are trying to push for them while browsers are more and more going away from them. It also touches on various proponents of HTTP and the wrong messages that are getting spread to a broader audience and also about <a href="https://scotthelme.co.uk/revocation-is-broken/">certificate revocations</a> and a lot more. It was a fun discussion and a great end to the three-day event.</p>

<h3>Location and Food</h3>

<p>NDC Security was held at <a href="https://www.qthotelsandresorts.com/gold-coast/">QT Gold Coast, Queensland</a> and well organized. Coffee and drinks were available all throughout the day with a barista on the last day (which was cool). Food was served at start, breaks, and lunch and was good. The conference rooms were great and spacious and had reasonable good internet. Did not face much connectivity issues and everything ran smoothly.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/ndc_security_food_location.jpg" class="center" alt="NDC Securtiy, 2018 - Food and Location"></p>

<p>One of the things I first did after coming from the conference was to <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/https-for-free-and-why-you-should-care/">move this blog over to HTTPS</a>. I had been procrastinating long on this, but there were enough reasons to make a move now. Also, there are a bunch of things that catch my eye at client places and other web sites that I visit often. Attending the conference and workshop has been a great value add and recommend to anyone if you have a chance to attend that. For the others, most of the content is available in <a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/">Pluralsight</a>.</p>

<p><em>PS: Special thanks to <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/finding-a-job-abroad/">Readify</a> for sending me to this conference and also providing a &lsquo;paid vacation (accommodation)&rsquo; in Gold Coast. It was a nice three-day break for my wife and son also.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Authy - Sync Two Factor Authentication Across Devices]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/authy-sync-two-factor-authentication-across-devices/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/authy-sync-two-factor-authentication-across-devices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-factor_authentication">Two Factor Authentication</a> (2FA) is becoming more and more common these days and is a good way to protect your accounts from getting into the wrong hands. SMS and App based 2FA are more common with the day to day services that we use, like Gmail, Outlook, Facebook etc. Enabling 2FA the user is prompted for a number that gets sent to them via phone or generated using an application, in addition to the username and password, when logging in. Enabling 2FA protects your account a level further. Even if an attacker has your credentials from a data breach, they would still need access to your phone to log in to your account. Using an app to generate the codes is more preferable than using SMS as it does not require internet connectivity or mobile service.</p>

<p>Until lately I have been using <a href="https://support.google.com/accounts/answer/1066447?hl=en&amp;ref_topic=2954345">Google Authenticator</a> to generate codes for all the accounts that I have 2FA enabled. The app does work well on a single mobile device but becomes a pain when you want to switch phones or lose the phone. You could potentially be locked out of your accounts if you lose the phone and don&rsquo;t have the backup codes available.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/authy_preview.png" alt="Authy" class="center" /></p>

<p><a href="https://authy.com/features/">Authy</a> is one of the best-rated 2FA application which targets exactly the issues with Google Authenticator. It is easy to setup, can be secured via TouchId/Password, supports encrypted backups and syncs across multiple applications and devices. Once setup any code that you add to your app gets synced through Authy servers and is all encrypted and secured. Authy has applications for the <a href="https://authy.com/download/">mobile, desktop and also has a plugin for Chrome browser</a>. You can also manage devices from the account and revoke a device if it gets lost or is not used anymore. <a href="https://authy.com/blog/authy-vs-google-authenticator/">Authy vs Google Authentication post</a> covers in detail all the differences between the two and the advantages of using Authy.</p>

<p>Check out <a href="https://authy.com/features/">Authy</a> and do setup 2FA if you are not already!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTTPS For Free and Why You Should Care]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/https-for-free-and-why-you-should-care/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/https-for-free-and-why-you-should-care</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are here and reading this probably you have a website and is serving it over HTTP. If you are unsure of whether your site needs HTTPS or not, don&rsquo;t think twice - <strong>YES, YOUR SITE NEEDS HTTPS</strong>.</p>

<p>If you are not convinced check out <a href="https://doesmysiteneedhttps.com/">https://doesmysiteneedhttps.com/</a>. One of the main reasons that I have seen (including me) why people have shied away from having HTTPS on sites was cost. And this post explains how to get HTTPS for free. But make sure you are getting it for the correct reasons and you know exactly what you are getting</p>

<div class="center">
    <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">HTTPS &amp; SSL doesn&#39;t mean &quot;trust this.&quot; It means &quot;this is private.&quot; You may be having a private conversation with Satan.</p>&mdash; Scott Hanselman (@shanselman) <a href="https://twitter.com/shanselman/status/187572289724887041?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 4, 2012</a></blockquote>
    <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</div>


<p>Depending on how you are hosting you could possibly take two routes to enable HTTPS on your site. Let&rsquo;s look at them in detail.</p>

<h3>Option 1 - Get your Certificate and Add to Your Host</h3>

<p>If your hosting service already allows you to upload a custom domain certificate, but you were just holding back because of the extra cost of getting a certificate, then head over to <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/">Let&rsquo;s Encrypt</a> to get your free certificate. Again depending on your hosting provider and the level of access that you have on your web server, Let&rsquo;s Encrypt has <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/getting-started/">muliple ways</a> on how you can get a certificate.</p>

<blockquote><p><a href="https://letsencrypt.org/docs/faq/#general"><strong>What does it cost to use Let’s Encrypt? Is it really free?</strong></a><br/>
<em>We do not charge a fee for our certificates. Let’s Encrypt is a nonprofit, our mission is to create a more secure and privacy-respecting Web by promoting the widespread adoption of HTTPS. Our services are free and easy to use so that every website can deploy HTTPS.</em></p>

<p><em>We require support from generous sponsors, grantmakers, and individuals in order to provide our services for free across the globe. If you’re interested in supporting us please consider donating or becoming a sponsor.</em></p>

<p><em>In some cases, integrators (e.g. hosting providers) will charge a nominal fee that reflects the administrative and management costs they incur to provide Let’s Encrypt certificates.</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>Option 2 - CloudFlare</h3>

<p>If you are like me on a shared/cheaper hosting service it is more likely that your hosting plan does not support adding SSL certificates. You will be forced to upgrade to a higher plan to upload a certificate, which in turn will cost you more. In this case, you can use <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/">Cloudflare</a>, to enable HTTPS for free.</p>

<p>Cloudflare provides lots of features for websites, but in our case, we are more interested in what the Free plan gives us. It gives us a Shared SSL Certificate and also added benefits of Global CDN.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/cloudflare_free_plan.png" class="center" /></p>

<p>Cloudflare acts as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reverse_proxy">reverse proxy</a> between you and the server hosting this web page, which simply means that all requests now go through Cloudflare which in turn reaches out to the web server, if it cannot find a locally cached copy. So this also means that there are now reduced number of calls to the web server as Cloudflare would serve it from its cache if already available.</p>

<p>Shared SSL is what is more interesting for us as part of this blog post. What shared SSL gives us is free HTTPS for our website. We get a Domain Validated (DV) certificate, with a small catch. It is not issued to our domain but to a shared Cloudflare domain server (sni154817.cloudflaressl.com in my case). If you want a custom SSL certificate then you need to be on a paid plan.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/blog_ssl_certificate.png" class="center" /></p>

<p>Cloudflare supports <a href="https://support.cloudflare.com/hc/en-us/articles/200170416">multiple SSL settings</a> - Off, Flexible SSL, Full SSL, Full SSL(Strict). Depending on how your host is setup you can choose one of the options. Since I am using <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-au/services/app-service/web/">Azure Web Apps</a> to host, it supports https over <em>*.azurewebsites.net</em> subdomain. But since the certficate is not for my custom domain name (rahulpnath.com), I have set the SSL setting to Full SSL. Cloudfare in this case will connect over HTTPS but not validate the certificate. If your host does not support HTTPs connection (for free) you can use Flexible SSL.
<a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/ssl/" >
<img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/cloudflare_ssl_modes.png" class="center" />
</a></p>

<p>You can also choose to enable Cloudflare with Full SSL(Strict) if you have followed Option 1 and have a custom SSL certificate for the domain. This will give you the added benefits that Cloudfare provides.</p>

<h3>Enabling HSTS Preload</h3>

<p>Now that you have HTTPS setup on your domain with either of the options above, we can see that the website is now accessible over HTTPS. However, when you make the very first request to the website, the request goes over HTTP which then redirects over to HTTPS, after which the communication happens over a secure channel. However, there is a risk where the very first request can be intercepted and cause undesired behaviour.</p>

<blockquote><p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trust_on_first_use">Trust on first use</a> (TOFU), or trust upon first use (TUFU), is a security model used by client software which needs to establish a trust relationship with an unknown or not-yet-trusted endpoint.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>By setting the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/Strict-Transport-Security">STS(Strict-Transport-Security)</a> header along with the preload directive, we can then add our domain to the <a href="https://hstspreload.org/">HSTS Preload list</a>. By adding your domain into this list it is literally getting hardcoded into source code of browsers (like for e.g <a href="https://chromium.googlesource.com/chromium/src/net/+/master/http/transport_security_state_static.json">Chrome here</a>). So anytime a request is made to a site it is checked against this hardcoded list available in memory and if present the request goes as HTTPS from the very first. You can set all subdomains for your domain as well as HSTS preloaded. Make sure you have all subdomains are served over HTTPS so that you do not lock yourself out on those sites. You can find more details on HSTS <a href="https://scotthelme.co.uk/hsts-the-missing-link-in-tls/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Now that the cost factor is out of making your site support HTTPS, is there anything else that is holding you back? If speed is a concern and it worries that encryption/decryption at both ends of communication is going to slow you down take a look at this post on <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/i-wanna-go-fast-https-massive-speed-advantage/">HTTPS&#8217; massive speed advantage</a>.
If you are still not convinced let me give it one last shot to get you on board. Going forward most modern browsers are going to default to the web as a secure place. So instead of the present positive visual security indicators, it would start showing warnings on pages served over HTTP. That means soon your sites would start showing <span style="color:red;">Not Secure</span> if you are not moving over to HTTPS.</p>

<p><a href="https://blog.chromium.org/2018/05/evolving-chromes-security-indicators.html" >
    <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/chrome_https.png" class="center" />
</a></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t see any reason why we should still be serving our sites over HTTP. As you can see I have moved over to the HTTPS and have added this domain to the preload list as well. Let&rsquo;s make the web secure by default!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Share and Inspire]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/share-and-inspire/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/share-and-inspire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started this blog around nine years back, my only intention was to share technical posts. But over period of time I started writing about a variety of things including <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/">productivity tips</a> that I found useful, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/travelogue/">travelogues</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/">random thoughts</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap/">personal goals</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/blogging/">blogging</a> etc. One of the things that I have noticed is that a lot of people have been inspired by these various posts and photos that I post online and have triggered them to do similar things.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/share_and_inspire.jpg" alt="Share and Inspire, Image Source https://www.saylor.org/2015/04/blog-saylor-student-stories/" class="center"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had my own similar inspirations to start the various things that I do today. Like for instance, I started running after being inspired by my friends, <a href="https://twitter.com/SatyKrish">Satish</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/jeyakums">Suresh</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/thirusv">Thiru</a>. I reached out to them for various tips when I started running a year ago. From running I moved on to cycling and a bit of swimming after seeing my friend <a href="https://www.facebook.com/rahul.revikumar477977">Rahul</a>. For travel, my inspiration has been <a href="https://www.facebook.com/arun.sudheendran.1">Arun Sudheendran</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/deepak.suresh">Deepak Suresh</a> who do a fair bit of exploration. I tend to reach out to them for travel ideas and places to visit. Similarly, there have been inspirations from people that I have never met or met just once or twice.</p>

<p>Below is a transcript of a chat with one of my readers whom I have never met. It&rsquo;s a great feeling to wake up to such messages and it boosts your own motivation to continue what you are doing.</p>

<p><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/share_and_inspire_chat.png" alt="Share and Inspire" class="center"></p>

<p>Social media plays a great role in spreading information these days. When you see people in your own friend&rsquo;s circle start doing things that you have always wanted to, it gives you an extra push to give it a try. There might be some people who feel you are sharing too much of things that don&rsquo;t interest them. For those, there is always an option to un-follow, mute, filter etc. Don&rsquo;t let that thought stop you from sharing things that you do.</p>

<p>Such a small act of sharing, even things that you might have seen someone do could add up and be of big impact to someone else, often referred to as the <a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/TheButterflyEffectOfTechnologyCommunity.aspx">Butterfly Effect</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>The <strong>Butterfly Effect</strong>: This effect grants the power to cause a hurricane in China to a butterfly flapping its wings in New Mexico. It may take a very long time, but the connection is real. If the butterfly had not flapped its wings at just the right point in space/time, the hurricane would not have happened. - <a href="http://fractalfoundation.org/resources/what-is-chaos-theory/">Chaos Theory</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Share things that you do, share positive things and inspire others!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Four Finger Swipe Gesture to Switch Between Virtual Machines]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/four-finger-swipe-gesture-to-switch-between-virtual-machines/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/four-finger-swipe-gesture-to-switch-between-virtual-machines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Of late I have been working for multiple clients at the same time. Different clients have different development environments, which has forced me into using Virual Machines (VM&rsquo;s) for my day to day work. I will cover my actual setup and new way of working using VM&rsquo;s in a different post.</p>

<p>When working on VM&rsquo;s I often have to switch to the host machine for email, chat and a few other programs that I have just on my host machine. Minimizing the VM host is time consuming and context breaking if you are working off a single screen. On a multi monitor setup you can always have VM on one screen and host on the other. This can still get tricky if you have more than one VM&rsquo;s connected.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fcbqOe8LnhM" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>The <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windowsexperience/2015/04/16/virtual-desktops-in-windows-10-the-power-of-windowsmultiplied/">Virtual Desktops</a> feature in Windows 10 is of great help in this scenario. We can move between desktops using keyboard shortcuts (Ctrl + Win + Right/Left Arrow). But with the VM running on separate Virtual Desktop any key presses gets picked up by the VM operating system and not by the host. This means that you cannot use the keyboard shortcuts to switch host desktops from inside a VM. However you can move between desktops using the Four Finger swipe gesture on your touchpad (if that is supported). These swipe gestures are picked up only by the host machine OS, unlike the keyboard shortcuts. So even when you are inside a VM, doing the four finger swipe gesture tells the host OS to switch desktops. This allows you to easily navigate between VM&rsquo;s running on different Virtual Desktops.</p>

<p>Hope this helps!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trips for the (Long) Weekend Around Sydney]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/trips-for-the-long-weekend-around-sydney/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/trips-for-the-long-weekend-around-sydney</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back I had written about various <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/one-day-trips-around-sydney/">one-day trip options around Sydney</a>. Here is a list of places that we traveled around Sydney during long weekend breaks with a day or two overnight stays.</p>

<blockquote><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Too_long;_didn%27t_read"><strong>TLDR;</strong></a></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three-day-trip-to-coffs-harbour-from-sydney/">Coffs Harbour</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.portmacquarieinfo.com.au/">Port Macquarie</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.grandpacificdrive.com.au/">Grand Pacific Drive</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.visitnsw.com/destinations/blue-mountains?nst=0">Blue Mountains</a></li>
<li><a href="https://visitcanberra.com.au/">Canberra</a></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h3><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three-day-trip-to-coffs-harbour-from-sydney/">Coffs Harbour</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three-day-trip-to-coffs-harbour-from-sydney/">Coffs Harbour</a> is one of the places that I liked the most of all my trips. It&rsquo;s been almost a year since I made my trip and the memories are still fresh. The beaches are great, especially the Jetty Beach. The rainforest walk in Dorrigo was the best I have had to date, especially because of the rain the night before. Coffs Harbour is perfect for a 3-4 days trip and there are a lot of places to visit around.</p>

<p><img alt="Jetty Beach, Coffs Harbour" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/coffs_harbour_jetty_beach_toys.jpg" /></p>

<h3><a href="https://www.portmacquarieinfo.com.au/">Port Macquarie</a></h3>

<p>We headed off to Port Macquarie to celebrate Gauthams birthday. Gautham likes strawberries a lot which was why we chose Port Macquarie. <a href="http://www.ricardoes.com/">Ricardoes Tomatoes &amp; Strawberries</a> is located just ten minutes north of Port Macquarie and provides a unique experience for picking your own strawberries. You can spend around 2-3 hours here and make sure you don&rsquo;t miss the scones from the cafe. Port Macquarie is also a great place for whale watching and we headed off on an early morning trip to be with the whales. The boat ride (<a href="https://www.portjet.com.au/">PortJet</a>) in itself is an experience and to our luck, we were able to see around 3 whales up close. We also went to Dooragan National Park, Kattang, Perpendicular Point and Charles Hamsey lookout.</p>

<p><img alt="Whale watching and Strawberry picking, Port Macquarie" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/port_macquarie.jpg" /></p>

<h3><a href="http://www.grandpacificdrive.com.au/">Grand Pacific Drive</a></h3>

<p>The Grand Pacific Drive makes a great one day trip as well as a multi-day trip for those who want to take their time along this stretch of land. Starting from Royal National Park and stretching all the way to Sapphire Coast, this makes a great drive with beautiful scenery and also a lot of places to visit. The <a href="http://www.grandpacificdrive.com.au/">Grand Pacific Drive</a> site has all the details that you need to plan your trip. It also has a trip planner that makes planning easier. If you want to cover most of the places along the way during a single trip, it is best to give it 2-3 days. During my trip, I stopped over at Wollongong and only made my way till Kiama.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.grandpacificdrive.com.au/">
    <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/sydney_trip_gpd.png" class="center" alt="Grand Pacific Drive" />
</a></p>

<h3><a href="https://www.visitnsw.com/destinations/blue-mountains?nst=0">Blue Mountains</a></h3>

<p>Just 90 minutes from Sydney by car, the Blue Mountains has a lot of attractions worth visiting, making it a good place for an extended weekend trip. Wentworth Falls, Echo Point, and Three Sisters are some of the popular lookouts. <a href="https://www.scenicworld.com.au/">Scenic World</a> offers some good rides and entertainment for kids. I liked the worlds steepest incline railway ride in particular. The entry tickets are a bit overpriced though.</p>

<p><img alt="Three Sisters, Blue Mountains" class="center" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/three_sisters_blue_mountains.jpg" /></p>

<p>Jenolan Caves is another one hour drive from the Blue Mountains and is a must-do. It&rsquo;s great for people of all ages and if you have kids they will love it. Make sure you check the different <a href="http://www.jenolancaves.org.au/">cave options</a> and choose one that fits the people in your group. Booking a spot in advance might help and make sure you arrive on time. The drive up there might be a bit slower so give enough buffer time before your cave walk starts.</p>

<h3><a href="https://visitcanberra.com.au/">Canberra</a></h3>

<p>Unlike Sydney, Canberra is a planned city and you can tell that from the moment you enter it. It&rsquo;s a beautiful little city with lots of variety of things to visit. We started off with the <a href="https://www.cockingtongreen.com.au/">Cockington Green Gardens</a> followed by the <a href="http://nationaldinosaurmuseum.com.au/">National Dinosaur museum</a>. You can spend almost half a day with these and try out the <a href="https://visitcanberra.com.au/eat-and-drink/57031e8c5d234a7604ea80b2/the-hamlet">Hamlet, Food Trucks</a>. The <a href="https://www.aph.gov.au/Visit_Parliament">Parliment House</a> and <a href="https://www.awm.gov.au/">Australian War Memorial</a> is also worth visiting. If you time your visit during September-October you can also see the <a href="https://visitcanberra.com.au/events/56b23aea266140594567dbbe/floriade">Floriade</a> - the tulip flower festival.</p>

<p><img alt="Floriade Tulip Festival, Canberra" class="center" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/canberra_tulip_festival.jpg" /></p>

<p>Nelson Bay, Hunter Valley, Orange, Port Stephens etc are some of the places that are on our list but could not make it yet. I moved over to Brisbane end of last year and not sure when I will have another chance to explore more around Sydney. But I have new places to look forward to now - Exploring Brisbane!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
