<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-29T18:48:13+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: f.lux - Make it Easy For Your Eyes]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/flux-make-it-easy-for-your-eyes/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/flux-make-it-easy-for-your-eyes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you spent a lot of time in front of a computer then <a href="https://justgetflux.com/">f.lux</a> is for you. You would have heard that using laptop or mobile just before sleep is bad. It is because of the <a href="http://www.bluelightexposed.com/">blue light</a> that digital screens emit.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>During the day, computer screens look good—they&rsquo;re designed to look like the sun. But, at 9PM, 10PM, or 3AM, you probably shouldn&rsquo;t be looking at the sun.</em></p>

<p><em>f.lux fixes this: it makes the color of your computer&rsquo;s display adapt to the time of day, warm at night and like sunlight during the day.</em></p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" alt="Flux Current Setting" src="/images//flux_current.png" /></p>

<p><em>Tell f.lux what kind of lighting you have, and where you live. Then forget about it. f.lux will do the rest, automatically.</em> <br/>
f.lux adjusts the screen to the room you are in and the time of the day. You can set the lighting that the room has, and it will adjust the screen for it.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Flux Settings" src="/images//flux_settings.png" /></p>

<p>I have been using f.lux for a couple of years and had it always on(except occasionally when <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/photography-learning-to-click/">processing photos</a>). <a href="https://fluxometer.com/">f.luxometer</a> tells how much blue light f.lux removes if you are interested.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Included Scrum and Pomodoro Technique in My Morning Routine]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back I had blogged about my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Morning Routine</a>. The routine helps set the pace for the day and in getting things done that matters to me most. During mid of December 2016, I started running once a week to get some exercise into my routine. I got interested in running and soon was running thrice a week along with some free body exercises another three days. Since this was new and exciting naturally my concentration was more on getting these done. I struggled to keep up with my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/">blogging schedule</a>, failed to get a video out in the month of February and lost track of <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2016-recap/">everything else</a> (FSharp, Reading, etc.). Though I continued to wake up <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">early in the morning</a>, I could not get much done. I badly wanted to fix things up and here is what I have come up with</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>TLDR;</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>One-week sprints and setting weekly goals</li>
<li>Break the Big Rocks (or MIT&rsquo;s) into smaller tasks</li>
<li>Improve Focus using Pomodoro Technique</li>
<li>Daily Review and Weekly Review</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h3>One Week Sprints</h3>

<p>The <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/psm-learnings/">PSM course</a> I attended in January made me realize the importance is sticking to a process. I decided to do weekly sprints for managing my personal work. I have a better estimate of how much I can get done with a shorter interval. I have blocked time on Sunday morning for my weekly planning and processing the &lsquo;In-Basket.&rsquo; The In-Basket is where anything that comes up during the week goes. Todoist has an Inbox Project to which any uncategorized items go by default. I process the inbox and move them to various categories that I have setup in Todoist. Depending on the priority things make their way into the coming week or get set to &lsquo;tentative&rsquo; dates and appropriate categories.</p>

<p><img alt = "Todoist Inbox" src="/images/pomodoro_todoist_inbox.png" /></p>

<p><em>Big Rocks</em> are tasks that matter to you the most. Identifying them is important so that you do not miss out on them. The idea is to fill your time available over the week with the Big Rocks. The rest will find its way through, just like if you were to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0VNmIxkyHd8">fill a bottle with stones first and then fill it with water, sand as opposed to the other way round</a>. Big Rocks are the same as the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Most Important Tasks (MIT&rsquo;s)</a> that we saw earlier.</p>

<p>For me the biggest rock is family, and I have all of my evenings and weekends (rather any time they are awake, and I am home) blocked out for them. Over the past year, since I have written about my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Morning Routine</a> one of the MIT&rsquo;s has changed. Blogging and FSharp still stay on, but I swapped in producing videos for Github contribution. Exercise is something I have set as a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2016-recap/">goal for 2017</a>. To keep up with my exercise goal, I <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">run three times a week and body weight exercises for another three days</a>.</p>

<p>Every day I have roughly three hours of &lsquo;me time&rsquo; from morning 4 am - 7 am. Waking up was difficult for a while but then I realized it&rsquo;s all about <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">waking up to an alarm</a>. The &lsquo;me time&rsquo; acts as the bottle into which I have to fit the Big Rocks into (if you watched the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0VNmIxkyHd8">video above</a>). I need to optimize the things in the best way possible to fit it all in there.</p>

<h3>Pomodoro Sized Tasks</h3>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">The Pomodoro Technique</a> is a time management technique that uses a timer to break down work into intervals, traditionally 25 minutes in length, separated by short breaks. These intervals are named Pomodoro.</p>

<p>Many times in the past I have tried Pomodoro Technique on and off but was never able to stick with it. From my previous <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Morning Routine</a> you can easily tell that I had a high-level plan on what my MIT&rsquo;s are, but did not have any specific plans or goals on what to do about them. I also left room for flexibility to choose each day to pick up things randomly. Often it happened that I took more time to blog and got a bit of time for the other MIT&rsquo;s. Though I have <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1YTjHWjepag">automated a lot of blogging activities</a>, writing a post often took more time. And since I was not tracking this I was always happy that I achieved some of my MIT&rsquo;s daily.</p>

<p>Once I started running things changed drastically. I struggled to keep up the with everything and concentrated on just blogging. It was because I started losing focus and started getting the feeling that it&rsquo;s too hard to fit in everything. I let this happen for over a month but was not very happy with it. Mid of February I sat down and dumped all my available time onto a paper and broke them up into Pomodoro sized intervals. So now I know how much time I have in a week for getting stuff done. I then broke down my big rocks s into smaller measurable pieces. For, e.g., with blogging, I have 4 Pomodoro of work - Creating a draft (high level), Refining the post body, Writing the introduction and conclusion and finally Adding in images, proofreading, and publishing. Similarly, I broke down publishing videos (happens throughout a month) and learning F#.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Plans are nothing; Planning is everything</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I blocked out the time for running and exercise first, then I filled in with blogging tasks, followed by videos and then with FSharp learning. I also have a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user_challenges/8539430">reading goal for 2017</a> and found that I can best do that during my commute to work. Though this is not a full sized pomodoro interval, I have this tracked. Weekly Planning and Daily Review are two other activities that I have started following religiously. I do my daily planning right after my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/psm-learnings/">Daily Scrum</a> at work so that I get to capture anything work related as well.</p>

<p><img alt = "Pomodoro Plan" src="/images/pomodoro_plan.png" /></p>

<p>I was surprised how easily I could fit all of these into the time I have. Since the task breakdown above is guesstimates, I have some buffer time in my plan so that I can accommodate tasks that take more time or urgent tasks that come up during the week or the laziness that kicks in at times.</p>

<h3>Increasing Focus and Removing Distractions</h3>

<p>Social Media and emails were one of the biggest distractions for me. Even though I try to reduce the amount of time I spent for these, I often ended up taking a glance at those sites now and then. It often ended distracting and taking me completely off course from the task. I decided to stick to checking personal email only once a day and work emails twice a day. As for social networks (especially Facebook), I decided to keep that to one as well. I wanted to track this as well and see how well I was with it. I use <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.isoron.uhabits&amp;hl=en">Loop Habit Tracker</a> app on my phone for tracking these habits.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Loop Habit Tracker" src="/images/pomodoro_habit_tracker.png" /></p>

<p>For tracking pomodoro I use <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tomighty-a-pomodoro-timer/">Tomighty, a simple Pomodoro tool</a>. It just tracks the interval and does that thing well. The Pomodoro Technique lists down different techniques to manage interruptions and distractions. Managing interruptions is particularly useful when working out of an office and using pomodoro. During the short intervals, I usually take a walk around, fill water, stretch, etc.</p>

<p>I have only been following this for three weeks. But I find this effective and hope to stick on with it for a longer time. I no longer have to spend time deciding what to do as that&rsquo;s already decided. The only thing is to do it. Having taken the reasoning part of what to do out, I find doing things is easy and I procrastinate less.  The important thing is sticking with the process and believing in it. I am sure this is going to pass as well, but for now I happy and it works for me. How do you keep yourself productive? Sound off in the comments</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Buffer - Smarter Social Sharing]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/buffer-smarter-social-sharing/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/buffer-smarter-social-sharing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Posts on this blog are published automatically on preset dates. I have created a custom workflow for this in Octopress, my blogging framework. If you are interested in the end to end workflow check out my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1YTjHWjepag">video on it</a>. Publishing to different social media was also one of the things that I wanted to automate in the whole workflow. So whenever a post is published to my blog, it also posts to the different social media (Twitter, Facebook, and LinkedIn).</p>

<p><a href="https://buffer.com/">Buffer</a> is a tool to manage all your social media networks and publish content to it at one. It is a &lsquo;<em>Write Once, Publish Everywhere</em>&rsquo; kind of service and works best for me. From the Buffer website or using <a href="https://buffer.com/extensions">browser extensions</a> posts can be manually buffered. A buffered post can be published immediately, scheduled to be shared next or scheduled for a particular date and time. You can have custom messages for each of the social network that you are sharing.</p>

<p><img src="/images/buffer_share.png" alt="Buffer Share" class="center" /></p>

<p>For automatic updates from my blog, I use <a href="https://buffer.com/guides/email">Buffer via Email</a>. With every buffer account, there is an associated email address. A post can be buffered by sending an email to this address in a specific format. So every time a new blog is published I send an email to my buffer account to publish immediately (@postnow). Automatic sharing posts also helps me reduce the time I spend on social networks; <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/life-learnings-after-being-a-parent/">learning to disconnect</a></p>

<p>I am on their <a href="https://buffer.com/pricing">Free plan</a> at present. I have only less than ten posts scheduled at any point in time, and the plan provides all the features I need.</p>

<p>Hope this helps you manage your social media content.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Went From Couch to Half Marathon in Twelve Weeks]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s about three months since I started running. I just completed my first half marathon and thought of putting together on how I have been going on with my running. I had a lot of questions myself when I started running, so hope this helps someone else taking the same journey.</p>

<div class="alert alert-warning">
<strong>DISCLAIMER!</strong> Just to make sure I get it right, I am not a doctor nor a professional runner. The below are just my personal experiences and has worked for me. If you feel you have a medical problem or are in need of professional help, please contact a professional. Always consult a doctor before starting a new diet or exercise program.
</div>


<h3>Tracking</h3>

<p>I started running using the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.runtastic.android&amp;hl=en">Runtastic</a> application on my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/">android phone</a>. The free version app offers most of the required features to start running. I upgraded to their <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/premium-membership">Premium version</a> primarily for <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/results">Runtastic Results</a>(more on it below).</p>

<p>Once I got regular with my runs I wanted better tracking, mainly to monitor heart rate. I was unsure of what a heart rate monitor would provide and if at all there is any value in getting one. I reached out to my runner friends, and all of them had one. Most of them had a Garmin, and a few had Fitbit. Until then I was planning to get the <a href="https://www.fitbit.com/au/charge2">Fitbit Charge 2</a> which comes with <a href="http://www.digitaltrends.com/wearables/whats-inside-fitness-tracker-anyway/#ixzz4cBARwI9q">optical heart rate monitoring</a>. It primarily uses an optical sensor and senses the heart rate from the wrist. The Garmin&rsquo;s make watches that are more <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-AU/AU/cIntoSports-cRunning-p1.html">specific for runners</a>, and since the majority of my friends owned Garmin, I decided on to get one of the Garmin Forerunner series.</p>

<p>One of the shops near to where I live was running a promotional offer on the <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-AU/AU/p/516105">Garmin Forerunner 630 Bundle</a>. But this model comes with a <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-AU/AU/p/530376">Heart Rate Monitor (HRM) Strap</a>. The strap needs to be worn around the chest during the run. Strap v Optical HRM added a new dimension of confusion to the whole tracker story. I reached out to my <a href="https://twitter.com/rahulpnath/status/835320810734694400">runner friends again</a> and surprisingly all of them had models of Garmin that uses an HRM Strap.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.wareable.com/garmin/garmin-forerunner-630-review">
<img alt="Garmin Forerunner 630 Bundle" class="center" src="/images/running_forerunner630.jpg" />
</a></p>

<p>The Garmin Forerunner 630 is a GPS SmartWatch with Advanced Running Metrics. It provides all the data a runner needs (and a lot more than what I need). Paired with HRM monitor it helps measure cadence, vertical oscillation and additional running dynamics like ground contact time balance, stride length and vertical ratio. I still don&rsquo;t understand all the data that it shows but find the GPS tracking, heart rate monitoring and zones, training plans and custom workouts a great help to my runs. Garmin also integrates well with <a href="https://www.strava.com/athletes/rahulpnath">Strava</a> where most of my other friends are there. The watch has a companion app on the phone and also a <a href="http://connect.garmin.com">website</a> which helps visualize the data.</p>

<h3>Exercise</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/results">Runtastic Results</a> provides a 12-week bodyweight training plan with the <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/premium-membership">premium subscription</a>. I am on week five of the training. It took a while for me to get started but now I try not to miss it. The free version of the app has all exercises available as stand-alone exercises. You can use these if you don&rsquo;t want to get the premium subscription.</p>

<p><img alt="Runtastic Results" class="center" src="/images/running_runtastic_results.png" /></p>

<p>I am following a diet to lose weight, and I weigh now 78 (±1) kilos and has been on that for around one month. I was around 95 when I started out with the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">running and diet</a>.</p>

<h3>Training</h3>

<p>During the first few weeks of running, I was mostly doing free runs and trying to cover the maximum distance possible. The tracked information was useful in isolation to a specific run, and I did not do anything to improve. I then started on a beginner training plan with Runtastic
to <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/users/4b76cfab-734e-1658-b5e4-600759a3b066/training-plans/747577">Run 50 min after 6 weeks</a>. This put me into the mode to compare my runs with the previous and work to improve on them. Now and then I wanted to stop the plan and continue with my normal run as I felt the plan wasn&rsquo;t working. But I decided to <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/psm-learnings/">stick to the process</a> until the end. On completion of the training, I was able to run continuously for fifty minutes, and that was a measurable improvement for me.</p>

<p><img alt="Runtastic Training Plan Certificate" src="/images/running_runtastic_certificate.png" /></p>

<p>My friend and colleague <a href="https://www.strava.com/athletes/12340841">Tony</a> is an avid runner. To improve on the pace, he advised starting shorter interval training. To improve pace, fix the pace to what you want to achieve and run for a specified interval (time or distance). Garmin enables you to create a custom workout setting various parameters on the run. The custom workout helps to keep up with your goals during the run.</p>

<p><img alt="Garmin Custom Workout" class="center" src="/images/running_garmin_workout.jpg" /></p>

<p>Running at a constant pace is important to help cover longer distances. Initially, I used to run with all my energy. So my pace often spiked and then fell and then spiked again. If you are training to improve your speed, it&rsquo;s hard to tell whether there is an improvement in speed unless you run at a constant (little variation) in speed. Check out the graph that plots your pace to check the pace variations. Most running applications show this information.</p>

<h3>Breathing</h3>

<p>Proper breathing is one the key things with running. I did not give much importance to breathing at first. I found it very hard to run long distances without stopping in between by following a random breathing pattern. There are different suggestions on breathing style. I found the article <a href="http://www.runnersworld.com/running-tips/running-on-air-breathing-technique">Running On Air: Breathing Technique</a> helpful and try to follow the pattern mentioned there (quoted below).</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The singular point of all rhythmic breathing patterns is this: Exhale on alternate footstrikes as you run. You never want to continually exhale on the same foot. The rhythmic breathing patterns I recommend call for a longer inhale than exhale. Why the longer inhale? Your diaphragm and other breathing muscles contract during inhalation, which brings stability to your core. These same muscles relax during exhalation, decreasing stability. With the goal of injury prevention in mind, it&rsquo;s best to hit the ground more often when your body is at its most stable—during inhalation. Let&rsquo;s start with a 5-count or 3:2 pattern of rhythmic breathing, which will apply to most of your running. Inhale for three steps and exhale for two.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I particularly liked the reference to yoga and meditation in the article. It gave the realization that running is a form of meditation. Establishing a breathing rhythm helped me run longer distances comfortably and without losing breath. If you want to get a deeper understanding of breath and how it affects our life I recommend reading the book <a href="http://amzn.to/2nkIlUQ">Science Of Breath</a>.</p>

<p>I ran my first <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/users/4b76cfab-734e-1658-b5e4-600759a3b066/sport-sessions/58d587fdd03a4c443e6d656c">Half Marathon</a> on 25th of March. I did at a casual pace to understand what it takes to run one. I tried to keep my pace between 6:15 - 6:30 min/km and was able to finish it at 6:19 min/km. It took me 2:13:11 hours and I am glad that I did not stop even once. It was more a mental game to stay at it than anything physical, and I am happy that I could finish it successfully! Hope this helps someone else as well starting off with running. Sound off in the comments if this helps you or some tips if you are already a runner!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Improved Code Navigation in Visual Studio 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/improved-code-navigation-in-visual-studio-2017/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/improved-code-navigation-in-visual-studio-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Visual Studio (VS) 2017 improves a lot on Code Navigation features.  If at all anything ever attracted me to ReSharper it was code navigation (though I have not been using it for a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/">couple of years now</a>). Visual Studio lacked behind in this aspect but not anymore. The new features help improve developer productivity and here are few I found worth looking.</p>

<p>In earlier versions, the navigation features are all over the menu. In VS2017 all the navigation features are available under <strong><em>Edit -> Go To</em></strong>. Though I usually prefer using the keyboard shortcut for opening the navigate dialogs, it&rsquo;s good to have all under the same menu.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio 2017 Code Navigation" src="/images/visualstudio_code_navigation.png" /></p>

<p><strong><em>Control + T</em></strong> brings up the Go To Dialog box which now has a lot more icons and options compared to the previous VS versions. Typing in &lsquo;<em>?</em>&rsquo; lists the different filtering criteria available when querying. It also allows searching across all the criteria by just not specifying the filtering criteria. To search for a file, type in &lsquo;<em>f FileName</em>&rsquo;. These filters also have direct shortcuts as shown in the image above.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio 2017 Go To Shortcuts" src="/images/visualstudio_goto.png" /></p>

<p>CamelCase search is the one that attracts me the most. By entering just the capital letters of the name it quickly filters out the particular class. As shown below by just typing <em>CSG</em> it brings up the class <strong>C</strong>har<strong>S</strong>equence<strong>G</strong>enerator. Typing in the full class name is no longer required and makes navigation faster.</p>

<p><img  class="center" alt="Visual Studio 2017 Go To Camel Case Matching" src="/images/visualstudio_camelcasematching.png" /></p>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p6NVTASKa1A">video</a> to see these features and more in action. Hope it helps!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
