<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-21T00:01:33+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Share and Inspire]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/share-and-inspire/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/share-and-inspire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started this blog around nine years back, my only intention was to share technical posts. But over period of time I started writing about a variety of things including <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/">productivity tips</a> that I found useful, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/travelogue/">travelogues</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/">random thoughts</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap/">personal goals</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/blogging/">blogging</a> etc. One of the things that I have noticed is that a lot of people have been inspired by these various posts and photos that I post online and have triggered them to do similar things.</p>

<p><img src="/images/share_and_inspire.jpg" alt="Share and Inspire, Image Source https://www.saylor.org/2015/04/blog-saylor-student-stories/" class="center"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had my own similar inspirations to start the various things that I do today. Like for instance, I started running after being inspired by my friends, <a href="https://twitter.com/SatyKrish">Satish</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/jeyakums">Suresh</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/thirusv">Thiru</a>. I reached out to them for various tips when I started running a year ago. From running I moved on to cycling and a bit of swimming after seeing my friend <a href="https://www.facebook.com/rahul.revikumar477977">Rahul</a>. For travel, my inspiration has been <a href="https://www.facebook.com/arun.sudheendran.1">Arun Sudheendran</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/deepak.suresh">Deepak Suresh</a> who do a fair bit of exploration. I tend to reach out to them for travel ideas and places to visit. Similarly, there have been inspirations from people that I have never met or met just once or twice.</p>

<p>Below is a transcript of a chat with one of my readers whom I have never met. It&rsquo;s a great feeling to wake up to such messages and it boosts your own motivation to continue what you are doing.</p>

<p><img src="/images/share_and_inspire_chat.png" alt="Share and Inspire" class="center"></p>

<p>Social media plays a great role in spreading information these days. When you see people in your own friend&rsquo;s circle start doing things that you have always wanted to, it gives you an extra push to give it a try. There might be some people who feel you are sharing too much of things that don&rsquo;t interest them. For those, there is always an option to un-follow, mute, filter etc. Don&rsquo;t let that thought stop you from sharing things that you do.</p>

<p>Such a small act of sharing, even things that you might have seen someone do could add up and be of big impact to someone else, often referred to as the <a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/TheButterflyEffectOfTechnologyCommunity.aspx">Butterfly Effect</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>The <strong>Butterfly Effect</strong>: This effect grants the power to cause a hurricane in China to a butterfly flapping its wings in New Mexico. It may take a very long time, but the connection is real. If the butterfly had not flapped its wings at just the right point in space/time, the hurricane would not have happened. - <a href="http://fractalfoundation.org/resources/what-is-chaos-theory/">Chaos Theory</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Share things that you do, share positive things and inspire others!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Text Editing - Extract Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/text-editing-extract-data/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/text-editing-extract-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At times you might need to extract data from a large text. Let&rsquo;s say you have a JSON response, and you want to extract all the <em>id</em> fields in the response and <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/text-editing-split-or-combine-multiple-lines/">combine them as comma separated</a>. Here&rsquo;s how you can easily extract data from large text using Sublime (or any other text editor that supports simultaneous editing).</p>

<pre><code class="json https://jsonplaceholder.typicode.com/posts">[
  {
    "userId": 1,
    "id": 1,
    "title": "sunt aut facere repellat provident occaecati excepturi optio reprehenderit",
    "body": "quia et suscipit\nsuscipit recusandae consequuntur expedita et cum\nreprehenderit molestiae ut ut quas totam\nnostrum rerum est autem sunt rem eveniet architecto"
  },
  {
    "userId": 1,
    "id": 2,
    "title": "qui est esse",
    "body": "est rerum tempore vitae\nsequi sint nihil reprehenderit dolor beatae ea dolores neque\nfugiat blanditiis voluptate porro vel nihil molestiae ut reiciendis\nqui aperiam non debitis possimus qui neque nisi nulla"
  },
  ...
]
</code></pre>

<p>Again the key here is to select the recurring pattern first. In this case, it is <em>&ldquo;id&rdquo;:</em> and then selecting all occurrences of that. Once all occurrences are selected, we can select the whole line and extract that out. Repeat the same to remove the <em>id</em> text. Then follow the same steps we used to <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/text-editing-split-or-combine-multiple-lines/">combine text</a>.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ouKm7Wkldp0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Hope this helps you to extract data from large text files.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Text Editing - Split or Combine Multiple Lines]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/text-editing-split-or-combine-multiple-lines/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/text-editing-split-or-combine-multiple-lines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a developer, I often end up needing to manipulate text. Sometimes this text can get quite large, and it might take a while to do it manually. If you have a text editor under your <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/">tool belt</a>, it often helps in situations like that. Let&rsquo;s looks at one of the common scenarios that I come across and how we can solve that using a text editor. I use <a href="https://www.sublimetext.com/">Sublime Text</a> as my go-to editor for such text editing hacks, but you can do this in any text editor that supports <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simultaneous_editing">simultaneous editing</a>.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say I just get a list of comma separated values and need to insert double (or single) quotes around each value to use in a SQL query. To demonstrate this, I ended up going to <a href="https://www.random.org/integers/">random.org</a> to generate a list of random values and had to use the same technique that I was to demonstrate as in the SQL query case. I generated 12 random numbers, and the site gave a tab separated list of values, as shown below.</p>

<pre><code class="text">91    66    31    11    90
80    1    24    48    61
61    66
</code></pre>

<p>I now need to convert this into a comma-separated list. Let&rsquo;s see how we can go about doing this.</p>

<ol>
<li>Select the recurring character pattern. In this case, it is the tab space.</li>
<li>Select all occurrences of the pattern. (Alt + F3 - Find All in Sublime)</li>
<li>Act on all the occurrences. In this case, I want to remove them, so I use <em>Del</em></li>
<li>Since I want to introduce a comma between each of the numbers, I first split them into multiple lines using <em>Enter</em>. Now I have all the numbers on a separate line.</li>
<li>Select all the numbers and insert a cursor at the end of each. ( Ctrl + Shift + L)</li>
<li>Insert comma. We still have the cursor at the end of all lines, so just pressing <em>Delete</em> again combines all the lines into one. Remove the trailing comma.</li>
</ol>


<div style="text-align: center;">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nDDWviJ5xHM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Though this is a specific example, I hope you get the general idea on how to go about manipulating text, to split and combine as required. I hope you will be able to insert double (or single) quotes around each value in the comma separated values that we have now, to use in a SQL query!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: The Headphones Rule]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/the-headphones-rule/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/the-headphones-rule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/headphone_rule.png" class="center" alt="The Headphones Rule" ></p>

<p>&lsquo;<em>I need some undistracted time</em>.&rsquo;</p>

<p>This was one of the things that came up in my team&rsquo;s retrospective yesterday. Having some undistracted time is necessary for getting things done. It&rsquo;s a good practice to have a consensus among the team members on how to manage disruptions and indicate whether you are open for a chat.</p>

<p><a href="http://theheadphonesrule.com/">The Headphone Rule</a> is an interesting way to indicate whether a person is open to interactions or not.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>no headphones, you can talk to me.</em></p>

<p><em>1 headphone, you can talk to me about work</em></p>

<p><em>2 headphones, do not talk to me.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>For people who do not use a headphone, some other technique needs to be used (like sticky notes, colored lights, etc.). Luckily in my team, everyone uses headphones, and it was an acceptable solution. Irrespective of the way you choose it is important to have some agreed way to indicate whether you are interruptible or not. It helps you and the team to have some undistracted time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Chocolatey - Install Softwares With Ease]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/chocolatey-install-softwares-with-ease/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/chocolatey-install-softwares-with-ease</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/chocolatey.png" alt="Chocolatey - Package Manager for Windows" class="center" ></p>

<p><a href="https://chocolatey.org/">Chocolatey</a> is a package manager for Windows. Chocolatey is a central store of applications, tools, and other packages. It allows you to install them on your computer from the command line. Let’s look at an example to make things more clear. Let’s say I want to install the Google Chrome Browser on my system. Below is how I would go about installing it.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Installing Google Chrome (Without Chocolatey)</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Bing for Google Chrome (Assuming that you are on Windows and open up Internet Explorer and search for Google Chrome)</li>
<li>Click the relevant link from the Search Results</li>
<li>Hit the Download Chrome button</li>
<li>Wait for the installer to download and open that to install.</li>
</ol>


<p><strong>Installing Google Chrome (With Chocolatey)</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Run &lsquo;<em>choco install googlechrome</em>&rsquo; from command line</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Installing with Chocolatey is quick and easy. You no longer need to go around searching the web for the software that you want to install. If you are unsure of the package name (e.g. googlechrome), you can search the entire packages library. This is possible from the command line using &lsquo;<em>choco search</em>.&rsquo; Or you can also search on their <a href="https://chocolatey.org/packages">website</a>.</p>

<p>Run the below script from the command line to <a href="https://chocolatey.org/install">install Chocolatey Package Manager</a>. Once installed you can start managing applications through the command line using Chocolatey.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">@"%SystemRoot%\System32\WindowsPowerShell\v1.0\powershell.exe" -NoProfile -ExecutionPolicy Bypass -Command "iex ((New-Object System.Net.WebClient).DownloadString('https://chocolatey.org/install.ps1'))" &amp;&amp; SET "PATH=%PATH%;%ALLUSERSPROFILE%\chocolatey\bin"
</code></pre>

<p>Other than installing and searching packages, Chocolatey also supports a lot of other commands to manage applications including un-installation. The entire commands supported are available <a href="https://chocolatey.org/docs/commandslist">here</a>. Instead, you can get the details in your command line using &lsquo;<em>choco -h</em>.&rsquo;</p>

<p>Hope that helps you save some time when you next want to install something.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
