<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-12T00:01:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Productivity Noise with Noisli]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/productivity-noise-with-noisli/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/productivity-noise-with-noisli</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are the kind of person that likes to listen to some music while working, then this one is for you. Music is proven to have significant effects on improving focus while working. But it is also quite possible to get fully immersed in the music and forget all about work. Different kinds of music contribute to improving concentration while not getting immersed in the music itself. I usually <a href="http://theheadphonesrule.com/">wear my headphones</a> at work while working and listen to music.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Music helps to minimize distractions and helps you reach a state of <a href="http://amzn.to/2jlYIgV">Flow</a>, which is ideal for improving productivity.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>At times I like to hear to just some background noises simulating different environments. <a href="https://www.noisli.com/">Noisli</a> is an application that helps mix different sounds and create your perfect environment. The sounds could either be working in a restaurant or while it&rsquo;s raining with thunder, in a forest, by the side of the fire, etc. It helps create the mood that you want and helps recreate it with sound. Since the noises are of a fixed pattern, you soon get used to it and improves concentration at work.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Noisli - Favorite Combos" src="/images/noisli_favorite.png" /></p>

<p>Here are my favorite mixes in Noisli.
<a href="https://www.noisli.com/get_combo_by_link/W5rvjLZXcoJbooq">Rain Mix</a>, <a href="https://www.noisli.com/get_combo_by_link/vjUpcG2OAXxKVSU">Jungle</a>, <a href="https://www.noisli.com/get_combo_by_link/uhRXMysAIcVEbHF">TRain</a>, <a href="https://www.noisli.com/get_combo_by_link/gFKhnETdoybxcmc">HotelRainFire</a></p>

<p>You can use Noisli directly from the <a href="https://www.noisli.com/">website</a> or use any of their <a href="https://www.noisli.com/apps">Apps and Extensions</a>. Find out what works for you and leave a comment on your favorite combos.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Paste Without Formatting]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/paste-without-formatting/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/paste-without-formatting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I share a lot of information copying and pasting from websites. Most of the times I want to share just the text and not any formatting. To remove any text formatting, I copy it into Notepad and then onto the destination. Yesterday I found that using <strong>Ctrl + Shift + V</strong> to paste (instead of <em>Ctrl + V</em>) removes all text formatting.</p>

<p>As shown, when using Ctrl + V the text gets copied along with the formatting as shown below.</p>

<p><img alt="Paste With Formatting" src="/images/paste_with_formatting.png" /></p>

<p>When using Ctrl + Shift + V, only the text gets copied and the formatting is ignored.
<img alt="Paste Without Formatting" src="/images/paste_without_formatting.png" /></p>

<p>Using this shortcut saves time as I no longer need to open Notepad for this!</p>

<p>PS: As one of my readers rightly pointed out (below in the comments), this might not work on all applications. I have tried this on Chrome Browser and Lync For Business and worked fine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Staying in the Learning Loop]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-in-the-learning-loop/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-in-the-learning-loop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The current state of the IT industry demands one to be constantly on the go and learning something new. New technologies, frameworks, languages etc. are getting released almost every other day. It is easy to get overwhelmed with all this information. The best way to keep up is to ignore most of it. But every now and then you would want to learn something new either because of project demands or out of personal interests. It is important to have a learning plan for yourself and stick through with it when wanting to learn something. If not it&rsquo;s easy to get distracted. These are some of the ways how I try to structure my learning.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.keele.ac.uk/media/keeleuniversity/lpdc/images/LPDC-Banner-Blue.jpg">
<img  alt="Make writing a habit - write daily" src="/images/learning_continuosly.png"/>
</a></p>

<h4><strong>Choosing and Sticking to a Topic</strong></h4>

<p>The most important thing in learning something new is to decide on what to learn. This could either be driven by work needs or personal interests. It&rsquo;s easier when driven by work needs as you do not have much to choose on. But still, you need to make sure that you stay within the boundaries of what you are trying to learn. It&rsquo;s easy to get off track as there might be a lot of things that come up which you are not aware of. At times understanding things with a certain level of abstraction is important. Just like social networks distracting you off from real work, different terminologies can get you off on a different path. So make sure you always stick to your end goal.</p>

<h4><strong>Books, Blogs, Videos</strong></h4>

<p>There are different ways that you can learn something new. It could either be books, videos, podcasts, blogs etc. There is no such thing as the best mode to learn. Mode of learning is person specific. So don&rsquo;t try to just imitate what your friend does. Try to find what works for you the best. Whenever I am learning something new, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/language-agnostic-books-for-every-developer-2/">books</a> work the best. Books give a structured approach to a new topic and eases your way through the topic. Though I have a Kindle, for technical books I <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/ebook-or-hard-copy/">prefer hard copies</a>. Often I find the need to refer back or forward a few pages and it feels best on a physical book.  I find blogs useful for learning more about a topic that I already have some idea about. For getting an overview of topics and interesting things I find videos and podcasts useful. So depending upon the need I mix and match these different learning modes.</p>

<p><img alt="Current Reading List" src="/images/learning_books.jpg"/></p>

<h4><strong>Open Source Projects, Forums, Demo application</strong></h4>

<p>It is important that you try out whatever your learn. There are different ways that you can learn by doing and depends on the individual. When learning a new topic I choose to come up with a sample application to be built using the new technology that I am learning. I created <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/store/p/picfinity/9wzdncrdwxx8">Picfinity</a> when I was learning Window 8 Modern applications. Once comfortable with a topic I choose to either answer <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count/">questions on forums</a> (mostly <a href="https://social.msdn.microsoft.com/profile/rahul%20p%20nath?type=forum&amp;referrer=http://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/azure/en-US/home?forum=AzureKeyVault">msdn</a> or <a href="http://stackexchange.com/users/2205373/rahul-p-nath">stack overflow</a>). Contributing to open source projects is also another approach to gets some hands-on experience. Contributing to open source projects also helps the community and improves your self-confidence. <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a> is a good place to start with open source contribution.</p>

<h4><strong>Freelancing</strong></h4>

<p>Not always you get to implement what you learn at your work. Implementing in real world projects is an important aspect of learning. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-freelancing-jobs-online/">Freelancing</a> is a good way to get work in areas that you want to improve or learn. Bid for projects that uses technologies that you are learning. It might be hard to get offered projects on technologies that you have no prior experience with. Showcasing any sample applications that you have built while learning increases your chances of getting the job. I used Picfinity to show that I can build Windows 8 and phone applications. This landed me opportunities to build different windows phone and windows 8 application.</p>

<h4><strong>Blog</strong></h4>

<p>Sharing your learnings helps improve your own understanding of the topic. It also helps others taking your same path and learning the new topic. Each one of us has a different perspective of understanding and learning things. So don&rsquo;t worry if you are writing about something that is already been written about. Make sure you blog your learnings and if you are new to blogging then there is no better time to <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/blogging/">get started</a>. Blogs act as a good resume when applying for a job.</p>

<p>With new technologies and frameworks coming up every other day it is hard to keep up with all of them. It is not necessary to understand everything that is out there. What is important is that you should be able to learn quickly when the need arises. Also keep yourself aware of the changes in the industry and technologies you use. It does not matter if you do not know all the latest technologies. What matters is how fast you can learn a new concept. Have a learning plan! What do you find the most effective way to learn? Sound off in the comments</p>

<p><strong>Edit:</strong> Came across this interesting <a href="http://hanselminutes.com/543/becoming-a-more-social-developer-with-daphne-chong">podcast on Hanselminutes</a> where Scott talks to Daphne.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maintaining a Blogging Schedule]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Consistency is important in blogging. It does not matter if you are bad at writing, have nothing to write or nobody reads your blog. What matters is whether you write on a predictable schedule - once a month, once a week, once a year, one per day etc. If you do not have a schedule you are more likely to fall off from sticking to blogging. I had <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/own-your-urls/">written before</a>, I always struggled to write regularly. But since the start of this year, I have been blogging to a schedule (once a week) and have been successful with that. This post looks into some of the challenges that I faced and things that I have incorporated to stick to a schedule.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/12389767@N04/3097124543/">
<img  alt="Make writing a habit - write daily" src="/images/bloggingSchedule_writedaily.jpg"/>
</a></p>

<h3>Make Writing a Habit</h3>

<p>Writing posts was hard and I always procrastinated on it. It often took me more than a week to complete a post. There&rsquo;s a saying, <strong><em>If it hurts, do it more often</em></strong> - So to make writing easy I had to write more often.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>I write only when inspiration strikes. Fortunately it strikes every morning at nine o&#8217;clock sharp.</em></p>

<p><em>- <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/302963-i-write-only-when-inspiration-strikes-fortunately-it-strikes-every">Somerset Maugham</a></em></p></blockquote>

<h4><strong>Generating Topics</strong></h4>

<p>Till a year back I struggled to find topics to blog. I did not find any &lsquo;cool thing&rsquo; that was worth blogging. Not much has changed even now on doing &lsquo;cool things&rsquo;. The only thing that changed was that I decided to write every day - no matter what I do or don&rsquo;t do.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>I have always struggled to find topics to blog, but then I realized all I need is to pay attention to things that I do daily</em></p></blockquote>

<p>A year back I asked <a href="https://simpleprogrammer.com/about-simple-programmer/">John Somnez from SimpleProgrammer</a> the same question.</p>

<p><img  alt="email to John Somnez (SimpleProgrammer) on finding a blogging schedule" src="/images/bloggingSchedule_john_email.png"/></p>

<p>Though I did not get a reply from John, it kept me thinking. Late last year I started a Daily challenge of &lsquo;<em>Generating at least one blog topic a day</em>&rsquo; for a month. I did not have to write anything, just find a topic to blog and add it to a OneNote list. I did this for a month and found that I had enough topics to write on. Since the challenge did not have anything to do with writing, I did not restrict my thoughts. This is when I realized that it is not the lack of topics that I don&rsquo;t blog, but the fear of writing. That&rsquo;s when I started the &lsquo;Write Everyday&rsquo; daily challenge.</p>

<h4><strong>Write Everyday</strong></h4>

<p>This is one of the most important things that I found to be able to write posts regularly - <strong>Write Everyday</strong>. Yes every day, no matter what happens, I write at least one line towards a post. Since the goal is to <em>Write just one line for a blog post</em>, I hardly miss this goal. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Keeping the goal small and simple</a> is a trick that I picked from the book Mini Habits and find it useful. You can follow this for anything that you want to make a habit.</p>

<h4><strong>Make it Visible</strong></h4>

<p>Seeing something progressing to completion helps me to get it done faster. I used to write elsewhere and then copy it to my blog and publish it. This did not give me a sense of progression. I now have a <a href="/blog/optimizing-octopress-workflow-for-new-posts/">draft post workflow</a>, integrated with my blogging platform. I can preview this blog along with the draft posts on my laptop. This helps give a sense of progression and also makes the end goal visible.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Making your goal clear and visible helps you achieve it faster</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I also use this to keep track of new post ideas. Whenever I find a topic to blog, I add it as a draft. I add bullet points to the post whenever I get more thoughts on that topic. Once there are enough points to write about, I work on that post.</p>

<h3>Make Blogging All About Writing</h3>

<p>The last thing that I want is to get stuck with mundane repetitive tasks of publishing a post to get in the way of writing. The more regular I became in writing, I started noticing a lot of repetitive tasks in my blogging workflow. When you do any activity repetitively you notice tasks that you do over and over again. I started modifying my blog engine for my needs and to reduce manual effort.</p>

<h4><strong>Write in Advance</strong></h4>

<p>Having posts ready to be published is helpful as it gives the flexibility to slack a bit when in need. It&rsquo;s a great feeling to have blog posts ready to be published (right now I have posts ready for a month). I modified my blogging engine to support <a href="/blog/automatic_deployment_of_future_posts_with_octopress">publishing posts on future dates</a>. This helps me set publishing dates in the future for posts and it gets automatically deployed on the day. Automating the publishing helped make blogging more about writing. I can forget about it as soon as I complete a post by specifying the date I want it to be published and be rest assured that it will get published.</p>

<h4><strong>Make Writing Accessible</strong></h4>

<p>You never know when you have that free time and want to blog. Maybe it&rsquo;s while traveling, or waiting in a queue or at your work desk. You might be <a href="/blog/staying-productive-offline">offline or connected</a> Making it possible to write from irrespective of the kind of device (laptop, mobile, tablet) and connectivity was key for me. I have my draft posts synchronized through Dropbox and available on all my devices. This helps use all the pockets of time that I get for myself.</p>

<p>These are the things that have helped me pick a schedule and follow it. I have been successful in publishing one post per week for the past 10 months and want to keep at it going forward. Now that I am able to publish regularly, I want to improve the speed at which I write posts. Though I reduced the time from over a week to days, I still find this too long and want to reduce it to a day. Modifying the way images are added, optimized and served is also something that I am trying to optimize currently. Do you <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/own-your-urls/">have a blog</a>? If not start one and stick to a schedule that works for you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Six Months and Counting - Logitech MX Master]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-six-months-and-counting-logitech-mx-master/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-six-months-and-counting-logitech-mx-master</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been six months with the <a href="http://amzn.to/2ddLmUf">Logitech MX Master</a> mouse and I absolutely love it for daily use. I picked this mouse a week after reading <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/FindingThePerfectMouse.aspx">Hanselman&rsquo;s review</a>. It feels just as it sounded in his review - Perfect!.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/mx-master">
    <img  alt="Logitech MX Master" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster.jpg"/>
</a></p>

<h4><strong>Key Features</strong></h4>

<ul>
<li><p>The mouse fits perfectly into the hand and supports the wrist in a native position. It is suitable for long duration use.</p></li>
<li><p>The battery is rechargeable and the mouse comes with a micro-USB charging cable. After a full charge, the mouse lasts me for 2-3 weeks.   The mouse can be used while charging, so there is no downtime. The LED lights indicate the charge status. If not the software also warns when the battery is low.</p></li>
<li><p>I connect the mouse using the Logitech Unifying Receiver. But the mouse also supports connecting over Bluetooth. This is useful in cases when you want to connect with multiple computers.</p></li>
<li><p>The mouse supports Easy Switch technology.  You can pair up to 3 devices and switch between them using buttons on the bottom side of the mouse. I have not used this feature as I mostly work on just one laptop.</p></li>
<li><p>Darkfield Laser Sensor tracks flawlessly over all surfaces. I use the MX Master across wooden and glass surfaces and find it smooth over both.</p></li>
<li><p>The mouse scroll supports smooth scrolling and &lsquo;Ratchet&rsquo; mode (click, click, click) scroll. It supports automatic and manual mode shifting. So when reading long documents you can be on smooth scrolling and when navigating code or shorter texts you can use Ratchet mode to feel greater control. It also has buttons to</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The mouse has an accompanying software that allows customizations of mouse buttons.</p>

<p><img  alt="Logitech MX Master Software" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster_software.png"/></p>

<p>The software allows setting application specific actions for buttons. For e.g. I have the Gesture button to archive emails in Outlook, &lsquo;Navigate to Definition&rsquo; in Visual Studio, close tab in Chrome etc. You can configure this to any action on applications of your choice (provided it supports keyboard shortcuts that can be linked to).</p>

<p><img  alt="Logitech MX Master Software customizations" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster_customize.png"/></p>

<h4><strong>Issue</strong></h4>

<p>The only issue that I faced so long is with the Mouse scroll mode. The &lsquo;Ratchet&rsquo; mode no longer works for me. It is always in smooth scrolling mode and the mechanical key to shift modes does not work anymore. Google tells me that this is a <a href="https://community.logitech.com/s/question/0D531000051026rCAA">common issue</a> with the mouse .
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KR9fLd_ViYw">This video</a> walks through on how to open up the mouse and fix the mechanical part that clicks in to switch the scroll modes. I have not tried this myself as I don&rsquo;t feel much a problem without the Ratchet mode.</p>

<p>Other than the Ratchet mode issue, I have not found any other issues with the mouse.</p>

<div align="center">
<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:41.712962963% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BC11BabgPpV/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Trying out the logitech mx master mouse. Liking it!</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Rahul P Nath (@rahulpnath) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-03-12T05:22:06+00:00">Mar 11, 2016 at 9:22pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>
<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>
</div>


<p><br />
If you are looking for a new mouse and willing to spend a little more than usual, I recommend the <a href="http://amzn.to/2ddLmUf">Logitech MX Master</a>. What mouse do you use?</p>

<p>* <em>Amazon links are affiliated.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
