<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-01T00:01:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Left Align Your Code For Better Readability]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/left-align-your-code-for-better-readability/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/left-align-your-code-for-better-readability</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Aesthetics of code is as important as the code you write. Aligning is an important part that contributes to the overall aesthetics of code. The importance of code aesthetics struck me while on a recent project. Below are some the code samples that I came across in the project. Traversing this code base was painful to me as the code was all over the place.</p>

<pre><code class="csharp Bad Formatting">public class Account
{
    public long   Id                    { get; set; }
    public string ClientId              { get; set; }
    public long   ContactId             { get; set; }
    public string UserName              { get; set; }
    public string Name                  { get; set; }
    public string Company               { get; set; }
    public string Address               { get; set; }
    public string BillingAddress        { get; set; }
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="csharp Bad Formatting">public ConnectToServer(string username, 
                       string password,
                       string server,
                       string port)
{
    ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>The code has too many alignment points that attract the eye which makes it hard to read in the first place. When in isolation this might still be fine to read, but with such a style across the code base, it soon becomes a pain for your eyes and your mind. When refactoring code, it becomes even harder as you need to put in the extra effort to make sure that this fancy alignment is maintained. Let&rsquo;s take a look at how even changing a property name (<em>Company to CompanyName</em>) or function name(<em>ConnectToServer to Connect</em>) will affect the current formatting.</p>

<pre><code class="csharp Renamed to CompanyName">public class Account
{
    ...
    public string Name              { get; set; }
    public string CompanyName           { get; set; }
    public string Address           { get; set; }
    ...
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="csharp Renamed to Connect">public Connect(string username, 
                       string password,
                       string server,
                       string port)
{
    ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see above the formatting is now all over the place, and you need to format them into place manually. Again when in isolation this might seem like a few press of spacebar. But when the property/function that you rename is used in multiple places this soon becomes a problem. Such code formatting introduces maintenance overhead and soon falls out of place if something gets missed.</p>

<h3>Better Ways To Format Code</h3>

<p>Left aligning code is one of the key things that I try to follow always. Keeping the code aligned to the left makes it easier to read (assuming that you are programming in a language written from left to right). Since we read from left to right having most of the code aligned to the left means that you have more code visible. Left aligning also means that you would almost avoid the need to scroll the code editor when reading through the code horizontally.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look how left aligning the above code will look like.</p>

<pre><code class="csharp Left Aligned">public class Account
{
    public long Id { get; set; }
    public string ClientId { get; set; }
    public long ContactId { get; set; }
    public string UserName { get; set; }
    public string Name { get; set; }
    public string Company { get; set; }
    public string Address { get; set; }
    public string BillingAddress { get; set; }
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="csharp Left Aligned Multiple Lines">public ConnectToServer(
    string username, 
    string password,
    string server,
    string port)
{
    ...
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="csharp Left Aligned Single Line">public ConnectToServer(
    string username, string password, string server, string port)
{
    ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see above left aligning makes it much easier to read and also reduces the number of alignment points. This is also refactoring friendly as there are no specific space patterns that need to be maintained. As for the parameters in a single line VS parameters in multiple lines (as above), I prefer the multi-line approach, as it keeps the code further aligned to the left and also reduces the chance of getting a horizontal scroll bar. You can use <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/introducing-code-formatting-into-a-large-codebase/">Column Guides</a> to remind yourself to keep the code within the acceptable horizontal space.</p>

<p>Code formatting is an important aspect of coding. It is important that as a team you need to agree on some standard practices and find ways to stick to it. You can use <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/introducing-code-formatting-into-a-large-codebase/">styling tools</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/code-review/">Code Reviews</a>, etc. to make sure it does not get missed. It takes a while for any new practices to set in, but soon it will be of second nature and easy to follow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Using Git Locally in a TFVC Repository]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/using-git-locally-in-a-tfvc-repository/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/using-git-locally-in-a-tfvc-repository</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The project that I am currently working on using <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/docs/tfvc/overview">Team Foundation Version Control</a>(TFVC) as it&rsquo;s source control. After <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/git-checkout-tfs/">using Git</a> for a long time it felt hard to move back to TFVC. One of the biggest pain for me is losing the short commits that I do when working. Short commits help keep track of the work and also quickly revert unwanted changes. Branching is also much easier with Git and allows to switch between work without much hassle of &lsquo;<em>shelving -> undoing -> pulling back the latest as with TFS.</em>&rsquo;</p>

<p><img src="/images/tfvc_local_git.png" alt="Use Git Locally in a TFVC Repository" class="center" /></p>

<p>The best part with git is that you can use it to work with any folder in your system and does not need any setup. By just running &lsquo;<em><a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-init">git init</a></em>&rsquo; it initializes a git repository in the folder. Running <em>init</em> against my local TFVC source code folder, I initialized a git repository locally. Now it allows me to work locally using git - make commits, revert, change branches, etc. Whenever I reach a logical end to the work, I create a shelveset and push the changes up the TFVC source control from Visual Studio.</p>

<p>If you want to interact with the TFVC source control straight from the command line, you can try out <a href="https://github.com/git-tfs/git-tfs">git-tfs</a> - a Git/TFS bridge. For me, since I am happy working locally with git and pushing up the finished work as shelvesets from Visual Studio I have not explored the git-tfs tool.</p>

<p>Hope this helps someone if you feel stuck with TFVC repositories!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Start New Habits That Stick]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/start_new_habits_that_stick/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/start_new_habits_that_stick</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><em>The beginning of a good habit is the elimination of an excuse.</em>   <br/>
<em>And The beginning of a bad habit is the finding of an excuse</em></p></blockquote>

<p>The ability to pick on something and to make a habit of it is something that is always helpful. This skill helps to create new habits and also let go off old ones that are not doing any good to you. Part of letting of bad old habits might be creating new ones. When I wrote about <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">Couch to Half Marathon</a>, some of my readers asked how to keep up with the plan. How to do &lsquo;Couch to Street&rsquo;; just getting out there.</p>

<p><a href= "https://quotefancy.com/quote/20375/Jim-Rohn-Motivation-is-what-gets-you-started-Habit-is-what-keeps-you-going">
    <img alt="Motivation is what gets you started. Habit is what keeps you going" src="/images/habit.jpg" class="center" />
</a></p>

<h3>How Habits Work</h3>

<p>To form new habits, it is important that we understand <a href="http://charlesduhigg.com/how-habits-work/">how habits work</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>a simple neurological loop at the core of every habit, a loop that consists of three parts: <strong>A cue, a routine and a reward.</strong></em></p></blockquote>

<p>As Charles Duhigg points out in his book, Power Of Habits (<a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc">recommended read</a>) the formula for changing habits differs from habit and persons. So it is more about using a framework to understand how habits work and experimenting on changing it. Changing a habit does take time and is not an easy one, but with a process in place, it is doable with time and effort.</p>

<p><img src="/images/habit_loop.jpg" class="center" alt="Cue-Routine-Reward Habit Loop" /></p>

<p>To break a bad habit one needs to identify it first. It could be anything from spending too much time on social media, eating unhealthy food, smoking, drinking, etc. Identifying that you have a habit and it&rsquo;s not good for you to continue with it is important. You can only change something once you identify it.</p>

<p>Once you recognize the habit, find out what is the trigger for the habit. Is it a particular place, people, time, etc. It might be hard to find the specific cue that triggers the habit, so note down everything that you find applicable. Then work on to isolate the cue by monitoring the habit over a couple of days. Wire up the cue that triggers the habit to perform some other action. Create that plan in advance and have some way to remind yourself of it. If your cue is time-based or location based, then you can use your smartphone to pop-up a reminder. If not try to find ways to keep yourself reminded to perform the new plan. It feels hard in the beginning but stick to the plan, and in time you will be able to change your habit. I recommend you to read the book <a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc">Power of Habits</a> to understand this subject better.</p>

<h3>Mini Habits and Short Term Goals</h3>

<p>To start creating new habits, I have found setting smaller goals to target daily works better. I began writing at least one line every day to be <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/">consistent in blogging</a>, running at least once a week to establish an exercise routine, eat at least one meal healthy, etc. Time-based cues help to enforce such new behavior. Setting aside a specific time as per the desired frequency to perform the activity makes sure that you do not skip doing it. Also, remember to keep the action as simple as possible so that you do not procrastinate when the time comes.</p>

<p>Like if it is running that you are planning to start it could be -  <em>Every Saturday at 6 am I will wear my running shoes and get out of my house</em>. When the time comes, this is such a simple task that you have set for yourself, and you are more likely to do it. Once you have taken the pain of putting the shoes and getting out of the couch, you are more likely to run for at least five minutes.</p>

<p>Break your goals into small and achievable mini goals. These mini goals are often referred to as <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Most Important Tasks (MIT)</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Big Rocks</a> etc. The key is to break them down into smaller achievable mini-goals and setting a cue to trigger the activity.</p>

<h3>Motivation and Its Role</h3>

<p>Very often we get motivated to start new activities and begin with great enthusiasm. In the beginning, we feel a spike in energy and see things happening. But soon you hit a point where you feel nothing is moving and you feel it a burden to continue. This stage is referred to as <em>plateau - a state of little or no change following a period of activity or progress.</em> You soon see your motivation levels dropping and justifying to yourself how little or no benefit your actions have. Eventually, you find yourself losing entire interest in the activity and start looking for new motivation spikes. This has happened to me many times.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Motivation is what gets you started.Habit is what keeps you going.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I have found this to be entirely true. We need the motivation to help us to get started with new activities and set new goals. But motivation alone cannot help us go all the way and achieve what we want. Before jump-starting with the idea give it a good thought to check if it is worth your time spent. If not park the idea to your <a href="http://gettingthingsdone.com/2010/10/what-goes-on-a-someday-maybe-list/">Someday Maybe list</a> (as referred to in <a href="http://amzn.to/2gsJaed">GTD</a>).</p>

<p>Once you have decided to pursue the idea, break it into smaller pieces and set achievable &lsquo;mini goals.&rsquo; Set dedicated time at regular intervals for achieving these mini-goals. Most important is in having some &lsquo;me time&rsquo; to get towards these goals. Like for me I have found that <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">mornings work best for me</a> and created a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Morning Routine</a>. To make sure that I make the best of my time I try to work in <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Pomodoro&rsquo;s and inspect and adapt the process</a> often.</p>

<h3>Tracking and Feedback</h3>

<p>Tracking is an important part of habit formation. Once you have set your goals and mini habits also find ways to track your progress. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/psm-learnings/">Inspect and Adapt</a> is the fundamental principle behind Agile Processes. Habit formation is nothing but being agile, keeping the end goal in mind, adjusting the way you reach there. Find ways and tools to track progress on the habits that you are trying to form.</p>

<p>I prefer automatic tracking with least manual entry, so the tracking happens in the background. But at times you will have to resort to manual methods as well. Make sure you have a time set aside daily to capture the information. Having a review of the data obtained once every week or two and taking adjustment actions is equally important. Some of the tracking tools that I use are <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/rescue-time-track-your-time/">Rescue Time</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">Garmin Forerunner 630</a> and a few manual ones. I [review my progress every week] and try to incorporate feedback into the upcoming week.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>All it takes to start a new habit is a moment - The moment where you decide on the new habit. The rest is process!</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">Eating Healthy, Exercise</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/">Blogging</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">Waking up Early</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Reducing time spent on Social Media, Reading</a> and <strike><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/recording-my-first-screencast/">Creating Videos</a></strike> (looking to give this up) are some of the habits that I have formed following these techniques. The ability to decide on something and getting it to done is the most important of all. Once you have mastered the skill of forming new habits, it boils down to choosing good habits and wiring that into your life. I have heard about the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jasonselk/2013/04/15/habit-formation-the-21-day-myth/">21-Day rule of habit formation</a> and similar myths. But I think all it takes to start a new habit is a moment - The moment where you decide on the new habit. The rest is process!</p>

<p><strong>References:</strong></p>

<div>
   <div class="row">
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
         <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc" >
            <img alt="Power Of Habit" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_powerofhabit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
         <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://amzn.to/2hmeokB">
            <img alt="Superhuman by Habit" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_superhumanbyhabit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;" >
            </a>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Feedly - One Stop Reading Place]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/feedly-one-stop-reading-place/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/feedly-one-stop-reading-place</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you want a one stop reading place to stay current and updated with posts from various blogs of your interest?</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Feedly is a news aggregator application that compiles news feeds from a variety of online sources</em></p></blockquote>

<p> <a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a> is what you are looking for. You can subscribe to the sites and news sources that you want to follow and Feedly shows that as a combined list for you.</p>

<p>News sources can be grouped into custom collections to group similar categories of information. Feedly offers a clean and minimalist reading experience, removing all the ads and other elements that create clutter. You can save articles to be read later, mark as favorite, share articles and a lot more.</p>

<p><img src="/images/feedly_site.png" class="center" alt="Feedly" /></p>

<p>Feedly has <a href="https://feedly.com/apps.html">apps and browser plugins</a> for a broad range of platforms and provides a uniform experience across devices. Currently, I am on the free version of the application, and it has a limit of 100 feeds. The <a href="https://feedly.com/i/pro/">pro version</a> provides a lot more features if you are interested.</p>

<p>Get a one stop reading place, Get <a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Todoist Template Transformer - Transform Tasks to 'X' Days From Now]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-template-transformer-transform-tasks-to-x-days-from-now/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-template-transformer-transform-tasks-to-x-days-from-now</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/todoist_templates.png" alt="Todoist Templates" class="center" /></p>

<p><a href="https://blog.todoist.com/2015/11/19/new-way-to-create-todoist-templates/">Todoist Templates</a> is a simple way to create tasks for any of your recurring activities. Be it blogging, cooking, or any of your activities. With Todoist Templates, you can turn any project into a checklist that you can easily duplicate later. I have been using <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-manage-your-todo-list/">Todoist</a> for a long time and find it useful to keep track of tasks (both personal and at work)</p>

<h4><strong>Problem</strong></h4>

<p>I <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">plan my tasks</a> for the upcoming week on Sunday morning. I pull in tasks for the upcoming week, and some of these tasks are template based. For e.g. for writing a blog post, I have the below template</p>

<pre><code class="text">TYPE,CONTENT,PRIORITY,INDENT,AUTHOR,RESPONSIBLE,DATE,DATE_LANG,TIMEZONE
task,Blog: BlogTopic,4,1,Rahul (3565260),,,en,Australia/Melbourne
task,BlogTopic: Draft Body,4,2,Rahul (3565260),,today,en,Australia/Melbourne
task,BlogTopic: Refine Body,4,2,Rahul (3565260),,today,en,Australia/Melbourne
task,BlogTopic: Intro and Conclusion,4,2,Rahul (3565260),,tomorrow,en,Australia/Melbourne
task,"BlogTopic: Images, Proof Read and Publish",4,2,Rahul (3565260),,tomorrow,en,Australia/Melbourne
</code></pre>

<p>The dates on the template are relative to the day that you import the template in Todoist. So if I pull in the template on a Sunday, the tasks will start on Sunday. This is not something that I want; I want them to start on a Monday. Alternatively, I can update the template to start from tomorrow. Even in that case, I will always have to know the exact start day relative to the day that I intend to pull in. I usually plan for the tasks on a Sunday but still, like the flexibility to pull in tasks any day of the week.</p>

<h3>Todoist Template Transformer</h3>

<p>The Todoist Template Transformer takes in a date and template path and adjusts all tasks in the template to start relative to the passed in date. In the above example, if I want to blog on Wednesday, I will input the Wednesday date and the template file path. The first two tasks will start on Wednesday and the third and fourth on Thursday. Running the transformer on a Sunday (07-May-2017) with the next Wednesday (10-May-2017) below is the new template</p>

<pre><code class="bat">TodoistTemplateTransformer.exe -startDate "10-May-2017" -templateFile "Blog Template.csv"
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="text">TYPE,CONTENT,PRIORITY,INDENT,AUTHOR,RESPONSIBLE,DATE,DATE_LANG,TIMEZONE
task,Blog: BlogTopic,4,1,Rahul (3565260),,,en,Australia/Melbourne
task,BlogTopic: Draft Body,4,2,Rahul (3565260),,in 3 days,en,Australia/Melbourne
task,BlogTopic: Refine Body,4,2,Rahul (3565260),,in 3 days,en,Australia/Melbourne
task,BlogTopic: Intro and Conclusion,4,2,Rahul (3565260),,in 4 days,en,Australia/Melbourne
task,"BlogTopic: Images, Proof Read and Publish",4,2,Rahul (3565260),,in 4 days,en,Australia/Melbourne
</code></pre>

<p>This utility is written in FSharp the <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/todoisttemplatetransformer">source code is available here</a> if you are interested. I am still in the initial stages of learning FSharp, so if you have any suggestions to improve the code, please raise a Pull Request or drop in a comment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
