<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-21T00:02:48+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Optimizing Octopress Workflow for New Posts]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/optimizing-octopress-workflow-for-new-posts/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-20T22:51:03+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/optimizing-octopress-workflow-for-new-posts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past month I had thought of migrating this blog to Hugo, a static site generator that is faster than the current one, Octopress. Lack of workflow for creating new posts and slower build times were the main reasons. I am the kind of person when writing post want to see often, how it looks like on the real site. With the current number of posts it takes around 40-50 seconds to build the entire site and it makes me to wander off to something else while the build is happening - at times it takes a long time to get back to writing!. But migrating to a new platform has a lot of challenges and time-consuming and I did not want to invest my time in that, so though of looking out for ways to optimize the current process. A bit of googling and playing around with Ruby, solved both of the major issues and I have an improved workflow!</p>

<h4><strong>Draft workflow</strong></h4>

<p>I was lucky to find this <a href="http://neverstopbuilding.com/how-to-enhance-your-octopress-draft-and-heroku-deploy-process">post</a> which handled most of the draft workflow process. Most of the code below is used from there with a very few minor additions. Newer versions of Jekyll support <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/docs/drafts/">working with drafts</a> and uses the &lsquo;<em>&ndash;drafts</em>&rsquo; switch to build the drafts (instead of using published flag as in thr above linked post), that are in &lsquo;<em>_drafts</em>&rsquo; folder. Drafts are posts which does not have date&rsquo;s, so I added in a placeholder text, &lsquo;<em>thisIsStillADraft</em>&rsquo;, in the yaml front matter of the post which will later be replaced with the post publish date. Also added in the code to open the default writer with the newly created post</p>

<pre><code class="ruby Rake new_draft"># usage rake new_draft[my-new-draft] or rake new_draft['my new draft']
desc "Begin a new draft in #{source_dir}/#{drafts_dir}"
task :new_draft, :title do |t, args|
  if args.title
    title = args.title
  else
    title = get_stdin("Enter a title for your post: ")
  end
  raise "### You haven't set anything up yet. First run `rake install` to set up an Octopress theme." unless File.directory?(source_dir)
  mkdir_p "#{source_dir}/#{drafts_dir}"
  filename = "#{source_dir}/#{drafts_dir}/#{title.to_url}.#{new_post_ext}"
  if File.exist?(filename)
    abort("rake aborted!") if ask("#{filename} already exists. Do you want to overwrite?", ['y', 'n']) == 'n'
  end
  puts "Creating new draft: #{filename}"
  open(filename, 'w') do |post|
    post.puts "---"
    post.puts "layout: post"
    post.puts "title: \"#{title.gsub(/&amp;/,'&amp;amp;')}\""
    post.puts "comments: true"
    post.puts "categories: "
    post.puts "tags: "
    post.puts "thisIsStillADraft:"
    post.puts "keywords: "
    post.puts "description: "
    post.puts "---"
  end
  system %{cmd /c "start #{filename}"}
end
</code></pre>

<p>The publish draft task just asks for the post to publish and replaces the placeholder text with the current date time. Also it moves the post from the &lsquo;<em>_drafts</em>&rsquo; folder to the &lsquo;<em>_posts</em>&rsquo; folder with the file name appended with the date time. Since I run this just before deploying a post, the date on the post will be the actual publish date, and not the date I started writing the post (usually writing a  post spans over multiple days).</p>

<pre><code class="ruby Rake publish_draft"># usage rake publish_draft
desc "Select a draft to publish from #{source_dir}/#{drafts_dir} on the current date."
task :publish_draft do
  drafts_path = "#{source_dir}/#{drafts_dir}"
  drafts = Dir.glob("#{drafts_path}/*.#{new_post_ext}")
  drafts.each_with_index do |draft, index|
    begin
      content = File.read(draft)
      if content =~ /\A(---\s*\n.*?\n?)^(---\s*$\n?)/m
        data = YAML.load($1)
      end
    rescue =&gt; e
      puts "Error reading file #{draft}: #{e.message}"
    rescue SyntaxError =&gt; e
      puts "YAML Exception reading #{draft}: #{e.message}"
    end
    puts "  [#{index}]  #{data['title']}"
  end
  puts "Publish which draft? "
  answer = STDIN.gets.chomp
  if /\d+/.match(answer) and not drafts[answer.to_i].nil?
    mkdir_p "#{source_dir}/#{posts_dir}"
    source = drafts[answer.to_i]
    filename = source.gsub(/#{drafts_path}\//, '')
    dest = "#{source_dir}/#{posts_dir}/#{Time.now.strftime('%Y-%m-%d')}-#{filename}"
    puts "Publishing post to: #{dest}"
    File.open(source) { |source_file|
      contents = source_file.read
      contents.gsub!(/^thisIsStillADraft:$/, "date: #{Time.now.strftime('%Y-%m-%d %H:%M')}")
      File.open(dest, "w+") { |f| f.write(contents) }
    }
    FileUtils.rm(source)
  else
    puts "Index not found!"
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>With these two new rake tasks, I can now create as many draft posts at a time and publish them once ready.</p>

<h4><strong>Improving the build time</strong></h4>

<p>Jekyll build command options provides a switch, &lsquo;<em>configuration</em>&rsquo;, that allows to pass a configuration file instead of using &lsquo;<em>_config.yml</em>&rsquo;. In the configuration file we can specify a &lsquo;exclude&rsquo; option to exclude the directories and/or files from the build. I created a new task for building only the current drafts, by specifying the &lsquo;<em>&ndash;drafts</em>&rsquo; switch and a dynamically generated configuration file, <em>_previewconfig.yml</em>, which excludes the &lsquo;<em>_posts</em>&rsquo; folder. This dramatically increases the build time, and completes almost immediately after a making a change to a post. This fits perfectly into my workflow, as while writing new posts I do not want to see any already published posts. You can  add the dynamically generated configuration file name to the <em>.gitignore</em> as I do not delete it in the tasks. I did not want to use the &lsquo;<em>rake isolate</em>&rsquo; task that is already present in the  rakefile, as that does not integrate with the draft workflow and unnecessarily moves all the posts to a temporary place.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">desc "preview the site in a web browser with all the draft posts"
task :previewdrafts do
  raise "### You haven't set anything up yet. First run `rake install` to set up an Octopress theme." unless File.directory?(source_dir)
  puts "Starting to watch source with Jekyll and Compass. Starting Rack on port #{server_port}"
  system "compass compile --css-dir #{source_dir}/stylesheets" unless File.exist?("#{source_dir}/stylesheets/screen.css")
  File.open("_config.yml") { |source_file|
      contents = source_file.read
      File.open("_previewconfig.yml", "w+") { |f|
      f.write(contents)
      f.puts("exclude: [\"#{posts_dir}\"]") 
      }
    }

  jekyllPid = Process.spawn({"OCTOPRESS_ENV"=&gt;"preview"}, "jekyll build --watch --drafts --config _previewconfig.yml")
  compassPid = Process.spawn("compass watch")
  rackupPid = Process.spawn("rackup --port #{server_port}")

  trap("INT") {
    [jekyllPid, compassPid, rackupPid].each { |pid| Process.kill(9, pid) rescue Errno::ESRCH }
    exit 0
  }

  [jekyllPid, compassPid, rackupPid].each { |pid| Process.wait(pid) }
end
</code></pre>

<h4><strong>Dropbox integration</strong></h4>

<p>At times, I have started to draft blog posts while commuting to work from my mobile device, so I wanted to sync my draft posts to <a href="https://db.tt/bvYw3pL6">Dropbox</a>, so that I can edit it from my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/">mobile phone</a>. Apps like <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.keepzero.markdrop&amp;hl=en">MarkDrop</a>/<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.keepzero.markdrop&amp;hl=en">JotterPad</a> integrates with Dropbox and supports Markdown editing. I set up a drafts folder on my Dropbox folder on laptop, which is automatically synced using the <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/install">Dropbox application</a>. I then used <a href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc753194.aspx">Mklink</a> to create a symbolic link from the folder on Dropbox to my drafts folder in my blog repository. Whenever a new draft post is added, it gets automatically inserted into the Dropbox folder, which will then be synced to cloud and available for edit on my mobile phone too. (Part of this post is written from my mobile!)</p>

<pre><code class="text">mklink /D "C:\blog\_drafts" "C:\dropbox\_drafts"
</code></pre>

<h4><strong>Cmder integration</strong></h4>

<p><a href="http://cmder.net/">Cmder</a> is a portable console emulator for Windows and provides a good nice looking feature rich console experience on Windows and is one of my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/">favourite tools</a>. Creating alias for commands is one of the features, that allows to create a short key combination for an otherwise long command. You can use this to create commands for the task in Octopress like below</p>

<pre><code class="text">alias rp=rake previewdrafts

// Below are the list of alias that I have for the rake tasks
rp=rake previewdrafts
rps=rake preview // Preview the whole site
rd=rake deploy
rnd=rake new_draft["$"] // Takes in the post name as parameter
rpd=rake publish_draft
rd=rake deploy
</code></pre>

<p><strong>So my new workflow is</strong></p>

<p>rnd Optimizing Octopress Workflow for New Posts <br/>
rp <br/>
rpd <br/>
rps <br/>
rd</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s much faster, cleaner and easier publishing new posts. To see the latest code for the rake tasks head over to the original file on <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com/blob/master/Rakefile">github</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Organizing Tests into Test Suites for Visual Studio]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/organizing-tests-into-test-suites-for-visual-studio/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-18T22:51:03+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/organizing-tests-into-test-suites-for-visual-studio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While working with large code base, that has a lot of tests (unit, integration, acceptance etc), running all of them every time we make a small  change (if you are doing TDD or just using build for feedback) takes a lot of time. Organizing tests into different test suites, making it easier to run as required by the current context, is handy in such cases.</p>

<p>There are multiple ways that we can do this within Visual Studio and below are some of the options available. I tend to use a mix of all these in my current project. This gives the flexibility to run only the new tests that I am writing while writing new code or set of related tests for the updates that I am making. Once done with the changes, I can run the full suite of unit tests, followed by the integration tests. This reduces the interruption duration while coding and has a direct impact on the overall productivity too. (If you think small interruptions does not matter much think twice!)</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Geek productivity" src="/images/geek_productivity.jpg" /></p>

<h4><strong>Test Traits</strong></h4>

<p>Traits are a good way to group tests together and to run them as different suites. It encompasses TestCategory, TestProperty, Priority and Owner. Using <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-au/library/microsoft.visualstudio.testtools.unittesting.testcategoryattribute.aspx">TestCategory</a> attribute we can specify  the group of the test and the Visual Studio Test Explorer uses this value to group the tests and allows executing tests in specific groups.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio Test Traits" width="75%" src="/images/vs_testExplorer_traits.png" /></p>

<p>Limitation with the above approach is that it depends on developers to put these attributes on the test cases or class level and not leveraging any existing conventions that might be already in place. Having integration tests, unit tests, acceptance tests in different projects is a very common practice, with conventions like project names ending with &lsquo;.UnitTests, .IntegrationTests, .AcceptanceTests&rsquo; etc.</p>

<h4><strong>Build Tasks and Task Runner Explorer</strong></h4>

<p>The <a href="https://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/8e1b4368-4afb-467a-bc13-9650572db708">Task Runner Explorer</a> (TRE) provides custom task runner support to Visual Studio, allowing to run grunt/gulp task or target inside Visual Studio. Grunt/Gulp has packages for most of the unit testing frameworks, using which different build tasks can be created. To select the tests to execute different conventions can also be used. Below is an example of a gulp task to execute all the c# unit tests in the project.</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var gulp = require('gulp');
var xunit = require('gulp-xunit-runner');
var xunitConsolePath = 'xunit.console.exe';
var unitTestsConvention = ['**/*.Tests.dll'];

gulp.task('c#UnitTests', function () {
    runTests(unitTestsConvention);
});

function runTests(dllPath) {
    return gulp.src(dllPath, { read: false })
        .pipe(xunit({
            executable: xunitConsolePath,
            options: { parallel: 'all' }
        }));
}
</code></pre>

<p>Similarly we can have multiple tasks to execute different groups of tests and it will be available in the TRE within Visual Studio as shown below. This approach gives the most flexibility, allowing tests be grouped any way and providing ability to execute tests across the stack of technologies.
<img class="center" alt="Visual Studio Task Runner Explorer" src="/images/vs_tre.png" /></p>

<h4><strong>Tests Settings File</strong></h4>

<p>Creating Test Playlist is an easy way to group tests into a playlist and executing them as  group. From the Test Explorer, select the tests to be grouped and on right-click, the option to create playlist is available. The saved playlists can be selected from the drop down menu on the top bar for later execution.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio Test Playlist" src="/images/vs_testExplorer_playlist.png" /></p>

<p>This works well for short-lived groupings, when we are actively working on a part of the code and need to execute tests for that area. Every time a new test is added, we need to add it explicitly to the playlist if required.</p>

<p>We have seen multiple ways of grouping tests into test suites, and each of them comes handy in different situations. For project wide convention tests, I tend to use build tasks that integrate with TRE as it is more flexible and extendable. Do you use any other ways to group your tests, drop in with a comment!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tools that I use]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-10T06:44:19+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tools are an indispensable part of our daily life and we all have our own likes and dislikes for them. Here are a list that I use (almost daily), most of them influenced from the <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/tools">greater list</a>. Having a great keyboard support is something that I look out for, especially for those that I interact with more frequently (IDE&rsquo;s or code editors). Couple of days back, while having a chat with my friend <a href="https://twitter.com/zpbappi">Bappi</a> some of these came up and he found a few interesting, so though of sharing the list over here.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong><a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio</a></strong>: This one is almost daily and is one of them that gets on along with my laptop. For a Microsoft stack developer I do not think there are much alternatives(<a href="http://www.microsoft.com/web/webmatrix/">WebMatrix</a>, <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio Code</a>) if you are looking for full fledged development. Personally I am on VS2015 now(since I am lucky enough to have a free MSDN subscription), but being on any of the version is equally good.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="https://www.onenote.com/">One Note</a></strong>: For note taking I prefer OneNote as it is easy to manage and organize and is available on all platforms. Collaborating with multiple users is also so easy and comes loaded with features making it suitable for all kinds of scenarios.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="https://onedrive.live.com/about/en-in/">OneDrive</a>/<a href="https://db.tt/bvYw3pL6">Dropbox</a></strong>: I use a mix of OneDrive and Dropbox for backing up my data and photos and find the experience for both good on all devices.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="http://cmder.net/">Cmder</a></strong>: Looking out for a cool console in Windows, then this is the one! Loads of features and awesome color scheme makes it really one of the best consoles. Ctrl + C for copy and Ctrl + V works nicely on this(and you do not need to be on Windows 10 for this) and that alone would drive me to try out this one.</p></li>
<li><p><strike><strong><a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/">Sublime Text</a></strong>: As the tag-line says, this is &lsquo;<em>The text editor that you would fall in love with</em>&rsquo;. I use this primarily for all my writing (except for markdown formats, for which I use <a href="http://markdownpad.com/">MarkdownPad</a>), quick edits, formatting and even for some coding when I do not want the full power of Visual Studio. There are loads of plugins available and a good community of users backing it.</strike>
<strong><a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio Code</a></strong>: The experience on VS Code has dramatically improved from the day that I originally wrote the post. Code is now my one stop editor and I use it for my blogging too.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="https://todoist.com/">Todoist</a></strong>: I have tried out a lot of tools and finally ended up with the premium version of Todoist for task management. Its got everything right and highly flexible to organize your tasks and has full fledged apps on all platforms, browsers and even mail integration. Its almost easy to access Todoist from any context that I am working on and syncs across all devices seamlessly. Its really worth paying for this one, if not you could use the free version with some reduced features.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="http://www.autohotkey.com/">AHK</a></strong>: This tiny little tool has innumerous uses and capabilities, but I just use very few of it to automate certain mundane tasks, store a list of <a href="http://ahkscript.org/docs/Hotstrings.htm">hotstring</a> and application <a href="http://ahkscript.org/docs/Hotkeys.htm">shortcut keys</a>. I have all my scripts synced across multiple PC&rsquo;s and have added a task in <a href="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-au/windows/schedule-task#1TC=windows-7">Task Scheduler</a> to run the scripts with highest privileges every time I log on.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="https://agilebits.com/onepassword">1Password</a></strong>: It&rsquo;s a password manager and is available on all platforms and quite easy to get started with. I had been using the browser capabilities to store and sync passwords before which was working fine. But password managers solve a totally different problem of generating passwords (though they also sync generated passwords without which it would be more difficult to use them given that we have multiple devices these days) as a <a href="http://www.troyhunt.com/2011/03/only-secure-password-is-one-you-cant.html">secure password is one that you cannon remember</a>. 1Password has a one time fee for license, can shared by up to six family members living in the same household, has various synchronization options and mainly gives you the control where all the data is stored.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="http://www.noisli.com/">Noisli</a>,<a href="https://soundcloud.com/">SoundCloud</a></strong>: Like to here music or have some background noise then these are for you. Noisli is a background noise generator, and lets you create different different combinations for your taste. SoundCloud has a lot of music tracks in them and it is free for online streaming.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="http://www.telerik.com/fiddler">Fiddler</a></strong>: The free web debugging proxy for any browser, system or platform, this one is really an indispensable tool if you are doing any kind of web development.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a>,<a href="https://getpocket.com/a/">Pocket</a></strong>: Feedly is an RSS reader and has got quite a good UI and syncs across all devices and helps me keep all the reading list in one place. If you want to have some articles to read while offline then Pocket is for you. Pocket downloads the article while online onto devices and keeps it available for reading. I have been experimenting (for a little over a month) to go offline on mobile and use this for my offline reading if I don&rsquo;t have the Kindle.(The experiment is going pretty good if not for a very few times I had to turn connectivity on for finding bus routes and timings.)</p></li>
<li><p><strong><a href="http://www.scootersoftware.com/">Beyond Compare</a></strong>: Really its &lsquo;beyond&rsquo; just comparing files and is really useful for comparing and merging files. I use the pro version and really recommend it. Integrates nicely with Visual Studio and other IDE&rsquo;s and also provides context menu&rsquo;s on file explorer.</p></li>
<li><p><del>Resharper</del>: I had been using this on and off and realized that mostly I was using only the &lsquo;navigate to&rsquo; feature and decided on to start using the in built features of Visual Studio. <a href="https://twitter.com/ploeh">Mark Seemann</a> has quite an interesting <a href="http://blog.ploeh.dk/2013/02/04/BewareofProductivityTools/">article</a> on this and I couldn&rsquo;t agree any more. Resharper is also changing their licensing model going from a one time fee to a <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/toolbox/">monthly fee</a>, which I don&rsquo;t personally prefer especially for a tool like R#.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>While there are some more, this is what I use most of the time. What tools help you at work. Do you have any better alternatives that I could try to replace something on this list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Waking up Early is All About Waking up to an Alarm]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-31T23:17:05+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have always been the &lsquo;<em>early to bed</em>&rsquo; type of person and my day mostly ends by ten thirty in the evening. But the &lsquo;<em>waking up early</em>&rsquo; part was not as &lsquo;strict&rsquo; as going to sleep part. I have always struggled to wake up at the sound of the alarm, which I always set without fail. It was either me hitting the dismiss button or it going completely unheard, only to be reminded about, at breakfast by my wife .</p>

<p>I have noticed that it&rsquo;s not that waking up in the morning that is a problem. Waking up from bed at any time of the day is a problem and we all tend to lie down for a few more minutes. Further reading about these on the Internet I came up with some strategies to help me wake up to an alarm. I have been following this for couple of months and its been working out for me, most of the time.</p>

<p><a href="http://flic.kr/p/6Zfgdp" class="center" title="Image By Guilherme Tavares, used under Creative Commons from http://flic.kr/p/6Zfgdp"><img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/alarm.png" class="center" alt="Image By Guilherme Tavares, used under Creative Commons from http://flic.kr/p/6Zfgdp"></a></p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Plan:</strong> Plan your activities to be done after waking up, before going to sleep the day before. &lsquo;<em>Not having anything to do</em>&rsquo;, is one of the main reasons that keeps us from waking up. So plan ahead for it and find activities like reading, writing , working out, anything that you like. But have a plan!</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Jump out:</strong> Don&rsquo;t let your brain rationalize on your plan at the sound of the alarm. The decision to wake up has already been made the night before and you have a plan at hand, so just jump out of bed. The more you think, the more likely it is to doze off.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Multiple alarms:</strong> At the early stages of trying this out, you can have multiple alarms set at very close intervals, as close as one or two minutes. Have a couple of them at one, two, five, ten minutes interval.(If somebody else shares the room with you make sure they don&rsquo;t mind this, for a couple of days till you find the rhythm.)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Alarm tone:</strong> Change the alarm tone frequently so that your brain does not get used to it and ignore it all together. You could also try having the same tone as that of your phone ringer, which would make you think you have a call and wake up immediately.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Early dinner:</strong> Have your dinner at least two to three hours before you sleep. Going to sleep with a full stomach makes you more tired in the morning and increases the chances of you having to hit the snooze button.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Daily alarms:</strong> Set your alarm daily and delete of all that recurrent alarms set for the entire week. This would ensure that you plan for your day when you set the alarm. No plan, No alarm!</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sleep Cycle:</strong> Over a period of time, listen to your body and understand how much sleep you require and adjust your timings accordingly. Too little or too much of sleep is bad.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Smart Alarms:</strong> There are mobile applications today that come up with puzzle based alarms, you would have to solve the puzzle to turn of the alarm. You could try one of those if needed(I had not used any though).</p></li>
</ol>


<p>These tips have really helped me to wake up to an alarm and be an early riser too. The feeling of starting the day as you wished for is great and stays throughout the day, helping you to do more and <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-organized-finding-a-system-to-manage-it-all/">staying organized</a>. Hope you find this useful and do let know if any other tricks has helped you to wake up to an alarm.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Staying Organized: Finding a system to manage it all]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-organized-finding-a-system-to-manage-it-all/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-23T03:23:04+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-organized-finding-a-system-to-manage-it-all</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In our busy lives, with multiple roles to play at home and work, everyone needs to have some kind of system to keep things organized and stay on top - <strong><em>to have control</em>. </strong>I&rsquo;ve been always amazed on how my father stays organized with all the things with his to-do list paper calendar and the energy with which he gets things done. Apart from his not-so-optimized short trips on the two-wheeler(which he does because he enjoys it) in getting things done across the town, that is what I have always wanted to attain.</p>

<p>I have always tried the pen-paper method to keep track of things to get done, but somehow I could never keep up with it. I always lost track of it as most of my work is <strong>not <em>track able with paper</em></strong>. Most of my work is done using a computer and I thought something that best suites me would be some tool that is right in my computer. I have tried with a variety of tasks application and some of them are pretty good in how it organizes tasks. But again it yet did not integrate into my life that easily, as there was always an overhead of entering tasks.</p>

<blockquote><p>Contemplating over why all these systems itself was an overhead, one thing that I have realized that I was always trying to live two lives - <strong>personal and official</strong>, with these systems.</p></blockquote>

<p>Major part of my day is spend at office where work mostly comes over email. Keeping track of it on a different task list manager or paper is really an overhead. So mostly I ended my leaving my office tasks in my mails itself and only tried to manage my personal tasks on the tool. This is why I <em>was living two lives</em>. There were two systems of management(or even more as bugs are assigned in <a href="http://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/tfs-overview-vs.aspx">Visual Studio TFS</a>) which by itself made tasks management an overhead and unmanageable.</p>

<p>After a  lot of reading and researching around the common productivity tools and systems finally I reached back to what I have been using day in and day out – <strong><em>Outlook. </em></strong>Outlook is more than a mere mailbox management tool. It has a lot of features that is built into it which is seldom used and overlooked upon. One advantage with outlook is that it is available everywhere – desktop, web, tablet and phone.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/Outlook_folders_productivity.png" alt="Outlook_folders_productivity" /></p>

<p>Most of us, even me used to just use flags on messages to indicate the messages that I had to take actions on. But this would soon turn out unmanageable, as it is hard to prioritize out from a single large list. Outlook has an important feature of <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-in/outlook-help/create-and-assign-color-categories-HA010217901.aspx">categorization</a> and also <a href="http://help.outlook.com/en-us/140/bb899478.aspx">folderization</a>. Either of this feature can be used to maximize the way in which we manage tasks.</p>

<p>I have chosen to use folders for the only reason that it is easier to sync folders on to my mobile, than categorized tasks, for which I would again need another application. As mentioned in the <a href="http://www.amazon.in/gp/product/0142000280/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3626&amp;creative=24822&amp;creativeASIN=0142000280&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-21">Getting Things Done</a>, by David Allen I have created various folders to categorize the tasks that come in</p>

<p><strong>.NextActions:</strong>  This holds the immediate next actions that I need to do. I further set a <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-in/outlook-help/flag-an-item-for-follow-up-HA010355003.aspx">flag date</a> to further prioritize them within the list.
<strong>.WaitingFor: </strong>This holds the items that I am waiting for somebody else to reply or something that I have delegated to someone else for action.(This is probably a NextAction on some one else’s list)
<strong>.TalkTo: </strong>These are things that I need to talk to people in person or over phone.
<strong>.References: </strong>These are reference documents that would be useful.
<strong>@Future: </strong>This contains tasks that needs to be done in the future, which might be in the next week. This would soon go into the .NextActions.
<strong>@Blog: </strong>These contain activities I need to do maintain this blog</p>

<p>And many of such folders that makes sense to me. You should create folders that makes sense to you.So all my official and personal tasks are now managed in my mailbox. For any tasks that do not come over a mail, I send a mail to myself.</p>

<p><strong>Reaching Zero Inbox</strong></p>

<p>Having a <a href="http://inboxzero.com/">zero mail inbox</a> is a very important thing – but not at any given point of time. Mails definitely can wait some time, before you take action on them. Allocate time to check mails and try to follow it. Once you check mails allocate them into the various folders that you already have. If it is something that you can answer to in less than a few minutes then do that immediately than allocating them to a folder and then picking it up from there. For anything else allocate them to different folders and act upon them later as per their priority. Create calendar entries/reminders only if it is strictly time bound, which has to happen at a specific time or date, like birthdays, booking time etc.</p>

<p>Create meaningful <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-in/outlook-help/manage-email-messages-by-using-rules-HA010355682.aspx">mail rules</a> so that you get to see what is urgent/important first. You need not scan all mail rule folders at all times. Mails that directly are addressed to you, mostly would need your attention. So the first rule would be to have messages that are directly addressed to you, to come to your inbox. Messages that you are <em>cc’ed</em>  in are mostly for information and should go to a different folder(Inbox-cc). But there are high chances that people who send messages  to you might not take a good look on when replying to messages in which field you are in. I have seen this, where it was directly addressed to me in the subject, but was cc’ed. But at least make sure you do not make this mistake. Always check the to and cc fields before sending/replying to mail. All other mails that reached me because I am in certain distribution lists goes into specific folders, which I scan only once a day.</p>

<p>Create a mail scanning process for yourself, whatever works for you. But try to stick to it.</p>

<p><strong>Managing Attention</strong></p>

<p>The biggest thing for staying productive and organized is attention management than time management. Even if you have scheduled your time for tasks, if you don&rsquo;t have the attention required then there is no point in managing your time. It is easy to manage your attention. Find things that distracts you and try to avoid them. One of the main thing in today&rsquo;s world that distracts us the most is – <strong>push notifications</strong>. Turn them off.Yes your heard it right. Turn them off right now. There is nothing that important coming over those notifications that is more important than keeping your attention to what you want. Notifications should be only for phone calls if you feel them important, because I do. I keep my internet turned on, as I would still want to have emails, tweets or other updates to be still updated onto my phone when I need them.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Turn off  Push Notifications</strong>. This is really going to help you manage your attention.</p></blockquote>

<p>Try to forcefully keep your attention to the task at hand. You can try out <a href="http://pomodorotechnique.com/">The Pomodoro Technique</a>. There are many apps for the phone that will work as a timer for the technique. I use <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.phlam.android.clockworktomato&amp;hl=en">Clockwork Tomato</a> - Yes for some time I am on an android Nexus5.</p>

<p>Plan your day so that you have a goal to achieve everyday, that just reacting to mails and working on someone else’s priorities. Don’t start your checking mails in the morning immediately after getting up. Have fixed times for checking mails, but definitely not the first thing in the morning.It might be hard for couple of days but it is only a matter of getting used to. You will definitely see a difference once you start following it.</p>

<blockquote><p>Stop checking your mails the first thing in the morning immediately after getting up.</p></blockquote>

<p>Its not been long since I have started to follow this, but I felt interesting enough to share this if it helps someone who is also searching for tools and methodologies to keep yourself productive and manage your tasks and responsibilities. There are a lot of resources that has inspired into this process and would be wrong to not mention it here</p>

<p><strong>Resources:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/HanselminutesPodcast268PersonalSystemsOfOrganizationReyBangoInterviewsScottHanselman.aspx">Scott Hanselman is always an inspiration</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.in/gp/product/0142000280/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3626&amp;creative=24822&amp;creativeASIN=0142000280&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-21">Getting Things Done: The Art of Stress-Free Productivity</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.in/gp/product/1118179676/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3626&amp;creative=24822&amp;creativeASIN=1118179676&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-21">Personal Productivity Secrets: Do what you never thought possible with your time and attention&hellip; and regain control of your life</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.in/gp/product/1471131823/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3626&amp;creative=24822&amp;creativeASIN=1471131823&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-21">The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>What system do you use to manage your life?. Do drop in the comments. I am still looking to refine more if it helps me to stay on top.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
