<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-05T04:50:50+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Continuos Delivery of Octopress Blog Using TravisCI and Docker]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/continuos-delivery-of-octopress-blog-using-travisci-and-docker/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-01T04:11:12+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/continuos-delivery-of-octopress-blog-using-travisci-and-docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a while since I have wanted to deploy my blog automatically whenever there is a new commit pushed into the associated <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com">git repository</a>. I use Octopress as my blog engine and have been <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/optimizing-octopress-workflow-for-new-posts/">tweaking it to my blogging workflow</a>. Octopress is a static blog generator built over Jekyll. So anytime I make any updates to the blog, I need to build the blog with the accompanying rake tasks and push the generated output (HTML, JavaScript, and CSS) to an Azure Web App that hosts my blog. For this I use the <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/documentation/articles/web-sites-deploy/#continuousdeployment">git deployment feature</a> of web apps, so just pushing the built output to a git repo (branch) deploys it to my website. As you see every time, I make a change I have to build the site and push it to the git repository and this can be automated. Since Octopress is in Ruby, I decided to use <a href="https://travis-ci.org/">Travis CI</a> for the build and deploy.</p>

<h3>Local Build Environment with Docker</h3>

<p>I am on an older repository fork of Octopress and have not updated to latest version. So it has hard dependencies with specific versions of gem packages that it needs and also on the Ruby and Jekyll version. So every time I change laptop it&rsquo;s difficult to set up the blog environment. In the past, I manually installed the dependencies whenever I got a new laptop. As changing laptop does not happen frequently, I had been delaying creating any script for this. But now since I had to setup the Travis build environment, I thought of also having a local build environment to test before pushing it up to Travis. Travis provides a Docker image that matches exactly their build environment.</p>

<p>Setting up Docker is just a few steps:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://docs.docker.com/docker-for-windows/">Install</a> the Docker components</li>
<li>Load the <a href="https://quay.io/organization/travisci">Docker image</a></li>
</ol>


<pre><code class="text">docker run -it -p 4000:4000 quay.io/travisci/travis-ruby /bin/bash
</code></pre>

<p>Once in the container, you can run the same build scripts that you manually run yo deploy and check. I had a few issues with the gem packages and <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com/commit/abefbf58e3696384c7931d5a4918239a41700106#diff-8b7db4d5cc4b8f6dc8feb7030baa2478">fixed it by specifying hard package dependency</a>. To launch the site hosted in Docker from host system <a href="https://github.com/wsargent/docker-cheat-sheet#exposing-ports">I expose incoming ports through the host container</a>. Once I have the local server running in the docker container (in port 4000) I can access it via <em>localhost:4000</em> from my host computer.</p>

<h3>Post Dates and TimeZones</h3>

<p>When building from the container, I noticed that the dates of posts were off by 1. For posts that were on month start (like Aug 1), it started coming up in July, on the archive page. After a bit of investigation, I realized that Jekyll parses the date time from the post and converts them into local system time. The container was running in UTC and when generating the site it converted post DateTime to UTC. All the posts that I had written after coming to Sydney had an offset of +1000 (or +1100) and most were published early in the morning. So it converted those posts to the previous date.
Since I am not that worried about the time zone of the post, I decided to remove it. I removed timezone information getting set for new posts in my Rake scripts. For the existing posts, <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com/commit/1d8902fa69a1aad9ad6615ee3c47e3474b6cd263">I removed all the timezone information from the <em>datetime</em> YAML header in the posts</a>. I set the config.yml to built in UTC irrespective of the system timezone that it is getting build.</p>

<h3>Setting up TravisCI</h3>

<p>Setting up automated build on Travis CI is smooth and easy process TDK. I just added a travis.yml with the &lsquo;<em>rake generate</em>. TDK The post build script does the following</p>

<ul>
<li>Clones the current statically generated code from my <em>blog</em> branch.</li>
<li>Perform a rake deploy that updates the cloned code above with the latest site.I updated the existing rake deploy to use GitHub token in push URL. As I did not want the token to be logged on to the Travis console I redirect the output using <em><a href="http://askubuntu.com/questions/12098/what-does-outputting-to-dev-null-accomplish-in-bash-scripts">&amp;> /dev/null</a></em>.</li>
</ul>


<pre><code class="yml">language: ruby
rvm:
  - 1.9.3
branches:
  only:
  - master
script: 
  bundle exec rake generate;
after_success: |
  if [ -n "$GITHUB_PUSH_URL" ]; then
    cd "$TRAVIS_BUILD_DIR"
    git clone -b blog --single-branch https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com.git _azure &amp;&gt; /dev/null
    bundle exec rake gitdeploy["$GITHUB_PUSH_URL"] &amp;&gt; /dev/null
    echo "Deployed!"
  fi
</code></pre>

<p>Every time I make a commit to the GitHub master branch, the automated build triggers and deploys the latest generated site.</p>

<h3>Current Blogging Workflow <a href="https://travis-ci.org/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com"><img src="https://travis-ci.org/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com.svg?branch=master" alt="Build Status" /></a></h3>

<p><img class="center" alt="Continuos Delivery of Octopress Blog" src="/images/blog_ci.PNG" /></p>

<ul>
<li>Write posts on my phone or laptop. (<a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/optimizing-octopress-workflow-for-new-posts/">Using Dropbox to sync posts across devices</a>)</li>
<li>Publish and Push to Github from laptop</li>
<li>Travis builds triggered by Github webhook</li>
<li>Travis pushes back generated site into Github (<em><a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com/tree/blog">blog branch</a></em>).</li>
<li>Azure Web App triggers automated deployment from Github.</li>
</ul>


<p>With the automated deployment, I have one less thing to take care of when writing posts. The whole process might feel a bit complicated, but it is not. It is just that I have been tweaking few things to ease blogging. And since I am a programmer, I like hacking things. If you are new to blogging you do not need them and don&rsquo;t get overwhelmed (if at all you are). All you need to make sure is to <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/">have a blog</a> and you <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/own-your-urls/">own the URL</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Morning Routine]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-16T05:00:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Humans are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zdGbHY9VKVM">creatures of habit</a> and things work well if made as a routine. It&rsquo;s what you build as your daily plan that defines what you end up achieving in the day and in turn with life.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>If you are a late night person, you can read &lsquo;morning&rsquo; as &lsquo;late night&rsquo; - the focus here is routine!</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.pexels.com/photo/coffee-cup-notebook-pen-64775/">
<img  alt="Win your day, create a morning routine" src="/images/morning_routine.jpg"/>
</a></p>

<p>A morning routine is nothing but a sequence of actions regularly followed. I have tried switching my routine too, to late in the night a few times but found that mornings work better for me. But this could be different for you, so stick to the time of day that works for you. Before going to how my morning routine looks like (which I just started a week back), I will explain how I made the plan for the routine.</p>

<h3>Brain Dump</h3>

<p>At any point in time, there are a lot of things in my mind and things that I kept committing to myself and others. It is not possible to keep up with everything that I wish to do. So the very first thing to do is to dump everything out onto to paper and then decide what needs attention. The <a href="http://gettingthingsdone.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/Mind_Sweep_Trigger_List.pdf">Incompletion Trigger List</a> assists to get everything out of your mind onto paper. It&rsquo;s a good idea to block some time of yours to perform this exercise and give it all the attention it needs. At times it helps to <strong><em>Slow Down to Go Fast</em></strong>.</p>

<p><img  alt="Slow down, to go faster" src="/images/morningroutine_slow_down.jpg"/></p>

<h3>Most Important Task (MIT)</h3>

<p>If you are following along, hope the brain dump helped to flush out all that was there in your mind. This exercise needs to be occasionally done (maybe every 2-3 months) to stay clear and stay on top of things. I was sure that I could not do everything on that list after the brain dump. Now comes the hard part of choosing what matters to you and choosing those that aligns well with your goals. For the morning routine, I stuck to items from the brain dump that fall under &lsquo;Personal Projects&rsquo; category (as highlighted in the below image).</p>

<p><img  alt="Choosing tasks for morning routine" src="/images/morning_routine_MIT.png"/></p>

<p>These are the items that matter to me and aligns to the short-long term goals that I have. Below is a part of my list.</p>

<pre><code class="text">Start Youtube channel
Become Pluralsight Author
Blogging
Learn Functional Programming
Learn Ruby
Open Source Contribution
Improving Writing Skills and Language
</code></pre>

<blockquote><p><em>The key is not to prioritize what’s on your schedule, but to schedule your priorities.</em></p>

<p><em>– <strong>Stephen Covey</strong></em></p></blockquote>

<p>Progressing towards all of these items on the list at the same time is not possible, as time available each day for achieving them is limited. I usually get around 2-3 hours a day of &lsquo;me time&rsquo;, provided I wake up at 4 in the morning (more on this shortly). The number of hours you have might differ, and you could choose those many items as you think you can fit in. But 3 is a good number to choose, as that helps to mix in a few different goals and gives the flexibility to shuffle around with them on a day. For me, it also means I roughly get around 40-60 minutes daily, for each item.</p>

<p>Currently, the ones that I have in my morning routine are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Blogging</li>
<li>Learn Functional Programming</li>
<li>Open Source Contribution</li>
</ul>


<h3>MITs to Mini Habits</h3>

<p>Having high-level short-long term goals is good, but does not provide anything actionable on a daily basis. It feels overwhelming to approach them because it does not give any sense of direction. So it&rsquo;s important that I have small actionable items that I can work on and progress towards achieving the goal.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Break your goal into the smallest possible task that you can think of so that you don&rsquo;t feel to skip it</em></p></blockquote>

<p>For me, the mini habits look like this</p>

<ul>
<li>Write at least one sentence for the blog</li>
<li>Read at least one line about Functional Programming</li>
<li>Read at least one line of code of an Open Source Project</li>
</ul>


<p>The idea behind keeping it so small is just to start. It&rsquo;s very rare that I have stopped writing after writing a sentence or stopped reading after a line. The trouble is only with getting started - once done you can easily carry on for at least 20-30 minutes. Even if I make 2 out of the 3 of the above tasks, I take it as a success, which gives me some flexibility each day.</p>

<h3>Waking up Tricks</h3>

<p>There are days when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resistance_(creativity)">Resistance</a> beats me to it, and I don&rsquo;t get up to the routine. But I feel low on those days for not able to progress on my goals. So I try hard to have less of such days.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Alarm Phone Inside Pillow:</strong> I use <a href="http://www.bitspin.ch/">Timely</a> on a spare phone to set alarms.  Till a while back I used to keep the phone at the bedside while sleeping. But I noticed that I often ended up snoozing the alarm, at times even without full consciousness. So to make I <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">wake up to the alarm</a>, I now keep the phone buried inside my pillow with just the vibration. The vibration forces me to wake up and also removes the need for any alarm sound - my kid and wife does not get disturbed.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Wear a Sweater:</strong> During winter, at times the cold beat me to it. It&rsquo;s hard to leave all the blankets and wake up to the cold. I started sleeping with the sweater, and I don&rsquo;t feel that cold when I wake up.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Rationalize Against Resistance:</strong> However hard I try not to rationalize on getting up when the alarm sounds off, looking at the snooze button I end up rationalizing. Often I have found that when I try to use the tasks that I can achieve if I wake up, to motivate myself, I end up justifying that it can wait for tomorrow. Because there is no hard deadlines or accountability to anyone - it&rsquo;s just me!. Now I try just the opposite - Think about the resistance that is trying to force me to the bed and reassure myself that I should not fall to it. The &lsquo;me&rsquo; waking up after sleeping in is not going to like it then. So wake up!</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>My Routine</h3>

<ol>
<li><em>Wake at 4 am</em></li>
<li><em>Brush</em></li>
<li><em>Drink Water</em></li>
<li><em>Stretching</em></li>
<li><em>Review the tasks for the day (<a href="https://en.todoist.com/">Todoist</a>)</em></li>
<li><em>Mini Habits (2 or 3)</em></li>
<li><em>Wake up wife at 5:45 am</em></li>
<li><em>Continue Mini Habits (2 or 3)</em></li>
<li><em>Tea</em></li>
<li><em>Wake up Gautham at 7 am</em></li>
</ol>


<p>Having a morning routine has helped me focus more on things that matter and not wander from one task to another. It has also helped set a sense of direction to what I do every day and spent less time in thinking what to do. I find my days starting in gradually and not rushing into it, setting up the pace for the day. Hope this helps you too!</p>

<h4><strong>References</strong></h4>

<div>
      <div class="row">
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://amzn.to/2a3wpUc">
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_powerofhabit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;" >
             </a>
          </div>
        </div>
       <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
          <a href="http://amzn.to/2ahrOcr" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_gtd.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://amzn.to/2aek2R5" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_warofart.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
          </div>
        </div>
     <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://zenhabits.net/" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_zenhabits.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
          </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       </div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[git checkout TFS]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/git-checkout-tfs/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-15T05:23:08+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/git-checkout-tfs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a year since using <a href="https://git-scm.com/">Git</a> as my mainstream version control system and I am loving it! Before Git, I had used Team Foundation Version Control (TFVC) for a very long time and was so used to it that I found Git a bit complex and overwhelming in the beginning. Team Foundation Server (TFS) is the whole product suite from Microsoft that provides source code management. Until TFS 2013, it supported only TFVC which is when it introduced <a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/mvpawardprogram/2013/11/13/git-for-tfs-2013/">Git in TFS</a>. Even today people use TFS and TFVC synonymously (like in the title of this post) though they are not the same.</p>

<h3>Fundamental shift in thinking</h3>

<p>By design, Git is a Distributed VCS, whereas TFS is centralized one. It takes quite a while to get your head around this and what it actually means. By definition</p>

<blockquote><p><em><strong>TFVC</strong>: Uses a single, centralized server repository to track and version files. Local changes are always checked in to the central server where other developers can get the latest changes.</em></p>

<p><em><strong>Git</strong>: Git is a distributed version control system. Each developer has a copy of the source repository on their dev machine. Developers can commit each set of changes on their dev machine and perform version control operations such as history and compare without a network connection.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>You. may not see the real Distributed benefits if you are working off a central repository (hosted on a server like GitHub or Bitbucket) and using <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/comparing-workflows/centralized-workflow">TFS way of development</a> :</p>

<p><em>Get latest code => Make your changes => Merge latest +> Check in (</em>Commit and push<em>)</em></p>

<p>The real power of Git is better understood when you start working disconnected, use branches to keep unrelated development activities separate and merge those into the main trunk (<em>master</em>) once comfortable. You get a local copy of the project and lets you make changes independent of all the other changes in the project.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Git feels so lightweight and never gets in the way of doing things.</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>Make command line your friend</h3>

<p>If you are a UI savvy person then Git might a good starting point to start using the command line. At first, it definitely feels hard especially if you were TFS/Visual Studio users and might be tempted to use the GUI tools available (<a href="https://desktop.github.com/">GitHub Desktop</a> or <a href="https://www.sourcetreeapp.com/">SourceTree</a>)</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Repetitive tasks become more evident when you use a command line and easily automatable.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I use Cmder (<a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/">one of my favourite tools</a>) with Git and have <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/generating-a-new-ssh-key-and-adding-it-to-the-ssh-agent/">set up SSH</a> to Bitbucket and Github (expected soon on TFS), secured by a paraphrase, so that I do not have to key in the credentials every time I interact with the repositories. I <a href="https://github.com/cmderdev/cmder/issues/193#issuecomment-63040989">start the ssh-agent the very first time I open Cmder</a>, which prompts for my paraphrase and continues to run in the background. Alternatively, you can also use <a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/Git-Credential-Manager-for-Windows">Credential Manager</a> to store credentials, when working with HTTP enabled Git repository. For the common commands, I have set up aliases like below, to save a bit on the keystrokes.</p>

<pre><code class="text">gl=git log --oneline --all --graph --decorate  $*
gs=git status
ga=git add -A 
gp=git pull
gpp=git push 
gc=git commit -m "$*"  
gcc=git commit
</code></pre>

<h3>Different workflows</h3>

<p>Git can be used in many ways and which makes it hard to get started. There are a few popular <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/comparing-workflows/">workflows</a> that one can use. Currently, I am using -  <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/comparing-workflows/feature-branch-workflow">Feature Branch workflow</a> -
which means that all work happen on independent feature branches and once completed gets merged into the main trunk (master branch). Code Reviews happens on the way it gets pulled into the main branch, which ensures code quality and familiarity.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/images/tutorials/collaborating/comparing-workflows/feature-branch-workflow/01.svg"><img class="center" alt="Git Feature Branch Workflow" src="/images/git_featurebranch_workflow.png" /></a></p>

<h3>Not Just for Code</h3>

<p>Git is a version control system and does not limit itself to storing code. You can use it for <a href="http://readwrite.com/2013/11/08/seven-ways-to-use-github-that-arent-coding/">version controlling any of your work</a>. For example, this blog is <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com">hosted on Github</a> and all the <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com/commits/master">changes are version controlled</a>, which gives me the flexibility to work and commit locally. Since the blog is <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/static-generator-is-all-a-blog-needs-moving-to-octopress/">static generated</a> I can also preview all the changes locally. I use git whenever I work on any documents or <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/Speaking">presentations</a> so that I can avoid manual copy of files and renaming with suffixes like &lsquo;<em>Draft</em>, &rsquo;<em>Draft1</em>,<em>Final</em>,&ldquo;<em>FinalRevision</em>&lsquo; etc. (if that sounds any similar)</p>

<h3>Managing Commits</h3>

<p>When coming to commits, which are nothing but checkpoints of meaningful work done, people might have a different  definition for &lsquo;<em>meaningful</em>&rsquo; - for some it might be really granular, for others a bit coarse and for yet another it means all the work is done. I tend to commit quite often - even a rename of a variable leads to a commit so that I do not have to backtrack if at all something goes wrong immediately after that.</p>

<p>if you really like the idea of committing often (locally), but want the pushes to remotes more coarse, you can &lsquo;<strong><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/5189560/squash-my-last-x-commits-together-using-git">squash your commits</a></strong>&rsquo;, before pushing it to remote branch. This allows you to commit often locally and still push  meaningful commit in the main source history. Make sure that the <a href="http://chris.beams.io/posts/git-commit/">commit messages and clear and communicates the intent</a> and helps <a href="http://megakemp.com/2014/08/14/the-importance-of-a-good-looking-history/">keep a good looking history</a>.</p>

<p>Git is one of the best things that happened to developers and hopes it stays long!</p>

<p><strong>References</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://gitref.org/index.html">Git Reference</a></li>
<li><a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2">Pro Git</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started With Freelancing Jobs Online]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-freelancing-jobs-online/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-01T11:57:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-freelancing-jobs-online</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Freelancing is a good way to learn new technology, get some hands on experience and not getting limited to the technology stack at your full-time job and of course earn some extra money!. There is a great demand for developers out there, so if its &lsquo;legal&rsquo; (check with your employer, if you already have another full-time job) for you to freelance then give it a try. There are a lot of online freelance platforms(<a href="https://www.upwork.com/">Upwork</a>, <a href="https://www.freelancer.com/">Freelancer</a>) that connects businesses and developers remotely. These platforms enable you as a developer, to start a profile and bid for jobs of your interest. If the business/client finds you as a match for the job, then you get signed up and can start working immediately.</p>

<p>Easy right! Yes absolutely it is, but here are a few things that might help you through the journey, that I have learned from my experiences.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Freelancer" src="/images/freelancing.jpg" /></p>

<h3><strong>Finding work</strong></h3>

<p>Finding work is just an easy search across on the platforms with your preferred skills. It will be a good idea to stick to one of the platforms so that you can build up a profile and then move on to other platforms. Landing your first job as a freelancer could be tricky as clients have a tendency to look for people with some work record on the platform, which assures them that it is a &lsquo;real human&rsquo; that they are talking to. But this is kind of &lsquo;chicken and egg problem&rsquo;. One of the best way to break into your first job is to sell yourself low - Yes, you heard it right - Really low!</p>

<p>While I started on with the idea of freelancing, I took on it with the perspective of that of an experienced developer(as I had a full-time job, which was paying me decently well). I bid on all projects with a relatively higher amount or at par to that my current job was paying, until I received back the below email from one of the clients.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>You lack test scores, have a small portfolio, and have no <a href="https://www.upwork.com">Odesk</a> history. You should try to underbid and get jobs when you are building up odesk history, get good feedback and then raise your rates later.I see you have good qualifications and don&rsquo;t mean you are not worth what you charge, this is just a way to get more clients in the beginning</em></p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s not always that you get a reply like this and it was an eye-opener for me. So to get the ball rolling, I tried bidding low on a couple of bug fix project which was about 1-2 hours work. Luckily I got one of the jobs and from then followed the exact feedback that I got back - Slowly increase rates and build profile.When bidding lower always make sure that you do on projects of smaller size, so that you don&rsquo;t feel really bad selling yourself low midway through the project (you could always renegotiate, but it might affect the feedback).</p>

<h3><strong>Bidding</strong></h3>

<p>Bidding is an important part of the freelancing cycle. Make sure you put in as much details to put across that you are an ideal candidate. It&rsquo;s where your skills to sell yourself come into play. Make sure you convey through the reasons on the &lsquo;Why&rsquo;,&lsquo;What&rsquo; and &lsquo;How&rsquo; in your bid cover letter.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Approach bidding the same way you would attend an interview with a prospective employer.</em></p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Why</strong> you are interested in the project</li>
<li><strong>What</strong> makes you a good candidate and your experiences. It will be good to have some references to existing projects/applications/blogs to back your claims.</li>
<li><strong>How</strong> you would approach the problem at hand and some questions probing more details.</li>
</ul>


<p>Many a times we have a tendency to copy paste bid cover letters and clients might look for specific references to their project. There are also clients who ask to start/end the bid with specific words or phrases just to make sure you have at least read through the job description.</p>

<h3><strong>Communication</strong></h3>

<p>Communication is the key when working remotely. Keeping your clients/stakeholders up to date on what&rsquo;s happening in the project, calling out any risks associated and clarifying on any issues should be done promptly. Your bid cover letter is the first impression that you leave on the client on your communications skills. So that makes it an added reason to give enough time while sending out your bid.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Missing a deadline is not really a problem, but not communicating it up front is.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good idea to set a rhythm to your updates and also sticking on to an update format, so that client knows how and when to expect for things. This will also allow them to plan for work. If working on hourly jobs, it would also be a good idea to set up repositories to share code or other artifacts that you are working on. <a href="https://github.com">Github</a> (paid for private repositories), <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-team-services-vs.aspx">Visual Studio Online</a> (VSO) or <a href="https://bitbucket.org">Bitbuket</a> (free with limits for private repositories) are good providers that you can use. Using <a href="https://trello.com">Trello</a> boards or <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-team-services-vs.aspx">VSO</a> for managing work/tasks will give enough visibility to clients on the current status at any point in time.</p>

<h3><strong>Hourly vs Fixed Price</strong></h3>

<p>When starting out it might be a good idea to start with an hourly project, so that you get introduced to various aspects of freelancing and get used to it. Once comfortable with the overall life cycle you can try fixed price projects. The challenge with fixed price projects, is in getting the scope fixed and making sure that you have accounted for all possible work. Also in tactfully raising cost variations when the client changes from agreed scope or when you discover work that you had not estimated for. Having cost change costs quite often does not put across a good message, so do that wisely and only when absolutely required. Even on hourly projects, there is nothing wrong in negotiating with the per-hour rate, especially if the project is a long running one.</p>

<p>Understand how the payment terms and conditions associated with the platform works. Some platforms have the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Escrow">escrow</a> model, so the risk of loosing out on money is less. For hourly projects, some platforms have tools that automatically track the amount of time you work on a project and directly bill the clients card once in a week/month, in which case you are sure to receive the payment (unless the client raises a conflict). For cases where none of the above applies, make sure that you have payment milestones set at different phases of the project and you share the code/working product only once you receive payments for milestones. Sharing videos, pictures, live remote sessions could be some alternatives to prove milestone criteria.</p>

<h3><strong>Branding</strong></h3>

<p>Proving your metal is tough if you are just starting out freelancing. Having some experiences to show case is valuable when bidding for projects. When I started off freelancing, my intention was to learn Windows Phone and Windows 8 Modern application development. Since the platform was relatively new then, I started off with a side project <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/store/apps/picfinity/9wzdncrdwxx8">Picfinity</a>, to showcase my capabilities. Building the application also helped me generate a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tag/500px/">few blog posts</a> around these areas and I used both of above to showcase my ability to build applications for the Windows platform. This also helped me increase my hourly rates at a faster pace.
Branding is an ongoing effort that you need to do when freelancing, which indirectly enables you to increase your rates over time. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/">Writing blogs</a>, creating reusable libraries, contributing on forums, etc. are some of the things that help with this.</p>

<p>From the experiences gained from these freelancing platforms you will soon be able to move to consulting on your own or join premium freelancing platforms like <a href="www.toptal.com">Toptal</a>, <a href="http://x-team.com/">Xteam</a>, etc. You could also stick on with these platforms and learn new technologies while getting paid. At the very least I see that it has helped me generate content for my blogs (as I still struggle with topics to blog about).</p>

<p>Hope this helps you to get started with freelancing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up AutoHotkey to Speed up Trivial Tasks]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/setting-up-autohotkey-to-speed-up-trivial-tasks/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-09T04:22:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/setting-up-autohotkey-to-speed-up-trivial-tasks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A lot of trivial tasks that we do daily on our computer can be automated to make it faster and reduce the number of keystrokes (<a href="http://www.keysleft.com">as they are limited</a>). <a href="https://autohotkey.com/">AutoHoykey</a>(AHK) is an excellent tool to automate a lot of these and is <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/">one of my favorite tool</a>. I use a very limited set of functionality of AHK,  to set up hot strings, launch applications, and mapping caps lock as backspace. The installer to the latest version is available <a href="https://autohotkey.com/download/ahk-install.exe">here</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;AutoHotkey (AHK) is a free, open-source macro-creation and automation software for Windows that allows users to automate repetitive tasks. It is driven by a scripting language that was initially aimed at providing keyboard shortcuts, otherwise known as hotkeys, that over time evolved into a full-fledged scripting language.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Hotstrings</strong> are to map short key combinations that expand on completion. This one is to handle all common phrases, words like emails, default mail replies, etc. Defining a hotstring is as shown below or look up the <a href="https://autohotkey.com/docs/Hotstrings.htm">documentation here</a> for more details</p>

<pre><code class="text">::emg::rahulpnath@gmail.com
::myn::Rahul P Nath
::myb::http://www.rahulpnath.com
</code></pre>

<p>You can use some easy to remember keywords for these like emg means &lsquo;Email Gmail&rsquo; and myn means &lsquo;My Name&rsquo; etc.</p>

<p><strong>Hot keys</strong> are to launch applications on those key combinations. You can use this to launch your favorite applications with the key combinations of your choice. Defining  hot keys is as shown below or look up the <a href="https://autohotkey.com/docs/Hotkeys.htm">documentation here</a> for more details</p>

<pre><code class="text">^!C::
Run "C:\Users\rahulpnath\Documents\Apps\cmder\Cmder.exe"
return
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Capslock to Backspace</strong> mapping is something that I got inspired from the <a href="http://colemak.com/">Colemak layout</a> and find it useful even with the QWERTY layout. I use the <a href="https://autohotkey.com/docs/commands/Send.htm">Send</a> command to send simulated keystrokes. In the rare case of actually needing the CapsLock key, I just need to press it along with Shift to toggle on and off.</p>

<pre><code class="text">CapsLock:: Send {BackSpace}
</code></pre>

<h4><strong>Running AHK scripts on startup</strong></h4>

<p>To automatically run these scripts on startup, I use the <a href="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-au/windows/schedule-task#1TC=windows-7">Task Scheduler</a> that comes with Windows. To create a new task follow the steps as shown below.</p>

<p>In Task Scheduler select &lsquo;Create Task&rsquo; and enter the Name and Description. Set it to run with highest privileges, so that the scripts work even when on application&rsquo;s running in admin mode. Create a trigger for the task to run and I have set it &lsquo;At log on&rsquo; to run every time I log on. Create an Action to &lsquo;Start a program&rsquo; and select the script file (.ahk) with all your scripts. Once created you can right-click on the task and select Run and verify that the script has started and is working.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio Code Coverage" src="/images/ahk_task_general.PNG" /></p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio Code Coverage" src="/images/ahk_task_trigger.PNG" /></p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio Code Coverage" src="/images/ahk_task_actions.PNG" /></p>

<p>I synchronize these scripts over Onedrive, to make it available on all my computers. The only thing to do on all the computers is to create the startup task. The features discussed above is just the tip of an iceberg, and should help you get started. AHK has a lot more features that you can explore at the project site. Hope this helps you to set up and automate some of your tasks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
