<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: java | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tag/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-14T00:01:56+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up the Development Environment for PhoneGap on Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/setting-up-the-development-environment-for-phonegap-on-android/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T05:49:22+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/setting-up-the-development-environment-for-phonegap-on-android</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been working on Microsoft stack for over a long time, in fact almost my entire career. Now that with all the platforms out there and cross platform being a very important factor in any application development, knowing about other platforms and developing for them is very important . Since I have had some prior experience on Java, I thought of ramping back on it so that I could also explore the Android operating system.</p>

<p>Setting up Java and choosing an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integrated_development_environment">IDE</a> was always confusing for me and so is it now. For .Net it was, is and always will be <a href="http://www.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio</a> and the setup experience is seamless. For a person in the .net world moving into java would take some time in setting up the environment, and getting used to the IDE’s. Personally I feel that none of the java IDE’s matches the experience and features provided by Visual Studio - but that might be just me. But lets be happy with what we have and start setting up our development environment.</p>

<ul>
<li><p> <strong>Download</strong> the <a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/jdk7-downloads-1880260.html">Java SDK</a>. I have chosen to download the latest one as on writing this blog, as I did not have any reason not to. If you have a specific need to have a particular java version then you should get that. Install it into the appropriate location (e.g. <em>C:\Program Files\java\jdk1.7</em>)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Set JAVA_HOME</strong> in the system environment variables.
Right Click on MyComputer –> Properties –>Advanced System Settings –> Environment Variables
Under System Variables, add a new variable by clicking New and entering <em>Variable Name </em>as JAVA_HOME and <em>Variable value</em> as the path to the root jdk folder installed in previous step.(<em>C:\Program Files\java\jdk1.7</em>). Save the changes.
To see if this has been saved you can verify by opening a command prompt and typing in <em>echo %JAVA_HOME%, </em>which should echo out the path set above.</p></li>
<li><p>Update <strong>PATH </strong>to include java path too, so that this can be executed from anywhere, without knowing the full path of the java compiler.
Under system variables there would already be a variable with name <em>path </em>(if not add it), to which you can append the java path. Java is in the bin folder under the root folder, so append “<em>;%JAVA_HOME%/bin;</em>” to the path variable. Save and close.
To check if this is successfully setup, open up command prompt and type in java. You should see usage information help for java.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Installing ANT. </strong>Download <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">ant library</a> and copy/install into a suitable location. Ant is used in the build of java applications and is more comparable to msbuild in .net.</p></li>
<li><p>Set <strong>ANT_HOME </strong>and<strong> PATH </strong>like we set for Java. Should be easy for you now.</p></li>
<li><p>Download and install <a href="http://developer.android.com/sdk/index.html">Android SDK</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Set <strong>ANDROID_HOME </strong>to the android sdk root folder.</p></li>
<li><p>Set <strong>PATH </strong>for android tools(<em>%ANDROID_HOME%\tools;</em>) and platform-tools<em>(%ANDROID_HOME%\platform-tools;</em>)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Download an IDE</strong>. <a href="https://www.eclipse.org/downloads/">Eclipse</a>, <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">IntelliJ Community Edition</a> , <a href="http://developer.android.com/sdk/installing/studio.html">Android Studio</a> are all freely available IDE’s that you can choose from. Android studio is based on IntelliJ IDEA. I chose to use IntelliJ for now for no specific reason.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Now you are all setup for starting your development with PhoneGap on Android . Hope this helps you to quick start your development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
