<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tipow | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-02T00:05:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Improved Code Navigation in Visual Studio 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/improved-code-navigation-in-visual-studio-2017/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/improved-code-navigation-in-visual-studio-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Visual Studio (VS) 2017 improves a lot on Code Navigation features.  If at all anything ever attracted me to ReSharper it was code navigation (though I have not been using it for a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/">couple of years now</a>). Visual Studio lacked behind in this aspect but not anymore. The new features help improve developer productivity and here are few I found worth looking.</p>

<p>In earlier versions, the navigation features are all over the menu. In VS2017 all the navigation features are available under <strong><em>Edit -> Go To</em></strong>. Though I usually prefer using the keyboard shortcut for opening the navigate dialogs, it&rsquo;s good to have all under the same menu.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio 2017 Code Navigation" src="/images/visualstudio_code_navigation.png" /></p>

<p><strong><em>Control + T</em></strong> brings up the Go To Dialog box which now has a lot more icons and options compared to the previous VS versions. Typing in &lsquo;<em>?</em>&rsquo; lists the different filtering criteria available when querying. It also allows searching across all the criteria by just not specifying the filtering criteria. To search for a file, type in &lsquo;<em>f FileName</em>&rsquo;. These filters also have direct shortcuts as shown in the image above.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Visual Studio 2017 Go To Shortcuts" src="/images/visualstudio_goto.png" /></p>

<p>CamelCase search is the one that attracts me the most. By entering just the capital letters of the name it quickly filters out the particular class. As shown below by just typing <em>CSG</em> it brings up the class <strong>C</strong>har<strong>S</strong>equence<strong>G</strong>enerator. Typing in the full class name is no longer required and makes navigation faster.</p>

<p><img  class="center" alt="Visual Studio 2017 Go To Camel Case Matching" src="/images/visualstudio_camelcasematching.png" /></p>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p6NVTASKa1A">video</a> to see these features and more in action. Hope it helps!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Rescue Time - Track Your Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/rescue-time-track-your-time/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/rescue-time-track-your-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Rescue Time - My dashboard for March,2017" src="/images/rescuetime.png" /></p>

<p>Tracking is essential for measuring progress. Depending on your area of focus tracking tools differ. If it is a time-based activity that you are tracking a simple watch can suffice the need. But this can soon become an overhead. <a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/">Rescue Time</a> helps track time spent on a computer or mobile devices.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Rescue Time is a  personal analytics service that shows you how you spend your time and provides tools to help you be more productive.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Rescue time runs in the background and helps you track the applications and websites that you use. Most of the applications are categorized automatically; However, it also allows manual categorization. Rescue Time lets you edit an activity and assign it to various categories and set productivity levels. So if you are spending more time on an application configured as <em>very productive</em> then your overall productivity pulse is higher for the day.</p>

<p><img alt="Rescue Time - Edit Activity" src="/images/rescuetime_edit_activity.png" /></p>

<p>Once you have your time tracked you can then adapt yourself to be more productive. Various reports are provided to visualize the data collected. The <a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/rescuetime-pro">premium version</a> offers a lot more features to help improve productivity. I am currently on the Free Plan. Rescue Time helps inspect your current behaviors and patterns at work. Once you have the details, you can understand where your time is spent and improve on it as required. Rescue Time is available for <a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/get_rescuetime">computer and mobile devices</a>. Hope this helps track your time and become more productive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Tomighty - A Pomodoro Timer]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tomighty-a-pomodoro-timer/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tomighty-a-pomodoro-timer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://tomighty.org/"><img alt="Tomighty, Pomodoro Timer" src="/images/tomighty.png" /></a></p>

<p>Over the past couple of weeks, I have been trying to improve my focus while working. With <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">running (3 * 1.5 hours a week) and bodyweight training (3 * 30 minutes a week)</a> taking a significant part of my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">morning routine</a>, I have less time for <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2016-recap/">blogging, learning, and videos</a>. Though I have known <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">The Pomodoro Technique</a> for a long time, I never practiced it regularly. With less time and more things to get done, I badly had to do something to get back on track with everything and thought of giving it a try.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The Pomodoro Technique is a time management technique that uses a timer to break down work into intervals, traditionally 25 minutes in length, separated by short breaks. These intervals are named Pomodoro</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Initially, I was looking at apps that can integrate with <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-manage-your-todo-list/">Todoist</a>, my task management tool. There are a lot of <a href="https://support.todoist.com/hc/en-us/articles/210762349-Pomodoro-with-Todoist">pomodoro apps that integrate with Todoist</a>, but I found all of them an overkill.
<a href="http://tomighty.org/"><strong>Tomighty</strong></a> is a simple Pomodoro timer that just tracks time and settings for the Pomodoro interval and long and short breaks. It hides away well in the Notification area of the taskbar and shows the amount of time left in the current interval. It plays sounds when an interval starts and ends. You can interrupt a Pomodoro session and restart it if required. That is all that you need from a timer to keep up with the Pomodoro technique.</p>

<p><em>If you are on a high DPI machine running Windows, the UI might not scale well. There is a <a href="https://github.com/tomighty/tomighty/issues/115">workaround</a> for this.</em></p>

<p>Sticking to the Pomodoro Technique has been working well for me, and I am able to focus better on the task at hand. I am still exploring the technique and trying to improve on it. Do you use Pomodoro Technique? If you are new to Pomodoro Technique and want to learn more check out the book, <a href="http://amzn.to/2nCSZW1">The Pomodoro Technique</a>, by Francesco Cirillo, the creator of the technique.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Track Current File in Visual Studio Solution Explorer]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/track-current-file-in-visual-studio-solution-explorer/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/track-current-file-in-visual-studio-solution-explorer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While working on large codebases, I want my Solution Explorer to be synchronized with the current working file. With the solution explorer in sync, it makes navigating to other related files, adding new classes in the same location, renaming files, etc. faster.</p>

<p><img alt="Track Active Item in Solution Explorer, Visual Studio" src="/images/visualstudio_trackActiveItem.png" /></p>

<p>The setting to keep the items in sync is configurable in Visual Studio and is turned off by default. You can enable this by checking the &lsquo;<strong><em>Track Active Item in Solution Explorer</em></strong>&rsquo; under <em>Options -> Projects and Solutions -> General</em>. You can navigate there quickly using <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/quick-launch-in-visual-studio/">Visual Studio Quick Launch (Ctrl + Q)</a>. Just type &lsquo;<em>Track active</em>&rsquo; and you will get the quick link to the setting. Keep it checked, and off you go, the solution explorer and the current file will be in sync.</p>

<p>PS: Visual Studio 2017 is now available.<a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/downloads/">Get it</a> if you have not already!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Switching Subscriptions Under Same Azure Account to Access Key Vaults]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/switching-between-subscriptions-under-same-azure-account-to-access-key-vault/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/switching-between-subscriptions-under-same-azure-account-to-access-key-vault</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" alt="Azure Powershell Get-AzureRmContext" src="/images/powershell_azurermcontext.png" /></p>

<p>When accessing Key Vault using Powershell it can be a bit tricky when you have multiple subscriptions under the same account. The Key Vault cmdlets being under the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-the-deprecation-of-switch-azuremode-affects-azure-key-vault/">Resource Manager (RM) mode</a> depends on the current RM Subscription. The Key Vault cmdlets enable you to manage only the key vaults under the selected subscription. To access the key vaults in other subscriptions, you need to switch the selected RM subscription.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Use <strong>Select-AzureRmSubscription</strong> to switch the selected RM subscription</em></p></blockquote>

<p> The <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/powershell/resourcemanager/azurerm.profile/v2.2.0/get-azurermcontext">Get-AzureRmContext</a> returns the metadata used for RM requests. The SubscriptionId/SubscriptionName property indicates the selected subscription. Any Key Vault cmdlets (or RM cmdlets) will work based off that selected subscription. To change the selected Azure RM subscription use the Select-AzureRmSubscription cmdlet. Pass in the SubscriptionId or the Subscription Name that you wish to switch to and the RM Subscription will be set to that. To get the SubscriptionId/SubscriptionName of the subscriptions under your account use <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn495302.aspx">Get-AzureSubscription</a> cmdlet.</p>

<pre><code class="` powershell"> Get-AzureRmContext
 Get-AzureRmSubscription
 Select-AzureRmSubscription -SubscriptionName  "Your Subscription Name"
 Select-AzureRmSubscription -SubscriptionId  a5287dad-d5a2-4060-81bc-4a06c7087e72
</code></pre>

<p> I struggled with this for some time, so hope it helps you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
