<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tipow | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-10T00:01:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Electronically Sign PDF - No More Printing and Scanning]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/electronically-sign-pdf-no-more-printing-and-scanning/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/electronically-sign-pdf-no-more-printing-and-scanning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Very often I need to sign forms, receipts, invoices in PDF format and send them across to someone else. Printing the PDF, signing them physically and scanning them back (of course using <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/office-lens-scan-documents-with-your-phone/">Office Lens</a>) is how I used to do this until a while back. Since I don&rsquo;t have a printer at home, I always had to wait till I reach office. Also, I did not like wasting paper and ink just to put a signature.</p>

<p>Adobe PDF reader allows us to &lsquo;Fill and Sign&rsquo; documents. Using this option we can add signatures without needing to print them. Follow the below steps to set up your Adobe Reader to sign any document.</p>

<p><strong>1.</strong> Sign on a white paper and take a picture. Upload the picture onto your computer and crop the image using your favorite <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/paint-dot-net/">image editor</a>. You should have something similar as shown below.</p>

<p><img src="/images/pdf_signature.png" alt="Your Signature" class="center" /></p>

<p><strong>2.</strong> Open the PDF file that you need to sign with <a href="https://get.adobe.com/reader/">Adobe Reader</a>.</p>

<p><strong>3.</strong> Open &lsquo;Fill and Sign&rsquo; option. You can do this either from the &lsquo;Tools Pane&rsquo; (Shift + F4 on windows) or the menu &lsquo;View -> Tools -> Fill and Sign.&rsquo;</p>

<p><strong>4.</strong> Under the Sign option, you can choose a signature image. Choose the image you created before and save.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adobe_add_sign.png" alt="Add your Signature" class="center" /></p>

<p>You are all set to sign documents now. Anytime you want to sign a document, choose &lsquo;Fill and Sign&rsquo; and you will see your signature under the Sign button. Click the signature and place it anywhere on the document that you want to sign. No more printing and scanning them back again.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Office Lens - Scan Documents With Your Phone]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/office-lens-scan-documents-with-your-phone/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/office-lens-scan-documents-with-your-phone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Scanning physical documents can be cumbersome using a scanner, especially if you do not have easy access to one. Taking pictures with the default camera application on the phone might not give the best of results that you are expecting. Also, you will mostly end up needing to trim such photos of unwanted elements.</p>

<p>Microsoft Office Lens is the perfect application for scanning documents and whiteboards. Office Lens focuses documents in the camera frame and allows you to capture just what is required. It enhances the selected document sections. Below is an example of the highlight and the captured document.</p>

<p><img src="/images/office_lens.png" alt="Office Lens Capture" class="center" ></p>

<h4><strong>Features</strong></h4>

<ul>
<li>Capture and crop a picture of a whiteboard or blackboard, and share your meeting notes with colleagues.</li>
<li>Make digital copies of your printed documents, business cards or posters, and trim them precisely.</li>
<li>Printed text will be automatically recognized (using OCR) by converting Word and PDF, so you can search for words in images and copy and edit them.</li>
</ul>


<p>Office Lens is available on all platforms. Download the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.microsoft.office.officelens&amp;hl=en">Android</a>, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/office-lens/id975925059?mt=8">iOS</a> or the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-au/store/p/office-lens/9wzdncrfj3t8">Windows</a> version from the stores. Next time you want to scan something just Office Lens it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: The Headphones Rule]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/the-headphones-rule/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/the-headphones-rule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/headphone_rule.png" class="center" alt="The Headphones Rule" ></p>

<p>&lsquo;<em>I need some undistracted time</em>.&rsquo;</p>

<p>This was one of the things that came up in my team&rsquo;s retrospective yesterday. Having some undistracted time is necessary for getting things done. It&rsquo;s a good practice to have a consensus among the team members on how to manage disruptions and indicate whether you are open for a chat.</p>

<p><a href="http://theheadphonesrule.com/">The Headphone Rule</a> is an interesting way to indicate whether a person is open to interactions or not.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>no headphones, you can talk to me.</em></p>

<p><em>1 headphone, you can talk to me about work</em></p>

<p><em>2 headphones, do not talk to me.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>For people who do not use a headphone, some other technique needs to be used (like sticky notes, colored lights, etc.). Luckily in my team, everyone uses headphones, and it was an acceptable solution. Irrespective of the way you choose it is important to have some agreed way to indicate whether you are interruptible or not. It helps you and the team to have some undistracted time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Visual Studio Dev Essentials]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/visual-studio-dev-essentials/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/visual-studio-dev-essentials</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are a .NET developer and looking for some awesome free stuff, then check out <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/dev-essentials/">Visual Studio Dev Essentials</a>. You get loads of free stuff</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Free tools, cloud services, and training</em></p>

<p><em>Get everything you need to build and deploy your app on any platform. With state-of-the-art tools, the power of the cloud, training, and support, it’s our most comprehensive free developer program ever.</em></p></blockquote>

<p><img src="/images/vs_dev_essentials.png" alt="center" alt="Visual Studio Dev Essentials" ></p>

<p>Some of the key attractions of the program are</p>

<ul>
<li>$300 Azure Credit for a year</li>
<li>Access to Xamarin University Training</li>
<li>Pluralsight access for three months</li>
<li>WintellectNOW access for three months</li>
</ul>


<p>All you need is a Windows Live ID to signup. Get it if you have not already!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Learn Touch Typing]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/learn-touch-typing/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/learn-touch-typing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><em>We are typists first, and programmers second.</em></p>

<p>-<a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/we-are-typists-first-programmers-second/"><em>Jeff Atwood</em></a></p></blockquote>

<p>If you are like me, spending a lot of time with a computer, it&rsquo;s worth you take the time to learn to type without looking at the keyboard a.k.a touch typing (if you currently type by the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Typing#Hunt_and_peck">hunt and peck method</a>). Though productivity cannot be measured by the number of words you type per minute, it&rsquo;s good to learn to touch type. There are various applications that help you to improve your typing speed. Some of them are online and some offline desktop applications. Pick one that suits you and improve your typing speed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/touch_typing.gif" alt="Touch Typing layout" alt="center" ></p>

<p>I learned to touch type only a couple of years back,  getting inspired after reading <a href="http://amzn.to/2hmblsw">Learn Anything in 20  Hours</a>. In the book, the author explains how he learned a new keyboard layout, Colemak, in just 20 hours.  The book explains the full process and setup used by the author. It uses various tools like <a href="https://wwwtyro.github.io/keyzen/">Keyzen</a>, <a href="http://type-fu.com/">Type-fu</a>, <a href="https://github.com/webiest/amphetype">Amphetype</a>. More than the tools it is the process and the approach to the learning that is interesting. A <a href="https://first20hours.com/typing/">summary of the tools and approaches</a> is available here but highly recommend reading the book. I found the approach very helpful and effective and used to learn QWERTY layout.</p>

<p>Irrespective of the way you choose to learn touch typing, it might seem a bit hard at the start. Keep at it for some time snd you will soon see an improvement in your typing speed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
