<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tipow | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-06-29T00:01:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Using Git Locally in a TFVC Repository]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/using-git-locally-in-a-tfvc-repository/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/using-git-locally-in-a-tfvc-repository</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The project that I am currently working on using <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/docs/tfvc/overview">Team Foundation Version Control</a>(TFVC) as it&rsquo;s source control. After <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/git-checkout-tfs/">using Git</a> for a long time it felt hard to move back to TFVC. One of the biggest pain for me is losing the short commits that I do when working. Short commits help keep track of the work and also quickly revert unwanted changes. Branching is also much easier with Git and allows to switch between work without much hassle of &lsquo;<em>shelving -> undoing -> pulling back the latest as with TFS.</em>&rsquo;</p>

<p><img src="/images/tfvc_local_git.png" alt="Use Git Locally in a TFVC Repository" class="center" /></p>

<p>The best part with git is that you can use it to work with any folder in your system and does not need any setup. By just running &lsquo;<em><a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-init">git init</a></em>&rsquo; it initializes a git repository in the folder. Running <em>init</em> against my local TFVC source code folder, I initialized a git repository locally. Now it allows me to work locally using git - make commits, revert, change branches, etc. Whenever I reach a logical end to the work, I create a shelveset and push the changes up the TFVC source control from Visual Studio.</p>

<p>If you want to interact with the TFVC source control straight from the command line, you can try out <a href="https://github.com/git-tfs/git-tfs">git-tfs</a> - a Git/TFS bridge. For me, since I am happy working locally with git and pushing up the finished work as shelvesets from Visual Studio I have not explored the git-tfs tool.</p>

<p>Hope this helps someone if you feel stuck with TFVC repositories!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Spigen - Awesome Phone Cases]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/spigen-awesome-phone-cases/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/spigen-awesome-phone-cases</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are looking to get a case for your phone, then check out cases by <a href="https://www.spigen.com/">Spigen</a>. I have been using Spigen cases for over three years, and I totally recommend it.</p>

<p>Spigen cases are made with premium materials and are slim, sleek and simple. Spigen provides various models that match different needs. The cases provide <a href="https://www.spigen.com/pages/military-grade">Military Grade Protection</a> and protect the phone from most falls. It fits</p>

<p>The first Spigen cases I got was for my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/">Nexus 5</a>. The Neo Hybrid lasted for over three years. With the Spigen cases, the Nexus was well protected. It did fall from my hands many times, and every time the case protected it well enough. A couple of months back the Spigen case broke, and I had been using the phone without a cover since then. Unfortunately, during one of my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">morning runs</a> the phone fell from my hands while slipping it into the armband. Without the Spigen to protect it, the Nexus screen broke at the corners.</p>

<p><img src="/images/spigen_pixel.png" alt="Spigen Neo Hybrid for Pixel" class="center" /></p>

<p>A month back I switched over to Google Pixel as the Nexus was becoming unusable with the broken screen. I got the <a href="https://www.spigen.com/collections/pixel/products/google-pixel-case-neo-hybrid?variant=29248762049">Spigen NeoHybrid for Pixel</a>. The case provides dual layer protection with TCU and PC bumper and comes with fingerprint resistance. The precise cutouts give easy access to all buttons and fingerprint sensor.</p>

<p>If you are looking to a get a case, check out if <a href="https://www.spigen.com/">Spigen</a> has one for your model!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: PNGGauntlet - Smash PNGs for Faster Sites]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/pnggauntlet-smash-pngs-for-faster-sites/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/pnggauntlet-smash-pngs-for-faster-sites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I upload images to my blog, I try to keep the file size as small as possible. Reducing image size helps improve the site load time. To grab screenshots I use <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/screenshots-with-snagit/">Snagit</a> and use <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/paint-dot-net/">Paint.net</a> for any editing and resizing the images.</p>

<p>To further optimize images and compress them I use <a href="">PNGGauntlet</a><a href="https://pnggauntlet.com/.">https://pnggauntlet.com/.</a> PNGGauntlet combines <a href="http://advsys.net/ken/util/pngout.htm">PNGOUT</a>, <a href="http://optipng.sourceforge.net/">OptiPNG</a> and DeflOpt and helps smash PNG&rsquo;s to the smallest size.</p>

<p><img src="/images/pnggauntlet.png" alt="PNG Gauntlet" class="center" /></p>

<p>PNGGauntlet provides options to configure the PNG output. You can play around with the options for the best output. I use the default options and has been working fine for me.</p>

<p>Check out <a href="https://pnggauntlet.com/">PNGGauntlet</a> to optimize images for the web.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Paint.net - A Layman's Photoshop]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/paint-dot-net/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/paint-dot-net</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For my blog&rsquo;s I often have to edit, resize, modify images often. The default paint application with Windows lacks a lot of features while <a href="http://www.adobe.com/au/products/photoshop.html">Photoshop</a> is too advanced for my needs. <a href="https://www.getpaint.net/index.html">Paint.net</a> is a freely available tool with many advanced features and is lightweight.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Paint.NET is free image and photo editing software for PCs that run Windows. It features an intuitive and innovative user interface with support for layers, unlimited undo, special effects, and a wide variety of useful and powerful tools</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.getpaint.net/screenshots.html">
<img src= "/images/pain_net_screen.png" alt="Paint.Net" class="center" />
</a></p>

<p>In addition to the basic features expected off an image editing tool, paint.net supports layers, create special effects with unlimited history/undo. It also includes gradient tool, Magic Wand, Clone Stamp, etc. for advanced editing. Every action performed on the image is recorded in the History window and allows undoing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.getpaint.net/download.html">Download</a> the latest version of paint.net for free.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Pocket - Don't Miss Out on the Articles That You Want to Read Later]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/pocket-offline-reading-made-easy/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/pocket-offline-reading-made-easy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/pocket.jpg" alt="Pocket" class="center" /></p>

<p>I try to stay offline for fixed times during the day and often <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-productive-offline/">prepare myself up for it</a>. Having things to read is one of the important things to it. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/feedly-one-stop-reading-place/">Feedly</a> allows to keep track of all the reading sources that I have, while I am online. Some articles need more time and focus to be well understood, and I often end up &lsquo;Saving them for Later.&rsquo;</p>

<p><a href="https://getpocket.com">Pocket</a> is an app that helps manage articles that you wish to read later. You can save articles, videos or pretty much anything into Pocket and view them later. The best thing about Pocket is that on mobile devices, it allows offline reading - i.e., without the need for an internet connection.</p>

<p>Pocket has <a href="https://getpocket.com/add/?ep=1">apps and browser extensions</a> for a variety of platforms making it easy to save articles that you find interesting. You can save to pocket while on your laptop or your mobile devices and have it available for later reading. Feedly integrates with Pocket and allows to save articles for future reading straight to Pocket. I am using the free version of Pocketand it works perfectly for me. But if you are interested in more advanced features you can upgrade to the <a href="https://getpocket.com/premium?ep=1">Premium version</a>.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t miss out on that article that you want to read (later), <a href="https://getpocket.com">Get Pocket</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
