<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tipow | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-06-05T00:02:24+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Prettier - An Opinionated Code Formatter]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/prettier-an-opinionated-code-formatter/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/prettier-an-opinionated-code-formatter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Code Formatting is an essential aspect of writing code, and I did write about this a while back on <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/introducing-code-formatting-into-a-large-codebase/">introducing code formatting into a large code base</a>. It&rsquo;s not about what all rules you and your team use, it&rsquo;s about sticking with the conventions and using them consistently. Code Formatting rules are best when applied automatically, and the developer does not need to do anything in particular about it.</p>

<p><a href="https://prettier.io/">Prettier</a> is an opinionated code formatter, which supports multiple languages and editors and easy to get started. Getting set up is as easy as just installing the <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/install.html">prettier package using yarn/npm</a>. There are multiple points at which you can integrate Prettier - <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/editors.html">in your editor</a>, <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/precommit.html">pre-commit hook</a> or <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/cli.html#list-different">CI environments</a>.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zgWBAKZvdFQ" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Most of the IDE&rsquo;s have plugins for Prettier which makes it easy to get it into the code right from the beginning. You might need to update your IDE settings to run prettier when you save a file. For VS Code I have to set editor.formatOnSave to true to turn on this behaviour.</p>

<p>As the title says, Prettier is opinionated, which is useful in many ways and removes much time wasted on unnecessary discussions. However, it does provide some <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/configuration.html">configuration options</a>. Check if it provides enough for you to call a meeting to decide on one of them :).</p>

<p>Write prettier code!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Check If You Have Been Hacked!]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/check-if-you-have-been-hacked/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/check-if-you-have-been-hacked</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/password_manager.jpg" alt ="https://pixabay.com/en/data-security-keyboard-computer-1590455/" class="center" /></p>

<p>With more and more data breaches happening it is possible that your personal information and passwords are already compromised. If you have been lazy and reusing passwords (just like me until a while back) across multiple sites then it is good to check if your password is already compromised. It necessarily need not be one of your social media account or bank account that needs to be compromised for an attacker to get your credentials. If you have been reusing passwords across sites, it might be that one site where security is not given much importance for that gets breached, exposing your credentials to the attacker or anyone who has the breached data. Often hackers use this information to try and enumerate other sites, social network, bank logins to try and login assuming the behaviour of password reuse.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Check your <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/">email</a> or <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/Passwords">password</a> to see if any has been part of a data breach.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>To check if you have been part of a data breach you can use the service <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/">haveibeenpwned</a>. If you have been part of any data breaches, then it will show you the details. In addition to that, you can also use the <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/Passwords">Pwned Passwords</a> list to check if the password that you use has been part of any data breaches. It&rsquo;s good to change your password if you find yours in there. If you are worried about entering your password in haveibeenpwned site, the good thing is that it uses <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/ive-just-launched-pwned-passwords-version-2/">k-anonymity model</a>, which means that your full password is not sent across the wire.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<ul>
<li>Update your passwords on all sites that you use if you have been reusing passwords. If you don&rsquo;t have much time to do this in one shot, you can do this incrementally as and when you next visit them.</li>
<li>Make sure you have unique passwords for each of the site. <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/only-secure-password-is-one-you-cant/">A good password is one that you cannot remember</a>. So if you are not using a <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/password-manager-get-one-if-you-havent-already/">Password Manager</a> it&rsquo;s a good idea to start using. If you don&rsquo;t want to spend money on a password manager, you can always use a <a href="https://www.lastpass.com/password-generator">random password generator</a> to generate one for you. Remembering that password might be hard, you could either write it down or save it in the browser (not that I am recommending it over getting a Password Manager, but better than reusing passwords).</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Authy - Sync Two Factor Authentication Across Devices]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/authy-sync-two-factor-authentication-across-devices/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/authy-sync-two-factor-authentication-across-devices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-factor_authentication">Two Factor Authentication</a> (2FA) is becoming more and more common these days and is a good way to protect your accounts from getting into the wrong hands. SMS and App based 2FA are more common with the day to day services that we use, like Gmail, Outlook, Facebook etc. Enabling 2FA the user is prompted for a number that gets sent to them via phone or generated using an application, in addition to the username and password, when logging in. Enabling 2FA protects your account a level further. Even if an attacker has your credentials from a data breach, they would still need access to your phone to log in to your account. Using an app to generate the codes is more preferable than using SMS as it does not require internet connectivity or mobile service.</p>

<p>Until lately I have been using <a href="https://support.google.com/accounts/answer/1066447?hl=en&amp;ref_topic=2954345">Google Authenticator</a> to generate codes for all the accounts that I have 2FA enabled. The app does work well on a single mobile device but becomes a pain when you want to switch phones or lose the phone. You could potentially be locked out of your accounts if you lose the phone and don&rsquo;t have the backup codes available.</p>

<p><img src="/images/authy_preview.png" alt="Authy" class="center" /></p>

<p><a href="https://authy.com/features/">Authy</a> is one of the best-rated 2FA application which targets exactly the issues with Google Authenticator. It is easy to setup, can be secured via TouchId/Password, supports encrypted backups and syncs across multiple applications and devices. Once setup any code that you add to your app gets synced through Authy servers and is all encrypted and secured. Authy has applications for the <a href="https://authy.com/download/">mobile, desktop and also has a plugin for Chrome browser</a>. You can also manage devices from the account and revoke a device if it gets lost or is not used anymore. <a href="https://authy.com/blog/authy-vs-google-authenticator/">Authy vs Google Authentication post</a> covers in detail all the differences between the two and the advantages of using Authy.</p>

<p>Check out <a href="https://authy.com/features/">Authy</a> and do setup 2FA if you are not already!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Four Finger Swipe Gesture to Switch Between Virtual Machines]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/four-finger-swipe-gesture-to-switch-between-virtual-machines/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/four-finger-swipe-gesture-to-switch-between-virtual-machines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Of late I have been working for multiple clients at the same time. Different clients have different development environments, which has forced me into using Virual Machines (VM&rsquo;s) for my day to day work. I will cover my actual setup and new way of working using VM&rsquo;s in a different post.</p>

<p>When working on VM&rsquo;s I often have to switch to the host machine for email, chat and a few other programs that I have just on my host machine. Minimizing the VM host is time consuming and context breaking if you are working off a single screen. On a multi monitor setup you can always have VM on one screen and host on the other. This can still get tricky if you have more than one VM&rsquo;s connected.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fcbqOe8LnhM" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>The <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windowsexperience/2015/04/16/virtual-desktops-in-windows-10-the-power-of-windowsmultiplied/">Virtual Desktops</a> feature in Windows 10 is of great help in this scenario. We can move between desktops using keyboard shortcuts (Ctrl + Win + Right/Left Arrow). But with the VM running on separate Virtual Desktop any key presses gets picked up by the VM operating system and not by the host. This means that you cannot use the keyboard shortcuts to switch host desktops from inside a VM. However you can move between desktops using the Four Finger swipe gesture on your touchpad (if that is supported). These swipe gestures are picked up only by the host machine OS, unlike the keyboard shortcuts. So even when you are inside a VM, doing the four finger swipe gesture tells the host OS to switch desktops. This allows you to easily navigate between VM&rsquo;s running on different Virtual Desktops.</p>

<p>Hope this helps!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Text Editing - Convert Text Casing]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/text-editing-convert-text-casing/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/text-editing-convert-text-casing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Often when working with SQL queries, I come across the need to capitalize SQL keywords across in a large query. For, e.g., to capitalize SELECT, WHERE, FROM clauses in an SQL query. When it is a large query/stored procedure, it is faster done using some text editor. Sublime Text is my preferred editor for such kind of text manipulations.</p>

<p>Sublime Text Editor comes with a few built-in text casing converters that we can use, to convert text from one case to another. Using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simultaneous_editing">simultaneous editing</a> feature, we can combine it with case conversion and manipulate large documents easily.</p>

<p><img src="/images/textediting_convert_case.png" alt="Convert case options in sublime text" ></p>

<p>For example, let&rsquo;s say I have this below SQL query. As you can notice the SELECT and FROM keywords are cased differently across the query.</p>

<pre><code class="sql">select * From Table1
select * From Table2
select * From Table3
SELECT * FROM Table4
Select * From Table5
</code></pre>

<p>To standardize this (preferably capitalize all), highlight one of the &lsquo;select&rsquo; keywords and highlight all occurrences of the keyword (ALT + F3). Once all occurrences of &lsquo;select&rsquo; is highlighted, bring up the <a href="http://docs.sublimetext.info/en/latest/extensibility/command_palette.html">command pallete</a> (CTRL + SHIFT + P on windows) and search for &lsquo;Convert Case&rsquo;. From the options listed choose the case that you want to convert. All selected occurrences of the keyword will now be in the selected case.</p>

<p>Hope this helps you when you have a lot of text case manipulations to be done.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
