<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tipow | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-04T00:01:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Kumon Books - Creative Workbooks]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/kumon-books-creative-workbooks/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/kumon-books-creative-workbooks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s always hard to keep young minds engaged and fresh. As a parent, it is good to have a few different options to keep your child engaged and also at the same time help them learn. Activity books are a great way of keeping kids involved and help them develop the skills that they need in their lives.</p>

<p><a href="http://kumonbooks.com/">Kumon Books</a> offer a wide variety of books for different <a href="http://kumonbooks.com/books/by-grade/">age groups</a> and <a href="http://kumonbooks.com/books/by-subject/basic/">subjects</a>. The books follow a progression and are meant to be used in the sequence to helps kids progress by building on previous skills. The <a href="http://kumonbooks.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2015-Workbook-Chart.pdf">workbook chart</a> helps if you are new to Kumon Books. You can also choose by your <a href="http://kumonbooks.com/books/by-grade/">kids age</a> if you don&rsquo;t find the chart useful.</p>

<p><img src="/images/kumon_books.png" alt="center" alt="Kumon Books" /></p>

<p>The books cover a variety of activities like coloring, cutting paper, folding, pasting stickers, reading, writing, maths, etc. Each book easily introduces the concept and makes your child repeat it over and over again until it becomes clear to them before moving to advanced skills. Activity books like cutting, folding, paste, etc. are intended to be used once but for the other ones like writing, reading, math, etc. you can get your child to use a pencil and erase it off if you want them to refresh on the skills sometimes.</p>

<p>We have got books across most of the activities for Gautham and found it valuable. The books have helped him learn to read, write, cut, paint, etc. and highly recommend to others. These books also give an excellent way to interact with your child and help him learn and grow.</p>

<p>Your local bookstore or online stores should be having these books. Google should be of help otherwise. Hope you find it useful!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Reading Eggs - Learning To Read Can Be Easy And Fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/reading-eggs-learning-to-read-can-be-easy-and-fun/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/reading-eggs-learning-to-read-can-be-easy-and-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of months back Gautham (my son) started playing <a href="https://readingeggs.com.au/">Reading Eggs</a>. We started off initially with a free trial after it being recommended by our friend <a href="https://www.facebook.com/asha.maria.90">Asha</a>. We got a 21-day extended trial in addition to the initial 21 days free trial (i.e a total of 42 days), which helped a lot with confirming that Gautham was to use this app. We noticed that he was reading small words quite comfortably and he grew an interest to read various things around. We took an annual subscription and feels totally worth it.</p>

<p><img src="/images/readingEggs_Levels.jpg" alt="Reading Eggs Levels" ></p>

<blockquote><p>Using the five essential keys to reading success, the program unlocks all aspects of learning to read for your child.</p>

<ul>
<li>The lessons use colourful animation, fun characters, songs, and rewards to keep children motivated.</li>
<li>The program is completely interactive to keep children on task.</li>
<li>When children start the program, they can complete a placement quiz to ensure they are starting at the correct reading level.</li>
<li>Parents can access detailed progress reports as well as hundreds of full-colour downloadable activity sheets that correspond with the lessons in the program.</li>
<li>The program includes over 2000 online books for kids – each ending with a comprehension quiz that assesses your child’s understanding.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Each level explores different letters/word combinations and has a knowledge quiz at the end of it to pass to the next level. <em>The program unlocks all aspects of learning to read for your child, focusing on a core curriculum of phonics and phonemic awareness, sight words, vocabulary, comprehension, and reading for meaning.</em></p>

<p>Do give the app a try if you have kids at home!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Prettier - An Opinionated Code Formatter]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/prettier-an-opinionated-code-formatter/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/prettier-an-opinionated-code-formatter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Code Formatting is an essential aspect of writing code, and I did write about this a while back on <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/introducing-code-formatting-into-a-large-codebase/">introducing code formatting into a large code base</a>. It&rsquo;s not about what all rules you and your team use, it&rsquo;s about sticking with the conventions and using them consistently. Code Formatting rules are best when applied automatically, and the developer does not need to do anything in particular about it.</p>

<p><a href="https://prettier.io/">Prettier</a> is an opinionated code formatter, which supports multiple languages and editors and easy to get started. Getting set up is as easy as just installing the <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/install.html">prettier package using yarn/npm</a>. There are multiple points at which you can integrate Prettier - <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/editors.html">in your editor</a>, <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/precommit.html">pre-commit hook</a> or <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/cli.html#list-different">CI environments</a>.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zgWBAKZvdFQ" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Most of the IDE&rsquo;s have plugins for Prettier which makes it easy to get it into the code right from the beginning. You might need to update your IDE settings to run prettier when you save a file. For VS Code I have to set editor.formatOnSave to true to turn on this behaviour.</p>

<p>As the title says, Prettier is opinionated, which is useful in many ways and removes much time wasted on unnecessary discussions. However, it does provide some <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/configuration.html">configuration options</a>. Check if it provides enough for you to call a meeting to decide on one of them :).</p>

<p>Write prettier code!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Check If You Have Been Hacked!]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/check-if-you-have-been-hacked/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/check-if-you-have-been-hacked</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/password_manager.jpg" alt ="https://pixabay.com/en/data-security-keyboard-computer-1590455/" class="center" /></p>

<p>With more and more data breaches happening it is possible that your personal information and passwords are already compromised. If you have been lazy and reusing passwords (just like me until a while back) across multiple sites then it is good to check if your password is already compromised. It necessarily need not be one of your social media account or bank account that needs to be compromised for an attacker to get your credentials. If you have been reusing passwords across sites, it might be that one site where security is not given much importance for that gets breached, exposing your credentials to the attacker or anyone who has the breached data. Often hackers use this information to try and enumerate other sites, social network, bank logins to try and login assuming the behaviour of password reuse.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Check your <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/">email</a> or <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/Passwords">password</a> to see if any has been part of a data breach.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>To check if you have been part of a data breach you can use the service <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/">haveibeenpwned</a>. If you have been part of any data breaches, then it will show you the details. In addition to that, you can also use the <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/Passwords">Pwned Passwords</a> list to check if the password that you use has been part of any data breaches. It&rsquo;s good to change your password if you find yours in there. If you are worried about entering your password in haveibeenpwned site, the good thing is that it uses <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/ive-just-launched-pwned-passwords-version-2/">k-anonymity model</a>, which means that your full password is not sent across the wire.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<ul>
<li>Update your passwords on all sites that you use if you have been reusing passwords. If you don&rsquo;t have much time to do this in one shot, you can do this incrementally as and when you next visit them.</li>
<li>Make sure you have unique passwords for each of the site. <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/only-secure-password-is-one-you-cant/">A good password is one that you cannot remember</a>. So if you are not using a <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/password-manager-get-one-if-you-havent-already/">Password Manager</a> it&rsquo;s a good idea to start using. If you don&rsquo;t want to spend money on a password manager, you can always use a <a href="https://www.lastpass.com/password-generator">random password generator</a> to generate one for you. Remembering that password might be hard, you could either write it down or save it in the browser (not that I am recommending it over getting a Password Manager, but better than reusing passwords).</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Authy - Sync Two Factor Authentication Across Devices]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/authy-sync-two-factor-authentication-across-devices/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/authy-sync-two-factor-authentication-across-devices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-factor_authentication">Two Factor Authentication</a> (2FA) is becoming more and more common these days and is a good way to protect your accounts from getting into the wrong hands. SMS and App based 2FA are more common with the day to day services that we use, like Gmail, Outlook, Facebook etc. Enabling 2FA the user is prompted for a number that gets sent to them via phone or generated using an application, in addition to the username and password, when logging in. Enabling 2FA protects your account a level further. Even if an attacker has your credentials from a data breach, they would still need access to your phone to log in to your account. Using an app to generate the codes is more preferable than using SMS as it does not require internet connectivity or mobile service.</p>

<p>Until lately I have been using <a href="https://support.google.com/accounts/answer/1066447?hl=en&amp;ref_topic=2954345">Google Authenticator</a> to generate codes for all the accounts that I have 2FA enabled. The app does work well on a single mobile device but becomes a pain when you want to switch phones or lose the phone. You could potentially be locked out of your accounts if you lose the phone and don&rsquo;t have the backup codes available.</p>

<p><img src="/images/authy_preview.png" alt="Authy" class="center" /></p>

<p><a href="https://authy.com/features/">Authy</a> is one of the best-rated 2FA application which targets exactly the issues with Google Authenticator. It is easy to setup, can be secured via TouchId/Password, supports encrypted backups and syncs across multiple applications and devices. Once setup any code that you add to your app gets synced through Authy servers and is all encrypted and secured. Authy has applications for the <a href="https://authy.com/download/">mobile, desktop and also has a plugin for Chrome browser</a>. You can also manage devices from the account and revoke a device if it gets lost or is not used anymore. <a href="https://authy.com/blog/authy-vs-google-authenticator/">Authy vs Google Authentication post</a> covers in detail all the differences between the two and the advantages of using Authy.</p>

<p>Check out <a href="https://authy.com/features/">Authy</a> and do setup 2FA if you are not already!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
