<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tipow | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-25T00:02:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Pocket - Don't Miss Out on the Articles That You Want to Read Later]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/pocket-offline-reading-made-easy/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/pocket-offline-reading-made-easy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/pocket.jpg" alt="Pocket" class="center" /></p>

<p>I try to stay offline for fixed times during the day and often <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-productive-offline/">prepare myself up for it</a>. Having things to read is one of the important things to it. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/feedly-one-stop-reading-place/">Feedly</a> allows to keep track of all the reading sources that I have, while I am online. Some articles need more time and focus to be well understood, and I often end up &lsquo;Saving them for Later.&rsquo;</p>

<p><a href="https://getpocket.com">Pocket</a> is an app that helps manage articles that you wish to read later. You can save articles, videos or pretty much anything into Pocket and view them later. The best thing about Pocket is that on mobile devices, it allows offline reading - i.e., without the need for an internet connection.</p>

<p>Pocket has <a href="https://getpocket.com/add/?ep=1">apps and browser extensions</a> for a variety of platforms making it easy to save articles that you find interesting. You can save to pocket while on your laptop or your mobile devices and have it available for later reading. Feedly integrates with Pocket and allows to save articles for future reading straight to Pocket. I am using the free version of Pocketand it works perfectly for me. But if you are interested in more advanced features you can upgrade to the <a href="https://getpocket.com/premium?ep=1">Premium version</a>.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t miss out on that article that you want to read (later), <a href="https://getpocket.com">Get Pocket</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Feedly - One Stop Reading Place]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/feedly-one-stop-reading-place/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/feedly-one-stop-reading-place</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you want a one stop reading place to stay current and updated with posts from various blogs of your interest?</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Feedly is a news aggregator application that compiles news feeds from a variety of online sources</em></p></blockquote>

<p> <a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a> is what you are looking for. You can subscribe to the sites and news sources that you want to follow and Feedly shows that as a combined list for you.</p>

<p>News sources can be grouped into custom collections to group similar categories of information. Feedly offers a clean and minimalist reading experience, removing all the ads and other elements that create clutter. You can save articles to be read later, mark as favorite, share articles and a lot more.</p>

<p><img src="/images/feedly_site.png" class="center" alt="Feedly" /></p>

<p>Feedly has <a href="https://feedly.com/apps.html">apps and browser plugins</a> for a broad range of platforms and provides a uniform experience across devices. Currently, I am on the free version of the application, and it has a limit of 100 feeds. The <a href="https://feedly.com/i/pro/">pro version</a> provides a lot more features if you are interested.</p>

<p>Get a one stop reading place, Get <a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Password Manager - Get One If you Haven't Already]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/password-manager-get-one-if-you-havent-already/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/password-manager-get-one-if-you-havent-already</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/password_manager.jpg" alt ="https://pixabay.com/en/data-security-keyboard-computer-1590455/" class="center" /></p>

<p>First things first; <strong>Check if any of your accounts on the web has been compromised in the various data breaches</strong>. All you need is enter your email address in <a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/">haveibeenpwned</a>, and it tells you the rest.</p>

<p>My email did show up on multiple breaches, and there is nothing much that you can do about it anyways. The problem with data breaches is not confined just to the site that got breached but also with other sites if you have reused your passwords. The best that we can do is to use different passwords for each account that we create and never reuse them across sites. Also, remember to use &lsquo;stronger&rsquo; passwords. So what makes a password stronger? - <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/only-secure-password-is-one-you-cant/">The one that you cannot remember</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Password_manager">Password manager</a> assists in generating, storing, and retrieving complex passwords from an encrypted database</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Password Managers allows keeping all your passwords in a single strongly encrypted location. This manager itself is protected by a password - the master password!. The master password is the only password that you need to remember, so make sure you <a href="https://support.1password.com/strong-master-password/">get this really strong</a>!</p>

<p>There are different <a href="http://au.pcmag.com/password-managers-products/4524/guide/the-best-password-managers-of-2017">password managers</a> out there, both paid and free. Personally, I use <a href="https://1password.com/">1Password</a> and love the experience that it has across all my devices. Initially, I was worried to have my passwords (password since I was mostly reusing the same one) on a cloud store with an external service. But with all these data breaches that I was part of and having realized that not having one is worse than having it in the cloud. <em><a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/password-managers-dont-have-to-be-perfect-they-just-have-to-be-better-than-not-having-one/">Password managers don&rsquo;t have to be perfect, they just have to be better than not having one</a></em>. Having a password manager does not prevent your from being part of data breaches, but at least it protects your accounts elsewhere as you have not reused the password.</p>

<p>So if you still remember your passwords or reuse them, go set yourself up with a password manager!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Visual Studio Task List - Keep Track of Your TODO Comments]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/visual-studio-task-list-keep-track-of-your-todo-comments/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/visual-studio-task-list-keep-track-of-your-todo-comments</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It often happens when coding that I skip over some part and want to come back to it at a later point in time. I leave some comments in the code so that I do not miss it. It can be a bit tricky to keep track of these comments themselves. Before pushing up the changes to <a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Branching-Branches-in-a-Nutshell">master branch</a> or creating a <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/about-pull-requests/">Pull Request</a>, I make sure that all such comments are addressed.</p>

<p>Visual Studio comes with a <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/txtwdysk(v=vs.120).aspx">Task List</a> that is handy to track such unfinished work in code. It helps track your pending work items in one place and easily navigate to it. To have a comment appear in the task list, it has to start with a defined token (TODO, HACK, UNDONE, etc.) followed by the comment.</p>

<pre><code class="csharp">public bool IsInRange(DateTime theDateTime)
{
    //TODO: Implement this function
    throw new NotImplementedException();
}
</code></pre>

<p><img src="/images/taskList.png" class="center" alt="Visual Studio Task List" /></p>

<blockquote><p><em>A comment in your code preceded by a comment marker and a predefined token will appear in the Task List window. For example, the above comment has three distinct parts:</em></p>

<ul>
<li><em>The comment marker (//)</em></li>
<li><em>The token (TODO)</em></li>
<li><em>The comment (the rest of the text)</em></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Visual Studio by default has TODO, HACK and UNDONE as tokens. You can modify this under Options -> Task List. New custom tokens can be added as required and used instead of the default ones.</p>

<p><img src="/images/taskList_customize.png" class="center" alt="Visual Studio, Customize Task List" /></p>

<p>When in a multi-member team you can either use custom tokens per member or append the comment with your name or feature name. The Task List provides Search feature with which you can filter the tasks created by you or for the feature you are working.</p>

<p>I try to remove all TODO comments before merging to the master branch. For tasks that need to be tracked even after a merge, I create separate work items to the project backlog (VSTS, GitHub Tasks, Jira whatever the team is using). I might still leave the TODO comment with the relevant ticket details as well for tracking.</p>

<p>The next time you leave some unfinished work for later make sure you have it tracked. Hope it helps!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: IF This Then That (IFTTT) - Connect Your Services]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/if-this-then-that-ifttt-connect-your-services/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/if-this-then-that-ifttt-connect-your-services</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IFTTT">IFTTT</a> is a free web-based service that people use to create chains of simple conditional statements, called applets. An applet is triggered by changes that occur within other web services such as Gmail, Facebook, Instagram, or Pinterest. An applet may send an e-mail message if the user tweets using a hashtag or to copy a photo on Facebook to a user&rsquo;s archive if someone tags a user in a photo</em></p>

<p>IFTTT helps you connect the services in your life. Most of the things that you use on the web is a service. There are a <a href="https://ifttt.com/search">broad range of services</a> that are available on IFTTT that you can start using right away. Each service has a set of triggers and actions. We can create applets which wire up triggers (if this) of one service to actions (then that) of another service.</p>

<p><img alt="IFTTT" src="/images/ifttt_recipe.png" class="center" /></p>

<p>There are a lot of <a href="https://ifttt.com/discover">pre-created applets</a> available for immediate use. You can also create custom applets that wire up the triggers and actions of services of your choice. For e.g. Whenever a new item is available on my blog <a href="https://ifttt.com/feed">RSS feed</a> I <a href="https://ifttt.com/gmail">send an email</a> to <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/buffer-smarter-social-sharing/">Buffer</a>. The email to Buffer triggers it to share the post to all my connected social media accounts.</p>

<p><img alt="IFTTT Recommended" src="/images/ifttt_popular.png" class="center" /></p>

<p>If you are consuming the services of IFTTT, then it is free to use. <a href="https://platform.ifttt.com/pricing">Paid plans</a> are for publishing your service and making it available for others to consume.
IFTTT also has apps for <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/app/apple-store/id660944635?mt=8">iOS</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.ifttt.ifttt&amp;utm_source=/about&amp;utm_medium=web">Android</a>. With the apps you can also use the mobile capabilities like location, messages, etc. to trigger actions.</p>

<p>Start connecting the dots between your services and get the web to work for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
