<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tipow | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-25T00:01:50+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Finding Keyboard Shortcuts on Websites]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/finding-keyboard-shortcuts-on-websites/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/finding-keyboard-shortcuts-on-websites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Keyboard Shortcuts" src="/images/keyboard_shortcuts.jpg" /></p>

<p>I prefer to use the keyboard to navigate within sites I use frequently. Keyboard enables to navigate faster within site and perform tasks quicker. The <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/review-six-months-and-counting-logitech-mx-master/">Logitech MX Master</a> mouse provides a lot of capabilities to navigate. But I find the keyboard faster to perform repetitive actions - like posting a new status update on social media sites, managing tasks in Jira, TFS online, GitHub, responding to emails, Todoist, etc. Finding keyboard shortcuts on these various sites can itself be a daunting task. One might need to google to get the shortcuts or find the relevant documentation on the site. Luckily most of the popular sites today display a pop-up modal with all the keyboard shortcuts for the site when pressing <strong>Shift + ?</strong>. Note that this might not work on all the sites out there. But for most of the common ones that I use l, I find it working.</p>

<p>So the next time you spend a lot of time on a website try hitting <strong>Shift + ?</strong> to look for supported keyboard shortcuts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Productivity Noise with Noisli]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/productivity-noise-with-noisli/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/productivity-noise-with-noisli</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are the kind of person that likes to listen to some music while working, then this one is for you. Music is proven to have significant effects on improving focus while working. But it is also quite possible to get fully immersed in the music and forget all about work. Different kinds of music contribute to improving concentration while not getting immersed in the music itself. I usually <a href="http://theheadphonesrule.com/">wear my headphones</a> at work while working and listen to music.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Music helps to minimize distractions and helps you reach a state of <a href="http://amzn.to/2jlYIgV">Flow</a>, which is ideal for improving productivity.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>At times I like to hear to just some background noises simulating different environments. <a href="https://www.noisli.com/">Noisli</a> is an application that helps mix different sounds and create your perfect environment. The sounds could either be working in a restaurant or while it&rsquo;s raining with thunder, in a forest, by the side of the fire, etc. It helps create the mood that you want and helps recreate it with sound. Since the noises are of a fixed pattern, you soon get used to it and improves concentration at work.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Noisli - Favorite Combos" src="/images/noisli_favorite.png" /></p>

<p>Here are my favorite mixes in Noisli.
<a href="https://www.noisli.com/get_combo_by_link/W5rvjLZXcoJbooq">Rain Mix</a>, <a href="https://www.noisli.com/get_combo_by_link/vjUpcG2OAXxKVSU">Jungle</a>, <a href="https://www.noisli.com/get_combo_by_link/uhRXMysAIcVEbHF">TRain</a>, <a href="https://www.noisli.com/get_combo_by_link/gFKhnETdoybxcmc">HotelRainFire</a></p>

<p>You can use Noisli directly from the <a href="https://www.noisli.com/">website</a> or use any of their <a href="https://www.noisli.com/apps">Apps and Extensions</a>. Find out what works for you and leave a comment on your favorite combos.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Paste Without Formatting]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/paste-without-formatting/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/paste-without-formatting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I share a lot of information copying and pasting from websites. Most of the times I want to share just the text and not any formatting. To remove any text formatting, I copy it into Notepad and then onto the destination. Yesterday I found that using <strong>Ctrl + Shift + V</strong> to paste (instead of <em>Ctrl + V</em>) removes all text formatting.</p>

<p>As shown, when using Ctrl + V the text gets copied along with the formatting as shown below.</p>

<p><img alt="Paste With Formatting" src="/images/paste_with_formatting.png" /></p>

<p>When using Ctrl + Shift + V, only the text gets copied and the formatting is ignored.
<img alt="Paste Without Formatting" src="/images/paste_without_formatting.png" /></p>

<p>Using this shortcut saves time as I no longer need to open Notepad for this!</p>

<p>PS: As one of my readers rightly pointed out (below in the comments), this might not work on all applications. I have tried this on Chrome Browser and Lync For Business and worked fine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
