<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tipow | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-29T00:01:56+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Rescue Time - Track Your Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/rescue-time-track-your-time/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/rescue-time-track-your-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Rescue Time - My dashboard for March,2017" src="/images/rescuetime.png" /></p>

<p>Tracking is essential for measuring progress. Depending on your area of focus tracking tools differ. If it is a time-based activity that you are tracking a simple watch can suffice the need. But this can soon become an overhead. <a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/">Rescue Time</a> helps track time spent on a computer or mobile devices.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Rescue Time is a  personal analytics service that shows you how you spend your time and provides tools to help you be more productive.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Rescue time runs in the background and helps you track the applications and websites that you use. Most of the applications are categorized automatically; However, it also allows manual categorization. Rescue Time lets you edit an activity and assign it to various categories and set productivity levels. So if you are spending more time on an application configured as <em>very productive</em> then your overall productivity pulse is higher for the day.</p>

<p><img alt="Rescue Time - Edit Activity" src="/images/rescuetime_edit_activity.png" /></p>

<p>Once you have your time tracked you can then adapt yourself to be more productive. Various reports are provided to visualize the data collected. The <a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/rescuetime-pro">premium version</a> offers a lot more features to help improve productivity. I am currently on the Free Plan. Rescue Time helps inspect your current behaviors and patterns at work. Once you have the details, you can understand where your time is spent and improve on it as required. Rescue Time is available for <a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/get_rescuetime">computer and mobile devices</a>. Hope this helps track your time and become more productive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Tomighty - A Pomodoro Timer]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tomighty-a-pomodoro-timer/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tomighty-a-pomodoro-timer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://tomighty.org/"><img alt="Tomighty, Pomodoro Timer" src="/images/tomighty.png" /></a></p>

<p>Over the past couple of weeks, I have been trying to improve my focus while working. With <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">running (3 * 1.5 hours a week) and bodyweight training (3 * 30 minutes a week)</a> taking a significant part of my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">morning routine</a>, I have less time for <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2016-recap/">blogging, learning, and videos</a>. Though I have known <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">The Pomodoro Technique</a> for a long time, I never practiced it regularly. With less time and more things to get done, I badly had to do something to get back on track with everything and thought of giving it a try.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The Pomodoro Technique is a time management technique that uses a timer to break down work into intervals, traditionally 25 minutes in length, separated by short breaks. These intervals are named Pomodoro</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Initially, I was looking at apps that can integrate with <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-manage-your-todo-list/">Todoist</a>, my task management tool. There are a lot of <a href="https://support.todoist.com/hc/en-us/articles/210762349-Pomodoro-with-Todoist">pomodoro apps that integrate with Todoist</a>, but I found all of them an overkill.
<a href="http://tomighty.org/"><strong>Tomighty</strong></a> is a simple Pomodoro timer that just tracks time and settings for the Pomodoro interval and long and short breaks. It hides away well in the Notification area of the taskbar and shows the amount of time left in the current interval. It plays sounds when an interval starts and ends. You can interrupt a Pomodoro session and restart it if required. That is all that you need from a timer to keep up with the Pomodoro technique.</p>

<p><em>If you are on a high DPI machine running Windows, the UI might not scale well. There is a <a href="https://github.com/tomighty/tomighty/issues/115">workaround</a> for this.</em></p>

<p>Sticking to the Pomodoro Technique has been working well for me, and I am able to focus better on the task at hand. I am still exploring the technique and trying to improve on it. Do you use Pomodoro Technique? If you are new to Pomodoro Technique and want to learn more check out the book, <a href="http://amzn.to/2nCSZW1">The Pomodoro Technique</a>, by Francesco Cirillo, the creator of the technique.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Track Current File in Visual Studio Solution Explorer]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/track-current-file-in-visual-studio-solution-explorer/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/track-current-file-in-visual-studio-solution-explorer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While working on large codebases, I want my Solution Explorer to be synchronized with the current working file. With the solution explorer in sync, it makes navigating to other related files, adding new classes in the same location, renaming files, etc. faster.</p>

<p><img alt="Track Active Item in Solution Explorer, Visual Studio" src="/images/visualstudio_trackActiveItem.png" /></p>

<p>The setting to keep the items in sync is configurable in Visual Studio and is turned off by default. You can enable this by checking the &lsquo;<strong><em>Track Active Item in Solution Explorer</em></strong>&rsquo; under <em>Options -> Projects and Solutions -> General</em>. You can navigate there quickly using <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/quick-launch-in-visual-studio/">Visual Studio Quick Launch (Ctrl + Q)</a>. Just type &lsquo;<em>Track active</em>&rsquo; and you will get the quick link to the setting. Keep it checked, and off you go, the solution explorer and the current file will be in sync.</p>

<p>PS: Visual Studio 2017 is now available.<a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/downloads/">Get it</a> if you have not already!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Switching Subscriptions Under Same Azure Account to Access Key Vaults]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/switching-between-subscriptions-under-same-azure-account-to-access-key-vault/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/switching-between-subscriptions-under-same-azure-account-to-access-key-vault</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" alt="Azure Powershell Get-AzureRmContext" src="/images/powershell_azurermcontext.png" /></p>

<p>When accessing Key Vault using Powershell it can be a bit tricky when you have multiple subscriptions under the same account. The Key Vault cmdlets being under the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-the-deprecation-of-switch-azuremode-affects-azure-key-vault/">Resource Manager (RM) mode</a> depends on the current RM Subscription. The Key Vault cmdlets enable you to manage only the key vaults under the selected subscription. To access the key vaults in other subscriptions, you need to switch the selected RM subscription.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Use <strong>Select-AzureRmSubscription</strong> to switch the selected RM subscription</em></p></blockquote>

<p> The <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/powershell/resourcemanager/azurerm.profile/v2.2.0/get-azurermcontext">Get-AzureRmContext</a> returns the metadata used for RM requests. The SubscriptionId/SubscriptionName property indicates the selected subscription. Any Key Vault cmdlets (or RM cmdlets) will work based off that selected subscription. To change the selected Azure RM subscription use the Select-AzureRmSubscription cmdlet. Pass in the SubscriptionId or the Subscription Name that you wish to switch to and the RM Subscription will be set to that. To get the SubscriptionId/SubscriptionName of the subscriptions under your account use <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn495302.aspx">Get-AzureSubscription</a> cmdlet.</p>

<pre><code class="` powershell"> Get-AzureRmContext
 Get-AzureRmSubscription
 Select-AzureRmSubscription -SubscriptionName  "Your Subscription Name"
 Select-AzureRmSubscription -SubscriptionId  a5287dad-d5a2-4060-81bc-4a06c7087e72
</code></pre>

<p> I struggled with this for some time, so hope it helps you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Todoist: Manage your To-Do List]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-manage-your-todo-list/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-manage-your-todo-list</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are the kind of person who wants to manage a list of tasks and like checking it off and moving towards a goal then this post is for you. I am a fan of the <a href="http://amzn.to/2gsJaed">Getting Things Done</a> methodology by David Allen and found the book and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=david+allen">videos</a> mind blowing. Ever since reading the book for the first time I had been searching for a tool that helps to follow the GTD process. Though the GTD process in itself is not tied to a particular tool and works well with pen and paper, I am more towards a digital medium, as that&rsquo;s where I spent most of my time. I have tried a lot of different tools, almost everything that came up when searching for to do lists.</p>

<p>Some of the key features that I was looking out of a to-do list application are</p>

<ul>
<li>Quickly Capture tasks from anywhere</li>
<li>Availability on multiple devices</li>
<li>Able to group and categorize tasks</li>
<li>Search</li>
<li>Assign date time and set reminders</li>
<li>Simplistic and easy user interface</li>
</ul>


<p><img alt="Todoist" src="/images/todoist.png" /></p>

<p><a href="https://todoist.com/">Todoist</a> is one platform that I found the best matching with my needs and have been with it for over two years. It started with a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-organized-finding-a-system-to-manage-it-all/#comment-1528539219">comment by my friend on one of my posts</a>. Since then I am using Todoist. After trying for a couple of weeks, I quickly moved on to their <a href="https://todoist.com/premium">premium version</a> for the various features that it provides. Todoist has a clean and minimalistic interface and never stays in the way of getting things done. Be it the mobile app, the desktop app or the Chrome plugin; it enables easy task management. Any new task added by default goes into the Inbox which can be categorized and processed later. This processing flow fits with the process outlined in GTD. Tasks can be assigned labels and categories, set priorities, set for action on a specific date. Tasks added to one app is synced across all the apps seamlessly., enabling a smooth and consistent experience across.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Getting Things Done is tool agnostic. Tools do not matter; it is about the process. Choose any tool that works for you, for me it&rsquo;s Todoist</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Todoist had all the features that I was looking out for in a task management application. Give Todoist a try if you are looking out for a task management application. Irrespective of the tools that you use it is your ability to stick to a plan and focus on tasks that will help you reach your goal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
