<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: azure | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/azure/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-06-02T00:01:33+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Azure Web App Restarting Automatically Due to Overwhelming Change Notification]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-web-restarting-automatically-due-to-overwhelming-change-notification/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-web-restarting-automatically-due-to-overwhelming-change-notification</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At one of my clients, we faced a strange issue recently. The Azure Web application restarted automatically very often. The event log in the <a href="https://github.com/projectkudu/kudu/wiki/Kudu-console">Kudu console</a> showed the below error message.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>2017-07-13 00:09:50,333 [P45516/D4/T171] INFO  Umbraco.Core.UmbracoApplicationBase - Application shutdown. Details: HostingEnvironment</em></p>

<p><em>_shutDownMessage=Directory rename change notification for &rsquo;D:\home\site\wwwroot&#8217;.</em>  <br/>
<em>Overwhelming Change Notification in wwwroot</em>   <br/>
<em>HostingEnvironment initiated shutdown</em>  <br/>
<em>Directory rename change notification for &rsquo;D:\home\site\wwwroot&#8217;.</em>   <br/>
<em>Overwhelming Change Notification in wwwroot</em>   <br/>
<em>Initialization Error</em>   <br/>
<em>HostingEnvironment caused shutdown</em></p></blockquote>

<p>As you can tell from the logs, the website is an <a href="https://umbraco.com/">Umbraco</a> CMS hosted as an Azure Web application. We noticed that the restarts were happening more when the content was getting updated through <a href="https://our.umbraco.org/documentation/getting-started/backoffice/">backoffice</a>. The error also states that the restart was caused due to <em>Overwhelming Change Notification in wwwroot</em>. This hints that there are changes that are happening under the wwwroot folder, where the site is hosted.</p>

<div class="alert alert-info">
Even though this post details on why the specific site on Umbraco was restarting, most of the contents are still applicable for any other ASP.NET MVC application.
</div>


<h3>fcnMode Configuration</h3>

<p>A quick search got me to the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.web.configuration.httpruntimesection.fcnmode(v=vs.110">fcnMode</a>.aspx)setting under <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.web.configuration.httpruntimesection(v=vs.110">httpRuntime</a>.aspx) section. An ASP.net application monitors certain files and folders under the wwwroot folder and will restart the application domain whenever it detects changes. This likely look looks the reason why the web site is restarting.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.web.configuration.fcnmode(v=vs.110">fcnMode enumeration</a>.aspx) can take one of the four values below. For an Umbraco application this is by <a href="http://issues.umbraco.org/issue/U4-7712">default set to <em>Single</em></a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Default</strong>: For each subdirectory, the application creates an object that monitors the subdirectory. This is the default behavior.</li>
<li><strong>Disabled</strong>: File change notification is disabled.</li>
<li><strong>NotSet</strong>: File change notification is not set, so the application creates an object that monitors each subdirectory. This is the default behavior.</li>
<li><strong>Single</strong>: The application creates one object to monitor the main directory and uses this object to monitor each subdirectory.</li>
</ul>


<pre><code class="xml fcnMode set to Single for Umbraco application">&lt;system.web&gt;
    ...
    &lt;httpRuntime 
        requestValidationMode="2.0" 
        enableVersionHeader="false"
        targetFramework="4.5"
        maxRequestLength="51200" 
        fcnMode="Single" /&gt;
    ...
&lt;system.web&gt;
</code></pre>

<blockquote><p><em>FCNMode creates a monitor object with a buffer size of 4KB for each folder. When FCNMode is set to Single, a single monitor object is created with a buffer size of 64KB. When there are file changes, the buffer is filled with file change information. If the buffer gets overwhelmed with too many file change notifications an “Overwhelming File Change Notifications” error will occur and the app domain will recycle. The likelihood of the buffer getting overwhelmed is higher in an environment where you are using separate file server because the folder paths are much larger.</em></p>

<p>-<a href="http://www.dnnsoftware.com/community-blog/cid/154980/aspnet-file-change-notifications-and-dnn"> ASP.NET File Change Notifications and DNN</a></p></blockquote>

<p>You can read more about fcnMode setting and how it affects ASP.Net applications <a href="https://shazwazza.com/post/all-about-aspnet-file-change-notification-fcn/">here</a>.</p>

<h3>What&rsquo;s causing file changes?</h3>

<p>Default reaction when you come across such a setting or configuration value might be to turn that off and fcnMode does allow that as well - <em>Disabled</em>. But first, it is better that we understand what is causing file changes under the wwwroot folder and see if we can address that. The <a href="https://shazwazza.com/post/fcn-file-change-notification-viewer-for-aspnet/">FCN Viewer</a> helps visualize how many files and folders are being watched in as ASP.Net application.</p>

<p>In the Umbraco website, we are using a third party library <a href="http://imageprocessor.org/">ImageProcessor</a> that helps to process images dynamically. The ImageProcessor caches images and the <a href="http://imageprocessor.org/imageprocessor-web/configuration/#cacheconfig">cache location is configurable</a>. By default, it caches files under the App_Data/cache folder, which also happens to be one of the folders that the ASP.Net application monitors for changes. So anytime there are lots of files changing in the cache folder it causes the single monitor object monitoring the folders. This causes a buffer overflow and triggers an application restart due to <em>Overwhelming file change notifications</em>. However, ImageProcessor does allow moving the <a href="https://github.com/JimBobSquarePants/ImageProcessor/issues/518">cache folder outside of the wwwroot folder</a>. This causes the file not to be monitored and still work fine with the application. Since the <a href="https://twitter.com/Shazwazza/status/885770960321773568">library does not create the cache folder automatically</a>, we need to make sure that the folder specified in the config file exists.</p>

<p>Having moved the cache folder outside of the wwwroot, I no longer need to update the fcnMode setting and can leave it as intended. If you are facing application restarts as well due to overwhelming change notification in wwwroot see what is likely causing the file changes and then try and fix that instead of just setting the fcnMode to disabled.</p>

<p>Hope that helps fix your application restarting problem!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Azure Key Vault From Azure Functions - Certificate Based Authentication]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-from-azure-functions-certificate-based-authentication/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-from-azure-functions-certificate-based-authentication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the previous post we saw how to connect to <a href="/blog/azure-key-vault-from-azure-functions/">Azure Key Vault from Azure Functions</a>. We used the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/authenticating-a-client-application-with-azure-key-vault/">Application Id and Secret to authenticate with the Azure AD Application</a>. Since the general recommendation is to use certificate-based authentication, in this post, we will see how we can use certificates to authenticate from within an Azure Function.</p>

<p>First, we need to create an Azure AD application and set it up to use certificate-based authentication. Create a new service principal for the AD application and associate that with the Azure Key Vault. Authorize the AD application with the permissions required. In this case, I am providing all access to keys and secrets.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">$certificateFilePath = "C:\certificates\ADTestVaultApplication.cer"
$certificate = New-Object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Certificate2
$certificate.Import($certificateFilePath)
$rawCertificateData = $certificate.GetRawCertData()
$credential = [System.Convert]::ToBase64String($rawCertificateData)
$startDate= [System.DateTime]::Now
$endDate = $startDate.AddYears(1)
$adApplication = New-AzureRmADApplication -DisplayName "CertAdApplication" -HomePage  "http://www.test.com" -IdentifierUris "http://www.test.com" -CertValue $credential  -StartDate $startDate -EndDate $endDate

$servicePrincipal = New-AzureRmADServicePrincipal -ApplicationId $adApplication.ApplicationId

Set-AzureRmKeyVaultAccessPolicy -VaultName 'RahulKeyVault' -ServicePrincipalName $servicePrincipal.ServicePrincipalNames[0] -PermissionsToSecrets all -PermissionToKeys all 
</code></pre>

<p>Create an Azure Function App under your subscription as shown below. You can also use the same application created in the previous post (if you did create one).</p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_newFunctionApp.png" alt="Azure Function New App" class="center" /></p>

<p>In the Function Apps page, select the app just created. Add a new function like in the last post. Selecting the Function App shows the available set of actions. Under the <em>Platform Features</em> tab we can upload the SSL certificates first and then update the Application Certificates to make the certificate available for the function.</p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_PlatformFeatures.png" alt="Azure Function Platform Features" class="center" /></p>

<p>Upload the certificate by selecting it from your folder system.</p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_addCertificate.png" alt="Azure Function Upload Certificate" class="center" /></p>

<p>For the certificate to be available for use in the Azure Functions an entry should be present in Application Settings. Under <em>Application Settings</em> in the <em>Platform Features</em> tab add App settings key and value - <em>WEBSITE_LOAD_CERTIFICATES</em> and the certificate thumbprint This makes the certificate available for consumption within the function. Multiple thumbprints can be specified comma separated if required.</p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_AppSetting.png" alt="Azure Function Certificates App Settings" class="center" /></p>

<p>Using a certificate to authenticate with the Key Vault is the same as we have <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/authenticating-a-client-application-with-azure-key-vault/">seen before</a>.</p>

<pre><code class="csharp">using System;
using Microsoft.Azure.KeyVault;
using Microsoft.IdentityModel.Clients.ActiveDirectory;
using System.Security.Cryptography;
using System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates;

private const string applicationId = "AD Application ID";
private const string certificateThumbprint = "Certificate Thumbprint";

public async static Task Run(TimerInfo myTimer, TraceWriter log)
{
    var keyClient = new KeyVaultClient(async (authority, resource, scope) =&gt;
{
    var authenticationContext = new AuthenticationContext(authority, null);
    X509Certificate2 certificate;
    X509Store store = new X509Store(StoreName.My, StoreLocation.CurrentUser);
    try
    {
        store.Open(OpenFlags.ReadOnly);
        X509Certificate2Collection certificateCollection = store.Certificates.Find(X509FindType.FindByThumbprint, certificateThumbprint, false);
        if (certificateCollection == null || certificateCollection.Count == 0)
        {
            throw new Exception("Certificate not installed in the store");
        }

        certificate = certificateCollection[0];
    }
    finally
    {
        store.Close();
    }

    var clientAssertionCertificate = new ClientAssertionCertificate(applicationId, certificate);
    var result = await authenticationContext.AcquireTokenAsync(resource, clientAssertionCertificate);
    return result.AccessToken;
});

    var secretIdentifier = "https://rahulkeyvault.vault.azure.net/secrets/mySecretName";
    var secret = await keyClient.GetSecretAsync(secretIdentifier);

    log.Info($"Secret Value: {secret}"); 
}
</code></pre>

<p>Make sure you add in the <em>project.json</em> as seen in the <a href="/blog/azure-key-vault-from-azure-functions/">previous post</a> to enable the required NuGet packages. The Azure function now uses the certificate to authenticate with Key Vault and retrieve the secret.</p>

<p>Hope this helps!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Azure Key Vault From Azure Functions]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-from-azure-functions/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-from-azure-functions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-functions/functions-overview">Azure Functions</a> is a solution for easily running small pieces of code, or &ldquo;functions,&rdquo; in the cloud. You can write just the code you need for the problem at hand, without worrying about a whole application or the infrastructure to run it. Functions can make development even more productive, and you can use your development language of choice, such as C#, F#, Node.js, Python or PHP. Pay only for the time your code runs and trust Azure to scale as needed. Azure Functions lets you develop serverless applications on Microsoft Azure.</em></p>

<p>Even when developing with Azure Functions you want to keep your sensitive data protected. Like for example if the function needs to connect to a database you might want to get the connection string from <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-azure-key-vault/">Azure Key Vault</a>. If you are new to Azure Key Vault check out <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/azure-key-vault/">these posts to get started</a>. In this post, we will explore how we can consume objects in Azure Key Vault from an Azure Function.</p>

<p><strong>Create Azure Function App</strong>: Let&rsquo;s first create an Azure Function App from the Azure portal. Under <em>New - Compute - Function App</em> you can create a new Azure Function.</p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_new.png" alt="" class="center" /></p>

<p>Enter the details of the new function app and press Create. Each function app has an associated storage account. You can choose an existing one or create a new one.</p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_create.png" alt="" class="center" /></p>

<p>You can view all Azure Functions Apps in the subscription under <em>More services - Function Apps</em></p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_all.png" alt="" class="center" /></p>

<p><strong>Create Function</strong>: To create a function you can create from an existing template or create a custom function. In this example, I will use a timer based function in C#.</p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_createFunction.png" alt="" class="center" /></p>

<p>In the <em>run.csx</em> file add in the code for the function. The below code fetches the secret value from the Key Vault and logs it. You need to provide the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/authenticating-a-client-application-with-azure-key-vault/">Azure AD Application Id and secret</a> to authenticate with it. Alternatively you can also use <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-key-vault-from-azure-functions-certificate-based-authentication/">certificate based authentication to authenticate with the Key Vault</a>. Make sure you add in the relevant <em>using</em> statements for the KeyVault client Azure Active Directory Authentication libraries (ADAL).</p>

<pre><code class="csharp">using System;
using Microsoft.Azure.KeyVault;
using Microsoft.IdentityModel.Clients.ActiveDirectory;

private const string applicationId = "AD Application Id";
private const string applicationSecret = "AD Application Secret";

public async static Task Run(TimerInfo myTimer, TraceWriter log)
{
    var keyClient = new KeyVaultClient(async (authority, resource, scope) =&gt;
    {
        var adCredential = new ClientCredential(applicationId, applicationSecret);
        var authenticationContext = new AuthenticationContext(authority, null);
        return (await authenticationContext.AcquireTokenAsync(resource, adCredential)).AccessToken;
    });

    var secretIdentifier = "https://rahulkeyvault.vault.azure.net/secrets/mySecretName";
    var secret = await keyClient.GetSecretAsync(secretIdentifier);

    log.Info($"C# Timer trigger function executed at: {secret}"); 
}
</code></pre>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_code.png" alt="" class="center" /></p>

<p>Since the KeyVaultClient and the ADAL libraries are NuGet packages, we need to specify these as dependencies for the Azure Function. To use NuGet packages, create a <em>project.json</em> file in the functions folder. Add in both the NuGet packages name and required version.</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
  "frameworks": {
    "net46":{
      "dependencies": {
        "Microsoft.Azure.KeyVault": "1.0.0",
        "Microsoft.IdentityModel.Clients.ActiveDirectory": "2.14.201151115"
      }
    }
   }
}
</code></pre>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_nuget.png" alt="" class="center" /></p>

<p>Executing the function, retrieves the secret details from the Key Vault and logs it as shown below.</p>

<p><img src="/images/azureFunction_run.png" alt="" class="center" /></p>

<p>Hope this helps you to get started with Key Vault in Azure Functions and keep your sensitive data secure.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Could Not Load Assembly msshrtmi.dll?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/could-not-load-assembly-msshrtmi-dll/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-19T17:38:37+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/could-not-load-assembly-msshrtmi-dll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While migrating a few Azure Cloud Services to Web Jobs, we started facing the error, <span style='color: red;'><em>Could not load assembly &hellip; /msshrtmi.dll</em></span>,for just one of the projects. The error provides the exact path from where it is trying to load the DLL and is the same path from which the process is running. But the location does have the <em>msshrtmi.dll</em>, which for some reason the process is not able to load.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/msshrtmi_load_error.png" alt="msshrtmi dll load error" /></p>

<div class="alert alert-info" role="alert">
<strong>TL;DR</strong> This error occurred due to an attribute - <i>&lt;Prefer32Bit&gt;false&lt;/Prefer32Bit&gt;</i> - in the csproj file, while the referred msshrtmi dll was 32-bit version. This might not be applicable to you, but since it has happened once it&#8217;s very likely to happen again.
</div>


<p>To our surprise, this was happening only with a specific worker, while all others (around 8) were working fine. All of the workers are generated by the same build process on a server. For some reason (I am still investigating into this) the msshrtmi.dll is added as an external reference in the project and referred from there in all the project files. This was done mainly because we had a few external dependencies that were dependent on specific Azure SDK version (2.2). But this explicit reference should not have caused any issues as all, as the other processes were working fine and only a specific one was failing.</p>

<p>One useful tool to help diagnose why the .NET framework cannot locate assemblies is <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/e74a18c4(v=vs.110).aspx">Assembly Binding Log Viewer(Fuslogvw.exe)</a>. The viewer displays an entry for each failed assembly bind. For each failure, the viewer describes the application that initiated the bind; the assembly the bind is for, including name, version, culture and public key; and the date and time of the failure.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Fuslogvw.exe is automatically installed with Visual Studio. To run the tool, use the Developer Command Prompt with administrator credentials.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Running <em>fuslogvw</em> with the application shows the assembly binding error, double clicking which gives a details error information, as shown below. This error message gives more details and tells us that the assembly platform or ContentType is invalid.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/msshrtmi_fuslogvw.png" alt="LOG: Assembly Name is: msshrtmi, Version=2.2.0.0, Culture=neutral, PublicKeyToken=31bf3856ad364e35
ERR: Invalid assembly platform or ContentType in file (hr = 0x8007000b).
ERR: Run-from-source setup phase failed with hr = 0x8007000b.
ERR: Failed to complete setup of assembly (hr = 0x8007000b). Probing terminated." /></p>

<p>In the Task Manager, the worker with the assembly loading error (last <em>worker</em> in the image below) shows as a 64-bit process, while the others as 32-bit. Since the referred msshrtmi DLL is 32-bit, it explains why it was unable to find the correct platform matching msshrtmi assembly.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/msshrtmi_task_manager.png" alt="msshrtmi task manager" /></p>

<p><a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms164699(v=vs.110).aspx">CorFlags.exe</a> is used to determine whether an .exe file or .dll file is meant to run only on a specific platform or under WOW64. Running the <em>corflags</em> on all the workers produces the below two results:</p>

<p><mark>corflags Problematic_Worker.exe</mark> <br/>
Version   : v4.0.30319 <br/>
CLR Header: 2.5 <br/>
PE        : PE32 <br/>
CorFlags  : 0x1  <br/>
ILONLY    : 1 <br/>
32BITREQ  : 0 <br/>
<mark>32BITPREF : 0</mark><br/>
Signed    : 0</p>

<p><mark>corflags Worker.exe</mark>    <br/>
Version   : v4.0.30319 <br/>
CLR Header: 2.5 <br/>
PE        : PE32 <br/>
CorFlags  : 0x20003 <br/>
ILONLY    : 1 <br/>
32BITREQ  : 0 <br/>
<mark> 32BITPREF : 1</mark>  <br/>
Signed    : 0</p>

<p>The <em>32BITPREF</em> flag is &lsquo;0&rsquo; for the worker that shows the error, whereas for the rest shows 1. The <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms164699(v=vs.110).aspx"><em>32BITPREF</em></a> flag indicates that the application runs as a 32 bit process even on 64-bit platforms. This explains why the problematic worker was running as 64-bit process since the flag is turned off.</p>

<blockquote><p><em><a href="http://blogs.microsoft.co.il/sasha/2012/04/04/what-anycpu-really-means-as-of-net-45-and-visual-studio-11/">From .NET 4.5 and Visual Studio 11</a>, the default for most .NET projects is again AnyCPU, but there is more than one meaning to AnyCPU now. There is an additional sub-type of AnyCPU, “Any CPU 32-bit preferred”, which is the new default (overall, there are now five options for the /platform C# compiler switch: x86, Itanium, x64, anycpu, and anycpu32bitpreferred). When using that flavor of AnyCPU, the semantics are the following:</em></p>

<ul>
<li><em>If the process runs on a 32-bit Windows system, it runs as a 32-bit process. IL is compiled to x86 machine code.</em></li>
<li><em>If the process runs on a 64-bit Windows system, it runs as a 32-bit process. IL is compiled to x86 machine code.</em></li>
<li><em>If the process runs on an ARM Windows system, it runs as a 32-bit process. IL is compiled to ARM machine code.</em></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>All the projects are getting built using the same build scripts, and we are not explicitly turning off/on this compiler option. So the next possible place where any setting for this flag is specified is the <em>csproj</em> file. On the properties of the worker project file (the one that shows error), I see that &lsquo;<em>Prefer 32-bit</em>&rsquo; option is not checked and the csproj file has it explicitly set to false (as shown below). For other projects, this option is checked in Visual Studio and has no entry in the csproj file, which means the flag defaults to true.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/msshrtmi_prefer32bit.png" alt="msshrtmi prefer 32bit csproj" /></p>

<p><strong><em>Deleting the Prefer32Bit attribute from the csproj and building fixed the assembly loading issue of msshrtmi!</em></strong></p>

<p>Though this ended up being a minor fix (in terms of code change), I learned a lot of different tools that can be used to debug assembly loading issues. It was using these right tools that helped me identify this extra attribute on the csproj file and help solve the issue. So the next time you see such an error , either with mssrhtmi or another DLL, hope this helps to find your way through!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Azure AD Application for Key Vault]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/managing-azure-ad-application-for-key-vault/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-27T19:13:48+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/managing-azure-ad-application-for-key-vault</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Please check <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-the-deprecation-of-switch-azuremode-affects-azure-key-vault/">here</a> for scripts using the latest PowerShell cmdlets.</p></blockquote>

<p>Access to the Key Vault is secured using AD application token, as we had seen in the &lsquo;<a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/authenticating-a-client-application-with-azure-key-vault/">Authenticating a Client Application with Azure Key Vault</a>&rsquo;. Quite often administrators require to manage the AD application created, performing activities like creating new AD applications, changing the certificate used to authenticate with the AD application, remove a certificate or even delete an application. All of these are possible using PowerShell scripts and administrators can even run this as part of their automation scripts. With the latest Azure PowerShell version(0.9.2 or higher), the Key Vault cmdlet&rsquo;s are included automatically and does not require any additional installations. For managing the Azure AD application we need to <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/azure/jj151815.aspx#bkmk_installmodule">install the Azure AD module for PowerShell</a> and import them into the PowerShell command prompt.</p>

<h4><strong>Creating AD application</strong></h4>

<p>The <em><a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn986794.aspx">New-AzureADApplication</a></em> cmdlet is used to create a new Azure AD application. It also provides an option to specify the certificate details used to authenticate with the AD application at the time of creation itself. This can be done as a separate step if required, which is shown later in the post.</p>

<p>First we need a certificate that is to be used for authenticating against the AD application, for which I use the below commands to generate a test certificate</p>

<pre><code class="text">makecert -sv mykey.pvk -n "cn=AD Test Vault Application" ADTestVaultApplication.cer -b 03/03/2014 -e 06/05/2017 -r -len 2048
pvk2pfx -pvk mykey.pvk -spc ADTestVaultApplication.cer -pfx ADTestVaultApplication.pfx -po test
</code></pre>

<p>This certificate is then used to create the AD application using the below script.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">$certificateFilePath = "C:\certificates\ADTestVaultApplication.cer"
$certificate = New-Object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Certificate2
$certificate.Import($certificateFilePath)
$rawCertificateData = $certificate.GetRawCertData()
$credential = [System.Convert]::ToBase64String($rawCertificateData)
$startDate= [System.DateTime]::Now
$endDate = $startDate.AddYears(1)
$adApplication = New-AzureADApplication -DisplayName "KeyVaultADApplication" 
  -HomePage  "http://www.rahulpnath.com" -IdentifierUris "http://www.rahulpnath.com"  
  -KeyValue  $credential -KeyType "AsymmetricX509Cert" -KeyUsage "Verify" 
  -StartDate $startDate -EndDate $endDate 
</code></pre>

<p>To associate the application created with the Key Vault, we need to create a service principal using <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn986799.aspx">New-AzureADServicePrincipal</a> and then associate that with the Vault using the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/azure/dn903607.aspx">Set-AzureKeyVaultAccessPolicy</a></p>

<pre><code class="powershell">$servicePrincipal = New-AzureADServicePrincipal -ApplicationId $adApplication.ApplicationId
Set-AzureKeyVaultAccessPolicy -VaultName 'KeyVaultRahul' -ObjectId  $servicePrincipal.Id -PermissionsToKeys all -PermissionsToSecrets all
$ServicePrincipal.ApplicationId #Outputs the ServicePrincipalName/AppPrincipalId
</code></pre>

<h4><strong>Adding a Certificate</strong></h4>

<p>The <em><a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/azure/dn194106.aspx">New-MsolServicePrincipalCredential</a></em> cmdlet is used to add a new credential to a service principal or to an application. The service principal is identified by supplying one of the following: object ID, appPrincipalID, service principal name (SPN).</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">$msolCredentials = get-credential
connect-msolservice -credential $msolCredentials
$certificateFilePath = "C:\certificates\ADTestVaultApplicationNew.cer"
$x509Certificate2 = New-Object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Certificate2
$x509Certificate2.Import($certificateFilePath)
$rawCertData = $x509Certificate2.GetRawCertData()
$credentialValue = [System.Convert]::ToBase64String($rawCertData)
$startDate= [System.DateTime]::Now
$endDate = $startDate.AddYears(1)
New-MsolServicePrincipalCredential -ServicePrincipalName $ServicePrincipal.ApplicationId -Type Asymmetric -Value $credentialValue -StartDate $startDate -EndDate   $endDate 
</code></pre>

<h4><strong>Removing a Certificate</strong></h4>

<p>Whenever a credential gets compromised or as part of regular credential refresh, administrators would want to remove an old certificate and replace with a new one. The <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/azure/dn194125.aspx">Remove-MsolServicePrincipalCredential</a> cmdlet is used to remove a credential key from a service principal by specifying the key ID for the credential and the objectID/applicationID/ServicePrincipalName to identify the service principal. To get the key ID of an existing credential, <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/azure/dn194091.aspx">Get-MsolServicePrincipalCredential</a> cmdlet can be used, which returns the list of credentials associated with a service principal. The below script just removes the first credential, you could loop through and remove all.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">$servicePrincipalCredential = Get-MsolServicePrincipalCredential -ServicePrincipalName $ServicePrincipal.ApplicationId -ReturnKeyValues 0
Remove-MsolServicePrincipalCredential -ServicePrincipalName $ServicePrincipal.ApplicationId -KeyIds $servicePrincipalCredential[0].KeyId
</code></pre>

<h4><strong>Delete an application</strong></h4>

<p>The <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/azure/dn194113.aspx">Remove-MsolServicePrincipal</a> cmdlet removes a service principal from Microsoft Azure Active Directory, by specifying objectID/applicationID/ServicePrincipalName to identify the service principal.</p>

<pre><code class="powershell">Remove-MsolServicePrincipal -ObjectId &lt;Guid&gt;
Or
Remove-MsolServicePrincipal -AppPrincipalId &lt;Guid&gt;
Or
Remove-MsolServicePrincipal -ServicePrincipalName &lt;string&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Managing the AD application is a very important and necessary process in the life cycle of a Key Vault, as the access to the Vault is controlled using that. Certificates securing the AD applciation should be rolled/updated frequently and application permissions should be reviewed often to make sure that all applications have only the required permissions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
