<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-23T06:06:56+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Life Learnings After Being a Parent]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/life-learnings-after-being-a-parent/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-14T16:48:25+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/life-learnings-after-being-a-parent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><em>His father asked Ethan in a raspy voice, &ldquo;You spend time with your son?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Much as I can,&rdquo; he’d answered, but his father had caught the lie in his eyes.</em></p>

<p><em>&ldquo;It’ll be your loss, Ethan. Day&rsquo;ll come, when he’s grown and it’s too late, that you&rsquo;d give a kingdom to go back and spend a single hour with your son as a boy. To hold him.Read a book to him. Throw a ball with a person in whose eyes you can do no wrong. He doesn&rsquo;t see your failings yet. He looks at you with pure love and it won&rsquo;t last, so you revel in it while it&rsquo;s here.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><em>Ethan thinks often of that conversation, mostly when he&rsquo;s lying awake in bed at night and everyone else is asleep, and his life screaming past at the speed of light—the weight of bills and the future and his prior failings and all these moments he&rsquo;s missing—all the lost joy—perched like a boulder on his chest.</em></p>

<p>- <strong> <em><a href="http://amzn.to/1YdxuYm">Pines (The Wayward Pines Trilogy, Book 1)</a></em> </strong></p></blockquote>

<p>Every second that I spent with Gautham is a pure joy and I enjoy it to the most. It&rsquo;s true that I have very less time to spend for myself, but then it also made me realized I have not been using all the time I did have before he was born. I have re-arranged all my schedules so that whenever I am home and he is awake, I do nothing else, but be with him! There has been a lot of learnings and realizations that I have had since the last 20 months.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Command Line Application Launcher" src="/images/gautham.jpg" /></p>

<h4><strong>Curiosity is what keeps us going</strong></h4>

<p>Each day is a new day and he learns at least one new thing. Though to us (the &lsquo;grown-ups&rsquo;), it feels that he is doing the same thing over and over again, for him, it&rsquo;s the same thing in a new perspective. He is curious about everything that he sees and happens around. I often felt that my job was boring, mundane and repetitive and often ended up being the same thing every day. But then I understood that it is not about what you do but how you see what you are doing, that matters. Having at least one new thing to learn from whatever you do daily is a good way to stay motivated.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Always try to understand one level below your current level of abstraction - happiness lies there!</em></p></blockquote>

<h4><strong>Making the Complex Simple</strong></h4>

<p>Often when playing with him I realize how overwhelming things are in the world and all that he is yet to learn. But that&rsquo;s just me putting my perspective through his eyes. For him, it&rsquo;s always &lsquo;try try and try again&rsquo;. He tries the best he can do something now and improve on it over the days or months.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>How do you eat an elephant? One bite at a time.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I often get overwhelmed when dealing with something new - learning a new language, buying a car or even planning a vacation. There are innumerable options for everything these days and all that information is available at our fingertips. But then the way to approach these is to break it down into smaller chunks of work and target that individually. Just like writing this blog post is overwhelming for me for all the things that I think I need to write, but then I write section by section or even line by line. Forming <a href="http://amzn.to/1toWtyy">habits</a> to break anything <a href="http://amzn.to/1Xg6biH">complex into smaller pieces</a> and tackling that is a good way to approach tasks.</p>

<h4><strong>Learning to Disconnect</strong></h4>

<p>I certainly do not want Gautham to be entertained with a smartphone, iPad or laptop while I get to do something else. Though it is very much plausible, that&rsquo;s just setting him up the wrong path. It&rsquo;s easy for us to get distracted into all these and not do what matters to us the most - just like all of us hooked into the social media.</p>

<blockquote><p><em><a href="https://medium.com/life-learning/how-to-live-a-life-of-balance-and-high-productivity-bd5434a61c79#.26mh9yvec">Social media is best as planned entertainment rather than unplanned distraction.</a></em></p></blockquote>

<p>The more you stay offline from these &lsquo;addictive&rsquo; social networks the less you will feel the need to check it. Like I do not want my kid to be addicted to these, I do not want it to get in the way of me using that time for something more useful. Staying disconnected from the internet and social network is a good way to get a lot of time for yourself.</p>

<h4><strong>Less is More</strong></h4>

<p>Gautham is happy just with a bottle cap, or a small thread of a shirt and can spend a lot of time playing with it. It&rsquo;s not in what you have but how you see things that you have matters. I was always attracted to the latest and coolest gadgets and often bought them too. Happiness then was directly related to the things I had in possession and how current I was. I have learned to get over that minimize my expense to what matters most. Though it&rsquo;s a bit late , the saying &lsquo;<em>Do not save what is left after spending but spend what is left after saving</em>&rsquo;, starts making a lot of sense. The fact that there is someone who is completely dependent on me(/wife) brings in a lot of responsibility to life which was missing earlier and puts savings in front of expenses.</p>

<h4><strong>Time is Valuable</strong></h4>

<p>One of the most precious things that I have is time. I used to while away time earlier but now I have very limited of it for myself that I try to spend it usefully. Having your <a href="http://zenhabits.net/purpose-your-day-most-important-task/">Most Important Task</a> (MIT) defined is important and helps prioritize your tasks for the day. If you feel a lot of time is getting lost, while sitting down to work (on a laptop for me) use monitoring tools like <a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/">Rescue Time</a> to understand your daily habits and improve on it.</p>

<blockquote><p><em><a href="http://quoteinvestigator.com/2013/10/30/inspire-nine/">Someone once asked</a> Somerset Maugham if he wrote on a schedule or only when struck by inspiration. “I write only when inspiration strikes,” he replied. “Fortunately, it strikes every morning at nine o’clock sharp.”</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Habits decide what we do every day so it&rsquo;s very important that we form good ones. Though it takes effort, it is possible to <a href="http://charlesduhigg.com/how-habits-work/">rewire any of your habits</a> just by giving attention to it.</p>

<h4><strong>Learning from Mistakes</strong></h4>

<p>When you try, you fail and you fail again and again until you succeed. When you don&rsquo;t try you fail - you fail to succeed! <a href="http://www.psychologyinaction.org/2012/11/22/infants-learn-to-walk-by-learning-to-fall/">Infants learn to walk by learning to fall</a>. It&rsquo;s easy to get into a comfort zone and stay there be it in your jobs or elsewhere. Intentionally putting yourself into a position to learn and grow is important. I spent a large part of my time at the workplace. So I try to own up a lot more unfamiliar things and get exposed more - It&rsquo;s Ok to fail!</p>

<p>Parenting is hard but it&rsquo;s also real fun. You get to learn a lot yourself while on the journey and <strong><em>they give back the initial years of your life</em></strong>. Let me wrap this up quickly as he is about to wake up and the last thing I want is to have all the keys pulled off my keyboard!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Make it Easy for the New Person Joining the Team - Have a Project Ramp up Plan]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/make-it-easy-for-the-new-person-joining-your-team-have-a-project-ramp-up-plan/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-18T12:38:24+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/make-it-easy-for-the-new-person-joining-your-team-have-a-project-ramp-up-plan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was in a discussion with my friend/colleague on conducting a few ramp up sessions for the new hires in our team. The discussion went as below,</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Me: We should hold a few sessions to make the new guys in team more comfortable</em></p>

<p><em>Friend: It&rsquo;s too early for it. We should let them find their own way and not &lsquo;spoon-feed&rsquo; them with information.</em></p>

<p><em>Me: But we are not &lsquo;spoon-feeding&rsquo; them, we are just making their learning process faster and giving then an overview on how all the technology fits together in our world of things.</em></p>

<p><em>Friend: But &lsquo;I did not have any ramp up when I joined, and I felt it was better to have learned it on my own, though it took a lot more time.</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.mindtickle.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/new_employee_orientation_business_strategy_research.png" class="center" title="Image, from http://www.mindtickle.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/new_employee_orientation_business_strategy_research.png"><img src="/images\rampup_plan.png" class="center" alt="Rampup Plan"></a></p>

<p>Just like there are company-wide induction/onboarding sessions, I have always felt that project specific onboarding plans are also required and help new hires be part of the team and be more productive with their day-to-day activities faster. As mentioned in this <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3029820/work-smart/infographic-the-real-ways-to-hold-on-to-new-hires/3">article</a>, <em>New hires care more about effective job training and clear guidelines, and it&rsquo;s time you provide that for them.</em> It&rsquo;s best to have a plan in place when you have someone new joining your team and you along with the team are the best people to put that plan together.</p>

<h3>Boy Scout Rule</h3>

<p>The Boy Scouts have a <a href="http://programmer.97things.oreilly.com/wiki/index.php/The_Boy_Scout_Rule">rule</a> - <em>&ldquo;Always leave the campground cleaner than you found it.&rdquo;</em>  New hires are like &lsquo;new camp group&rsquo; at a campground, so it&rsquo;s the duty of the &lsquo;existing team&rsquo; there to make it a good experience for them.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>&lsquo;Refactor&rsquo; your experiences to make it better for the next person who is about to take on the same journey</em></p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s not that my friend was intentionally trying not to pass on any information, but he felt that learning on their own would be better. Even I agree with him that learning on your own is far better than &lsquo;spoon-feeding&rsquo; - but a ramp up plan is not spoon-feeding. A ramp up plan is only to speed up the learning process and to make it more comfortable for someone joining new.</p>

<h3>When to create the plan?</h3>

<p>The need for such a plan is there only when there has been enough progress made on the project, after which there is someone new joining the team. So when a new hire is scheduled to join is a good time to create the &lsquo;draft&rsquo; plan. Once the new hire has gone through it and updated back with his own experiences it could become the first version of the plan, which can then be confidently shared to anyone joining after as it has worked for at least one person.</p>

<h3>What should be there in the plan</h3>

<p><em>It depends!</em></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s totally up to the team to decide what should be there in the plan. Some of the things that I usually have are</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Overview of the project and what problem it is trying to solve</strong></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s really important that everyone on the team knows what the application is trying to solve and have a common goal to work towards. It&rsquo;s not just about the code we write but about the problem we are solving and that needs to be clearly defined. I would record a video, when this is done the first time and share it with anyone joining after that, as most of the core concepts of a project rarely change. There could be a follow-up session post watching the video, to also have a quick walk through and fill any missing gaps.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Introduction to various technologies used in the project and how everything fits together</strong></p>

<p>Technology changes so fast these days that it is nearly impossible to stay updated with all the available options. So a walk through of the different technologies and pointers to resources that worked for you and the team will be of help. If there are any specific libraries, frameworks getting used, an introduction to those should also help.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Release cycle and Release management</strong>
Every project has its own model of delivering the end product and everyone on the team should understand this process well. Having a continuous build is becoming more common these days and helps reduce the complexity of release. An end to end walk-through of the deployment process helps understand the application better and provides exposure to all the moving parts in the system.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Environment/Machine setup</strong>
Software installation is one of the biggest pain when setting up a new machine for a project, especially with having specific versions of the software. Having a documented list of all the project dependencies (hardware and software) makes setting the project environment easy. It&rsquo;s preferable to have these <a href="https://chocolatey.org/">scripted</a>. Have a common place, where you can find links to all the various environments (dev, at,prod etc) and related resources.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Patterns and Conventions</strong>
Every project has its own conventions and certain core patterns that are followed. It&rsquo;s good to have these patterns available for reference so that it helps understand the code better and helps reduce code-review cycles. Than having one big boring document, what I prefer more is to have multiple blog articles targeting each of those. I try to generalize commonly used patterns in the projects that I have worked on and create blog posts. This also helps generate content for <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/">your blog</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tips &amp; Tricks</strong>
This could range from how to easily navigate the code base, scripts to do some commonly occurring task and general things to keep an eye for.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>These are just some of the things I generally try to include in a ramp up plan but as said it totally depends on the team and the project.</p>

<h3>Sharing the plan</h3>

<p>Depending on the plan, if it has confidential information, you could split this into two (or more) different documents and share it at different phases of onboarding. Once a new hire is confirmed it&rsquo;s good to share the parts which do not have any confidential information. Technology stack, conventions used, machine setup (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bring_your_own_device">BYOD</a>) are usually not confidential and can be shared well before actual employment. Once all employment agreements are in place the rest too can be shared. It&rsquo;s also a good idea to have some walk-through of the plan itself to make it easier to follow.</p>

<h3>Iterate and Improve</h3>

<p>Updating back with the experiences of the people using the plan is important to keep it current and valuable. Suggesting improvements and updates should be an item in the plan so that this does not get missed. To make updates manageable, the plan must be accessible to all and preferably version controlled if they are documents.</p>

<p>What are your thoughts on having a ramp up plan?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Checking in Package Dependencies into Source Control]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/checking-in-package-dependencies-into-source-control/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-26T12:21:21+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/checking-in-package-dependencies-into-source-control</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post looks into why we should include packages in the source control and not resolve it via configuration files at build time.</em></p>

<p>Over the past few years, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Package_manager">Package Managers</a> have gained an important role in the way software gets developed. There is an <a href="https://github.com/showcases/package-managers">increasing number of package managers</a> catering to different programming languages and areas of development, making the distribution of reusable libraries and plugins easy. The convention that&rsquo;s usually followed with these package dependencies is to exclude them from source control, and use a configuration file (<a href="https://docs.npmjs.com/files/package.json">package.json</a>, <a href="https://docs.nuget.org/consume/package-restore">packages.config</a>) to retrieve all the packages at build time. Even the <a href="https://github.com/github/gitignore">GitHub’s collection</a> of <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/gitignore">.gitignore</a> file templates ignores the packages folders of various package managers.</p>

<pre><code class="text"># NuGet Packages
*.nupkg
# The packages folder can be ignored because of Package Restore
**/packages/*
...
# Dependency directories
node_modules
jspm_packages
</code></pre>

<h3>Common Arguments for not Checking in Packages</h3>

<p>Since checking in packages is not a common practice, let&rsquo;s first see some of the arguments for not doing this and how it compares to having them checked in.</p>

<h4><strong>Storage</strong></h4>

<p><em>Packages are something that can be resolved at runtime and keeping them excluded saves that extra space on the source control system.</em></p>

<p>Yes, this might have been a good reason few years back, but these days this is not a good reason as storage has become really cheap. Moreover popular source control systems charge by the <a href="https://github.com/pricing/plans">number of repositories</a> and not by the space it occupies (although it has <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/what-is-my-disk-quota/">limits</a> on it).</p>

<h4><strong>Time</strong></h4>

<p><em>The clone is faster when you do not have packages in the source control repository as opposed to having them.</em></p>

<p>But for the project to build we need the packages restored first. So the time is either spent in the clone or in the restore. But if the packages are included in the git clone then you can immediately start working on the project after a clone and do not need any internet connectivity to make the project build. This is also of advantage if you want to run a &lsquo;<a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-clean">git clean</a>&rsquo; - which cleans the working tree by recursively removing files that are not under version control. With packages not under the source control, you have to restore them every time you run it - This is not a problem if you have internet connectivity, but will block your work if you do it when you don&rsquo;t.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Without checking in dependent packages, you can&rsquo;t git clone and get on a flight nor can you git clean while on a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airplane_mode">flight</a></em></p></blockquote>

<p>Moreover cloning a repository is a one-time activity, while a clean can be done any time a developer wants to. So it actually saves more time to keep the packages checked in.</p>

<h3>More Reason for Checking in Packages</h3>

<p>Now that we have seen most of the common arguments are not valid, let&rsquo;s see more reasons on why including the packages into the source control is actually better.</p>

<h4><strong>Explicit Dependencies</strong></h4>

<p>It&rsquo;s always better to be explicit about your code dependencies and not have them resolved by a package manager.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Packages are nothing but code and can alter the behaviour of the application.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>There are possibilities of specific package versions getting <a href="http://blog.npmjs.org/post/141577284765/kik-left-pad-and-npm">removed from the package manager</a>, which your application is still dependent on and leads to build breakage! If your package configuration is set up in such a way to resolve the latest available package of  the specific dependency, there are possibilities that the package owner pushes an update that is not backward compatible, causing the build to break! Given that these possibilities exist there is no reason to exclude package dependencies from checked in.</p>

<h4><strong>Package Source Downtime</strong></h4>

<p>Though the publicly available package sources like NuGet, npm are available almost all the time, it is likely that they too <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/17806889/nuget-feed-reliability">can go down</a>. The last thing you would want is to get blocked by the downtime of these services - be it failure to build locally or on a server or even block a critical deployment. With the packages available in your source control, you have one less moving part in your whole deployment pipeline and it is better to have lesser dependencies.</p>

<h4><strong>Custom Package Sources</strong></h4>

<p>Many times I have had to update my Package sources in Visual Studio and break my head on the specific order of these entries to get the project building. This is very common when using custom packages sources like <a href="http://inedo.com/proget">ProGet</a> or <a href="https://myget.org/">MyGet</a>. Such dependencies make project setup harder and is easily avoided if all the dependent assemblies are available within the repository.  You can still have them as custom NuGet sources but have the dependencies included into the repository and update the references whenever source changes. This makes project ramp up easier and faster, with one less configuration step.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Nuget custom package source" src="/images/nuget_package_sources.png" /></p>

<p>Do you still see any reason for not checking in package dependencies into the source control? If not let&rsquo;s go and change that package folder exclude and have them included in the source. (I just updated <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/clal-command-line-application-launcher/">CLAL</a> to <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/clal/commit/736023d9ab4bd285cb077ff54acd1bbaad142a08">include dependencies.</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developer Learnings from the IKEA Experience]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/developer-learnings-from-the-ikea-experience/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-16T05:44:03+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/developer-learnings-from-the-ikea-experience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When we moved over to Sydney, last year, we had to start over with all the home furnishings. Since we were just starting out, didn&rsquo;t want to spent a lot on furnishings, so decided to go with <a href="http://www.ikea.com/au/en/?cid=au|ps|branded|brand|google|ikea_australia">IKEA</a> for its cost effectiveness and value for money.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>IKEA is a multinational group of companies that designs and sells ready-to-assemble furniture (such as beds, chairs and desks), appliances, small motor vehicles and home accessories. <span class="right">Wiki</span></em></p></blockquote>

<p>Right from the in-shop experience to setting it up, I found many similarities with the IKEA experience and Software Development. Visiting IKEA is an experience in itself and totally wow&rsquo;s you. If not for any of the displayed items, the &lsquo;<em>Self Serve Furniture Area</em>&rsquo; surely will. The sheer size and setup there was breath-taking for me and my wife!</p>

<p><figure>
    <img alt="IKEA Self Serve Furniture Area, Ikea Tempe" src="/images/ikea_self_serve_furniture_area.jpg" />
    <figcaption><em>This is just one of the aisle and there were around 35 of them!</em></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<h3>Code Management &amp; Inventory Management</h3>

<p>Throughout the <a href="https://shoutsfromtheabyss.files.wordpress.com/2013/06/ikea-map.jpg">Showroom</a> you see an <em>Aisle number</em> and the <em>Location</em> displayed under the displayed items. For the items interested in, one can note those numbers on paper or use the mobile application to <a href="http://www.ikea.com/ms/en_KR/customer-service/apps/mobile_app_14.html">scan the QR code of the product</a> for reference. In the checkout area, you can find the item at the said aisle/location number. Finding and picking up the item from the aisle is easy and joyful.</p>

<p>Code management is an important aspect in Software development, as code bases can get quite large. Setting up a <a href="https://github.com/">version control</a> to manage code bases have become a norm and is a good practice to follow even on your side projects. Few other things to follow include</p>

<ul>
<li>Maintain a project structure, naming conventions and code conventions.</li>
<li>Code Navigability and discoverability are important for fast and smooth development. Good and descriptive class names allow us to navigate easily based on the application functionality.</li>
<li><a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/893ke618(v=vs.71).aspx">Organizing Namespace</a></li>
<li>Remove unused code and not comment it out. Let the version control system take care of file history.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Manual</h3>

<p>The assembly instructions that comes with each package is clear and expressive. It&rsquo;s mostly <a href="http://www.ikea.com/au/en/assembly_instructions/malm-desk__AA-516949-7_pub.pdf">conveyed through pictures</a> and easy to follow through. The manual is up to date with the packaged product and matched exactly with the contents.</p>

<p>This shows the importance of having a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/README">README</a> file or software manuals or in context help for users to use the application. Feedback messages and keeping the user always connected with the system is also important. Long wait times, unresponsive progress bars, silent suppression of error messages are not acceptable. Error messages are for the application user and the level and kind of details differs based on who the user is:</p>

<ul>
<li>For business/non-technical users, mostly of Front-end applications, Business error messages makes more value than technical errors</li>
<li>For developers consuming an API, detailed technical error messages add value than just returning a &lsquo;500 - Internal Server Error&rsquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>Error messages must be relevant and up to date with the current functionality. Always review messages for appropriateness.</p>

<p>Code comments used for communicating intent mostly gets out of sync with what the code actually does. So it&rsquo;s a better practice to avoid comments in code and break code into descriptive function and classes to convey the intent.</p>

<blockquote><p><em><a href="http://butunclebob.com/ArticleS.TimOttinger.ApologizeIncode">A comment is an apology</a> for not choosing a more clear name or a more reasonable set of parameters, or for the failure to use explanatory variables and explanatory functions.</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>Tools</h3>

<p><img class="left" alt="IKEA Tools" src="/images/ikea_tools.jpg" /></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.ikea.com/us/en/catalog/products/00169254/">FIXA 17-piece tool kit</a>, is all that you need for fitting all the furniture. Some products have an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hex_key">Allen Key</a> packaged along with them, but otherwise, most of the time the FIXA toolkit is all that one needs.</p>

<p>Having the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/">right set of tools</a> for assisting in the development and being familiar with it is important.  It&rsquo;s not just about having the best/costliest tools, but about knowing them well. Taking some time out to understand the tools that you use daily is important. By tools, I include keyboard, mouse, programming languages, IDE&rsquo;s and other support software that you use daily.</p>

<div style="clear: both;"></div>


<blockquote><p><em><a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/we-are-typists-first-programmers-second/">We are Typists First, Programmers Second</a>: The keyboard is one of the most important tools for a developer - learn it well</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>Componentization</h3>

<p>The furniture comes as separate pieces that can be easily assembled, with all the screw holes of perfect size. All the different pieces fit perfectly and right even when done by an amateur. Though some of the pieces required two people to fix, I could fix them up myself. It was all cut to perfection with all the holes right in place and fits perfectly the first time.</p>

<p>Having well-defined interfaces that interact with each other seamlessly is important in software development. Any application should be composed of smaller parts that can fit together well. Adhering to good design principles and design patterns helps us to achieve this.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>One of the most important principles while using Object Oriented  languages is <strong><a href="http://butunclebob.com/ArticleS.UncleBob.PrinciplesOfOod">SOLID</a></strong>:   <br/>
  Single Responsibility, Open-Closed, Liskov Substitution, Interface segregation and Dependency Injection</em></p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" alt="IKEA Components" src="/images/ikea_components.jpg" /></p>

<p>Interfaces should be well-defined and not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leaky_abstraction">leak abstractions</a>. The name and parameters(input/return) should completely abstract the &lsquo;how&rsquo; part of the functionality and expose only the &lsquo;what&rsquo;. This helps to build more robust interfaces.</p>

<h3>Packaging and Shipping</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.wsj.com/articles/ikea-cant-stop-obsessing-about-its-packaging-1434533401">IKEA&rsquo;s efficiency in packaging</a> is one of the reasons that enables them to sell at a low-cost and they keep improving at it. Compact and small packages make it easy to handle right from &lsquo;self-checkout&rsquo; to unpacking it at your home. It also helps in optimizing transportation costs for IKEA which in turn enables them to reduce prices.</p>

<p><figure>
    <img alt="IKEA Packaging" src="/images/ikea_packed.jpg"></img>
    <figcaption><em>King size bed frame with storage, extendable dining table and four chairs!</em></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Deployment in software development is a key part and having the entire pipeline automated is essential for a smooth delivery. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/automated-clickonce-deployment-of-a-wpf-application-using-appveyor/">Setting up a build server, automated building, running tests</a> etc are some of the starting points to move towards <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/ContinuousDelivery.html">Continuous Delivery</a>. Deployment needs to be scripted and be possible to deploy to any environment at the click of a button. If it is a distributable software then easily accessible delivery mechanisms should be available and preferably offer multiple options (like distributable media, server hosted images etc like Windows)</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The package has just the right number of screws, nails and other assembly accessories - not one less, not one more!</em></p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" alt="IKEA Components" src="/images/ikea_assembly_accessories.jpg" /></p>

<p>This shows IKEA&rsquo;s confidence in the shipped product and the self-belief of nothing going wrong. For a software product to be shipped with this level of confidence it should be thoroughly tested - preferably automated, which allows verifying each time we make a release and allows us to release more often.</p>

<h3>Cost Effective</h3>

<p>Having always bought pre-assembled furniture I have never had to think about anything - it was always just about the money. But with IKEA being self-assembled, you get the flexibility to choose the components/features that you need for the furniture like you could choose to have a <a href="http://www.ikea.com/au/en/catalog/products/20228714/">headboard for the bed</a> or not, which obviously implies a reduced price. You could choose to self-checkout and pay nothing, but also do a paid checkout, where an IKEA member would get all the items out for you to the billing counter. You could transport it yourself to your home or <a href="http://www.ikea.com/ms/en_AU/customer_service/ikea_services/home_delivery.html">get it delivered</a>. So it&rsquo;s all about giving you the options to choose what you want and really keep the cost low.</p>

<p>Keeping the cost low is an important aspect in software industry too and at various levels</p>

<ul>
<li>Development and Licensing  costs - Try to keep these costs low, by looking for open source alternatives and choosing your technology wisely and not just looking for the &lsquo;cool and latest&rsquo;.</li>
<li>Deployment/Infrastructure costs - Build applications for scale and as independent services so that they can be  turned on and off  as required. <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/">The cloud</a> has greatly reduced the infrastructure setup costs and provides an easy way for setup. Make sure you understand well the pricing models offered by various cloud providers.</li>
<li>Software Costs/Subscription Costs: Give flexibility to your consumers in how they can consume your software. Keeping functionality loosely coupled and pluggable allows to offer various subscription plans or selling model.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Value Added Services</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s not just in the home furnishings and their core business that IKEA has taken great care for. The other <a href="http://www.ikea.com/ms/en_SG/service-offer/">Value Added Services</a> they offer like Delivery, Assembly, Planning Tools, Gift Cards, Children&rsquo;s Services and Return Policy are top-notch.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Users are happy when the expected works, and wowed when it goes beyond expectations.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>The <a href="http://www.ikea.com/au/en/catalog/categories/departments/food/">food at IKEA</a> is worth mentioning (and a picture) - low-priced and tasty! It caters for the needs of all kinds of people and age. The value for money attracts people to IKEA just for the food.</p>

<p><img alt="IKEA Components" src="/images/ikea_food.jpg" /></p>

<p>Any product should deliver what it&rsquo;s supposed to anyways, but it&rsquo;s in providing a bit extra that really matters. Like the few examples below,that gave a better experience to me</p>

<ul>
<li>When you hit Ctrl + V with an image in clipboard on Facebook it automatically uploads the image</li>
<li>When Amazon sent a replacement for my broken Kindle (all the way from the US to India) for free</li>
<li>When Google Now showed the <a href="https://support.google.com/websearch/answer/6015842?hl=en">parking location</a>.</li>
<li>The IKEA Experience!</li>
</ul>


<p>Strive to look for cases where you can delight your customers every time you deliver a product. The IKEA has made me think about delivering products and the need for constantly improving at it. We often need to take a stop, look at what we are doing and correct things and move forward.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The only way to make the deadline—the only way to go fast—is to keep the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0132350882/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0132350882&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-20&amp;linkId=CVCVZFAR5SBYVMJW">code as clean</a> as possible at all times.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Head off to an IKEA store if there is one <a href="http://www.ikea.com/">near you</a> and get wowed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started With Freelancing Jobs Online]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-freelancing-jobs-online/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-01T11:57:03+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-freelancing-jobs-online</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Freelancing is a good way to learn new technology, get some hands on experience and not getting limited to the technology stack at your full-time job and of course earn some extra money!. There is a great demand for developers out there, so if its &lsquo;legal&rsquo; (check with your employer, if you already have another full-time job) for you to freelance then give it a try. There are a lot of online freelance platforms(<a href="https://www.upwork.com/">Upwork</a>, <a href="https://www.freelancer.com/">Freelancer</a>) that connects businesses and developers remotely. These platforms enable you as a developer, to start a profile and bid for jobs of your interest. If the business/client finds you as a match for the job, then you get signed up and can start working immediately.</p>

<p>Easy right! Yes absolutely it is, but here are a few things that might help you through the journey, that I have learned from my experiences.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Freelancer" src="/images/freelancing.jpg" /></p>

<h3><strong>Finding work</strong></h3>

<p>Finding work is just an easy search across on the platforms with your preferred skills. It will be a good idea to stick to one of the platforms so that you can build up a profile and then move on to other platforms. Landing your first job as a freelancer could be tricky as clients have a tendency to look for people with some work record on the platform, which assures them that it is a &lsquo;real human&rsquo; that they are talking to. But this is kind of &lsquo;chicken and egg problem&rsquo;. One of the best way to break into your first job is to sell yourself low - Yes, you heard it right - Really low!</p>

<p>While I started on with the idea of freelancing, I took on it with the perspective of that of an experienced developer(as I had a full-time job, which was paying me decently well). I bid on all projects with a relatively higher amount or at par to that my current job was paying, until I received back the below email from one of the clients.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>You lack test scores, have a small portfolio, and have no <a href="https://www.upwork.com">Odesk</a> history. You should try to underbid and get jobs when you are building up odesk history, get good feedback and then raise your rates later.I see you have good qualifications and don&rsquo;t mean you are not worth what you charge, this is just a way to get more clients in the beginning</em></p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s not always that you get a reply like this and it was an eye-opener for me. So to get the ball rolling, I tried bidding low on a couple of bug fix project which was about 1-2 hours work. Luckily I got one of the jobs and from then followed the exact feedback that I got back - Slowly increase rates and build profile.When bidding lower always make sure that you do on projects of smaller size, so that you don&rsquo;t feel really bad selling yourself low midway through the project (you could always renegotiate, but it might affect the feedback).</p>

<h3><strong>Bidding</strong></h3>

<p>Bidding is an important part of the freelancing cycle. Make sure you put in as much details to put across that you are an ideal candidate. It&rsquo;s where your skills to sell yourself come into play. Make sure you convey through the reasons on the &lsquo;Why&rsquo;,&lsquo;What&rsquo; and &lsquo;How&rsquo; in your bid cover letter.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Approach bidding the same way you would attend an interview with a prospective employer.</em></p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Why</strong> you are interested in the project</li>
<li><strong>What</strong> makes you a good candidate and your experiences. It will be good to have some references to existing projects/applications/blogs to back your claims.</li>
<li><strong>How</strong> you would approach the problem at hand and some questions probing more details.</li>
</ul>


<p>Many a times we have a tendency to copy paste bid cover letters and clients might look for specific references to their project. There are also clients who ask to start/end the bid with specific words or phrases just to make sure you have at least read through the job description.</p>

<h3><strong>Communication</strong></h3>

<p>Communication is the key when working remotely. Keeping your clients/stakeholders up to date on what&rsquo;s happening in the project, calling out any risks associated and clarifying on any issues should be done promptly. Your bid cover letter is the first impression that you leave on the client on your communications skills. So that makes it an added reason to give enough time while sending out your bid.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Missing a deadline is not really a problem, but not communicating it up front is.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good idea to set a rhythm to your updates and also sticking on to an update format, so that client knows how and when to expect for things. This will also allow them to plan for work. If working on hourly jobs, it would also be a good idea to set up repositories to share code or other artifacts that you are working on. <a href="https://github.com">Github</a> (paid for private repositories), <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-team-services-vs.aspx">Visual Studio Online</a> (VSO) or <a href="https://bitbucket.org">Bitbuket</a> (free with limits for private repositories) are good providers that you can use. Using <a href="https://trello.com">Trello</a> boards or <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-team-services-vs.aspx">VSO</a> for managing work/tasks will give enough visibility to clients on the current status at any point in time.</p>

<h3><strong>Hourly vs Fixed Price</strong></h3>

<p>When starting out it might be a good idea to start with an hourly project, so that you get introduced to various aspects of freelancing and get used to it. Once comfortable with the overall life cycle you can try fixed price projects. The challenge with fixed price projects, is in getting the scope fixed and making sure that you have accounted for all possible work. Also in tactfully raising cost variations when the client changes from agreed scope or when you discover work that you had not estimated for. Having cost change costs quite often does not put across a good message, so do that wisely and only when absolutely required. Even on hourly projects, there is nothing wrong in negotiating with the per-hour rate, especially if the project is a long running one.</p>

<p>Understand how the payment terms and conditions associated with the platform works. Some platforms have the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Escrow">escrow</a> model, so the risk of loosing out on money is less. For hourly projects, some platforms have tools that automatically track the amount of time you work on a project and directly bill the clients card once in a week/month, in which case you are sure to receive the payment (unless the client raises a conflict). For cases where none of the above applies, make sure that you have payment milestones set at different phases of the project and you share the code/working product only once you receive payments for milestones. Sharing videos, pictures, live remote sessions could be some alternatives to prove milestone criteria.</p>

<h3><strong>Branding</strong></h3>

<p>Proving your metal is tough if you are just starting out freelancing. Having some experiences to show case is valuable when bidding for projects. When I started off freelancing, my intention was to learn Windows Phone and Windows 8 Modern application development. Since the platform was relatively new then, I started off with a side project <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/store/apps/picfinity/9wzdncrdwxx8">Picfinity</a>, to showcase my capabilities. Building the application also helped me generate a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tag/500px/">few blog posts</a> around these areas and I used both of above to showcase my ability to build applications for the Windows platform. This also helped me increase my hourly rates at a faster pace.
Branding is an ongoing effort that you need to do when freelancing, which indirectly enables you to increase your rates over time. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/">Writing blogs</a>, creating reusable libraries, contributing on forums, etc. are some of the things that help with this.</p>

<p>From the experiences gained from these freelancing platforms you will soon be able to move to consulting on your own or join premium freelancing platforms like <a href="www.toptal.com">Toptal</a>, <a href="http://x-team.com/">Xteam</a>, etc. You could also stick on with these platforms and learn new technologies while getting paid. At the very least I see that it has helped me generate content for my blogs (as I still struggle with topics to blog about).</p>

<p>Hope this helps you to get started with freelancing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
