<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-25T23:15:52+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Language Agnostic Books For Every Developer]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/language-agnostic-books-for-every-developer/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-01T18:33:14+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/language-agnostic-books-for-every-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reading is inevitable to keep up to date with the latest technologies and rapid changes happening in the programming world. But technology is nothing but a tool for getting things done. What one has to understand are the concepts and principles underlying these technology and the core principles of development. These are to be gained through <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/an-enterprise-it-project-experience/">our own experiences</a> and also from the learnings and the experiences of others. Books are a great source of such experiences, and this post is a list of those that I have found interesting and helpful. I have not read all these nor was I able to fully understand whatever I have. These books are to be read/referred to multiple times, practiced and adopted into our work. It&rsquo;s also worth referring other books from the same author&rsquo;s or other writings as they are among the pioneers in our industry.</p>

<p>The books would speak for themselves and I don&rsquo;t think I can do justice writing a summary to any of these. So I have decided to just list them down here(in no specific order). It&rsquo;s worth having a personal copy of each one of these in your bookshelves. (mine is still short of some of them).</p>

<p><div>
      <div class="row">
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0735619670/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0735619670&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=6EBVFQ44LVCQC3VW">
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_codecomplete.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;" >
             </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Code Complete</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
       <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
          <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321146530/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321146530&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=UFKBUSTB43PNRS76" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_tdd.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Test Driven Development</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0131489062/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0131489062&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=2IKSKNFHUIXAC3V4" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_applyinguml.jpeg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Applying UML and Patterns</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
     <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321125215/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321125215&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=LGNNMURUNPIQJ22Q" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_ddd.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Domain Driven Design</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      <div class="row">
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0596805829/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0596805829&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=BAC6OAIRWSGB4ZBB" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_restinpractice.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Rest in Practice</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/020161622X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=020161622X&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=I6W7QKVDPXSBR37P" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_pragmaticprogrammer.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>The Pragmatic Programmer</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0201485672/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0201485672&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=VPJIMQDT3AENNVY6" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_refactoring.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Refactoring</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
    <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321193687/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321193687&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=HXUV2APJ7YOHRIZY" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_umldistilled.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>UML Distilled</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div class="row">   <br/>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0201835959/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0201835959&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=HKH5I6Q3Y6IYSCI5" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_mythicalmanmonth.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>The Mythical Man-Month</strong></h5>         <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0262510871/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0262510871&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=7YASXOZAUG7JDUDI" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_sicp.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
             </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Structure and Interpretaion of Computer Programs</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
       <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0131857258/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0131857258&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=SQ27A44S24WSXQK4" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_agilepatterns.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
           <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Agile Principles, Patterns and Practices</strong></h5>      <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
         <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321127420/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321127420&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=UR5IBEFV64BK5FYG" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_poeaa.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
          </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Patterns of Enterprise Application and Architecture</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>    <br/>
      </div></p>

<p>Hope you start of this year off with some nice readings and gift yourself with some these master pieces. I am sure that I have not covered all of them and there are still more to be &lsquo;chewed and digested&rsquo;. Do drop in with a comment on Which books have helped you be better in programming.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get started with your blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T19:01:58+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are a programmer and don’t have a blog, then there is no better time than now to start one. <a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Shows/HanselminutesOn9/Hanselminutes-on-9-Social-Networking-for-Developers-Part-1-Every-Developer-Needs-a-Blog">Every developer should have a blog</a>, for a very simple reason – <strong>Otherwise all your work is just going wasted!.</strong> I can bet that the best of your code or ideas would either be in some old email that you hardly have access to or archived or in some backup hard-disk waiting to be formatted or already formatted and all gone. All the thought, research and creativity that you would have spent would be lying just wasted and with little or no use. Having an online presence has really become a necessity in today&rsquo;s connected world, and a blog is the best place to show your presence. I started off answering <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count/">mdsn forums</a> and then figured that most of the people had similar questions and I was giving the same answers many a times, which gave me the thought of blogging answers and posting links to them. So anytime someone asks you something or you do something awesome blog it, so that your work does not get wasted and more people would find it useful. As with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rule_of_three_(computer_programming">rule of three</a>) for refactoring, with blogging it’s just rule of one – <em><strong>blog it always </strong>(</em>even this blog is because some one asked me after I recently moved on to a self hosted blog<em>).</em>
I have had a taste of blogspot and WordPress blog web hosting service,  before moving on to a self-hosted blog here. I think you would have guessed which one I would suggest you to get if you are starting your blog – a self hosted one. Indeed there is some effort that goes in to maintain the blog, but its worth every effort that you put.</p>

<p>I use WordPress as the blogging software and am running it on a Linux server (had to change over from windows, as there were a lot of compatibility issues that I faced). WordPress is a very popular blogging engine and so has an immense collection of themes, plug-in and add-on that are available to enhance yours and your readers experience. Once you get your wordpress installed on your self hosted domain, which should be as easy as clicking a button, install the below plugin’s.</p>

<ol>
<li><p> The first thing would be to <strong>connect with </strong><a href="http://jetpack.me/"><strong>jetpack</strong></a>. This would give you a lot of features including stats, social integration, publicize options and many more.</p></li>
<li><p> Connect with <a href="http://akismet.com/"><strong>akismet</strong></a> using the <a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/akismet/">plug-in</a> for preventing/moderating spam comments. Akismet provides a free subscription for personal users.</p></li>
<li><p> <a href="http://feedburner.google.com/"><strong>Claim your feed</strong></a> and put it on your blog. You can again use a <a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/feedburner-form/">feedburner-form</a> if you want.</p></li>
<li><p> Integrate with<strong> </strong><a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/"><strong>Google analytics</strong></a>, if you want more detailed statistics than the one provided with jetpack. Once you get your code, you can use the <a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/googleanalytics/">plug-in</a> to integrate with your site. This will add the necessary code in all your pages header.</p></li>
<li><p> Make sure you have a <strong>backup plan</strong>, as you would not want all your data to vanish off if something happens with the hosting server. You could either use vaultpress or use freely available plug-in to back up to popular cloud storage like Dropbox, Skydrive or Google drive.</p></li>
<li><p> Get a <strong>good theme</strong> for your blog, there a lot of free and paid ones out there.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Now that you have most of the things setup, it’s time for you to put up your first page, <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/about/">About me</a>. This is very important as it gives a sense of credibility to your readers, so make sure you have one. For creating content on to your blog, you can either use the online editor or use some offline editor. Personally I use <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/en-in/download/details.aspx?id=8621">Windows live writer</a>. I love using this and all my blogs are written using this. The one plug-in that you would want to get, if you are a developer is <a href="http://precode.codeplex.com/">PreCode</a>, which makes inserting code really easy.
There are a lot more things that your blog would need, you would soon find that out and when you do, please leave a note of it in the comments section below. Happy Blogging!</p>

<p><strong>Edit</strong>: Couple of people were asking about getting started with a free blog. <a href="http://wordpress.com/">Wordpress.com</a> or <a href="https://www.tumblr.com/">Tumblr</a> would be a very good option to start with. Personally I used Wordpress as I felt that better. The advantage with tumblr over wordpress is that you can <a href="http://www.tumblr.com/docs/en/custom_domains">link your custom domain name with tumblr for free</a> while <a href="http://en.support.wordpress.com/domains/map-existing-domain/">worpress charges for linking a custom domain</a>. (You would need to pay for the custom domain in either cases). But then I ended up hosting all myself after moving away from Wordpress.com.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MVVM – Does it really matter?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/mvvm-does-it-really-matter/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-08T10:42:07+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/mvvm-does-it-really-matter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>MVVM (Model-View-ViewModel), is a popular architectural pattern since WPF/Silverlight. Separation of concerns(UI/code), testability etc are some of the key things that motivates one to go via the MVVM route. There are innumerous articles out there, just like this <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-in/library/hh848246.aspx">one</a>, that gets into the details of how and why one should use MVVM.</p>

<p>With Windows phone also embracing xaml and silverlight, any one who knew silverlight turned a phone developer overnight. MVVM did find its way into this space too. But most of the phone app developers, unlike those who developed for enterprise. would have never cared for MVVM , as they rarely would have written test cases for their apps, nor were they actually concerned on the UI/code separation. Since most of the apps were just out of a hobby, the only idea was just to have it up and available in the store as fast as possible. I might not be fully correct here, but I do know at least a dozen people,including me, who did this, so am good enough to put out that statement</p>

<p>With windows 8 too taking the store way and having the same development platform of silverlight/xaml, don’t be surprised MVVM  showed up there too. Now anyone who had an app on the phone, had to do a lot of copy pasting over the code to have the same application available in both the stores. This gives MVVM a totally new dimension for motivation that was not spoken  about earlier – <strong><em>Reusability. </em></strong></p>

<p>Having an application for phone and windows 8 app store with the minimum amount of rework is best possible by using MVVM and also a couple of other techniques. There is a detailed <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windowsphone/develop/jj681693(v=vs.105">article</a>.aspx) on msdn on how how to maximize code reuse between Windows Phone 8 and Windows 8.</p>

<p>MVVM does really matter now, if we do not want to end up copy pasting code from phone app to the windows 8 store app. Also fixing and adding in new features would become more easier with following MVVM</p>

<p><a href="http://nuget.org/packages/Portable.MvvmLightLibs/">MVVM Toolkit</a> is a very popular helper library for implementing MVVM pattern, as is available on nuget as a PCL(Portable class library)</p>

<p><strong>MVVM<em>, It really does matter !!!</em></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Venturing out ]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/venturing-out/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-15T21:54:47+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/venturing-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Blogs are always a very good medium to express our thoughts,views,knowledge and much more.In cases of where you blog on topics new to you,blogging can also be a way to learn and to get feedback.</p>

<p>But what good does it come to if the reader base for your blogs are less.It&rsquo;s true that with social sites like Facebook,twitter etc you stand a better chance to publicize your blogs more and increase your reader base.But still it has its own limitations as not all of the people that follows you might be interested in the topics that you blog.<del>So the best thing would be to find communities/group blogs that relate to topics that you commonly blog on and contribute there.</del></p>

<p><del>Being in Microsoft I have this privilege of having a space in the msdn blogs.Its been a long time since I had started an account <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/rahulpnath/">there</a> and kept thinking on what to post.I think its high time to start off with that and enjoy one of the biggest reader base for technical topics.</del></p>

<p><del>Why from today but???&hellip;..Thanks to the guys who motivated me to move on and venture out. :)
</del></p>

<p><strong>Edit:</strong> Yes I still do have the privilege, but I think it is better to have it here in my on domain than anywhere else, as it will always be mine. So I have decided to keep all my thoughts and posts on this site. I have even moved from wordpress hosting to a self hosted one so I have more control.</p>

<p>“<em>Human beings, who are almost unique in having the ability to learn from the experience of others, are also remarkable for their apparent disinclination to do so.</em>”</p>

<p>PS: Posting out my recent blog on REST</p>

<p><a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/rahulpnath/">http://blogs.msdn.com/b/rahulpnath/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stars Do Count!!!!]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-17T17:33:58+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For all those who are wondering what this stars are,please go through my first <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/do-stars-count/">post</a> on this.</p>

<p>Casually browsing through my mails today morning,I found a mail with the subject stating,&lsquo;<em>Your online community contributions have been recognized by Microsoft</em>&rsquo;,informing me that I have won the Microsoft <a href="http://www.microsoftcommunitycontributor.com/">Community Contributor Award</a>.Really excited to have the first award for a technical contribution,and that too from Microsoft.</p>

<p><img src="/mcca_rahulpnath.png" alt="Microsoft Community Contributor Award Certificate for Rahul P Nath" /></p>

<p>I appreciate Microsoft for promoting community contributors and rewarding them.Personally,I enjoy contributing in communities as I find it one another way to learn.I used not just reply to questions that I knew,but often ended up creating a sample application and finding out the solution first,which has helped me a lot in learning.</p>

<p>I would like to thank Microsoft and all the community members and people who would  have nominated me for this award.</p>

<p>Stars Do Count sometimes :)</p>

<p>edit: The award would be retired as now I am an Microsoft employee.I had intimated them on this ,as I guess somehow their records missed that I am their employee :).So got the mail confirmation today..award is retired .Still it&rsquo;s a good feeling in having achieved it at the first place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
