<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-18T04:50:48+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Morning Routine]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-16T05:00:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Humans are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zdGbHY9VKVM">creatures of habit</a> and things work well if made as a routine. It&rsquo;s what you build as your daily plan that defines what you end up achieving in the day and in turn with life.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>If you are a late night person, you can read &lsquo;morning&rsquo; as &lsquo;late night&rsquo; - the focus here is routine!</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.pexels.com/photo/coffee-cup-notebook-pen-64775/">
<img  alt="Win your day, create a morning routine" src="/images/morning_routine.jpg"/>
</a></p>

<p>A morning routine is nothing but a sequence of actions regularly followed. I have tried switching my routine too, to late in the night a few times but found that mornings work better for me. But this could be different for you, so stick to the time of day that works for you. Before going to how my morning routine looks like (which I just started a week back), I will explain how I made the plan for the routine.</p>

<h3>Brain Dump</h3>

<p>At any point in time, there are a lot of things in my mind and things that I kept committing to myself and others. It is not possible to keep up with everything that I wish to do. So the very first thing to do is to dump everything out onto to paper and then decide what needs attention. The <a href="http://gettingthingsdone.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/Mind_Sweep_Trigger_List.pdf">Incompletion Trigger List</a> assists to get everything out of your mind onto paper. It&rsquo;s a good idea to block some time of yours to perform this exercise and give it all the attention it needs. At times it helps to <strong><em>Slow Down to Go Fast</em></strong>.</p>

<p><img  alt="Slow down, to go faster" src="/images/morningroutine_slow_down.jpg"/></p>

<h3>Most Important Task (MIT)</h3>

<p>If you are following along, hope the brain dump helped to flush out all that was there in your mind. This exercise needs to be occasionally done (maybe every 2-3 months) to stay clear and stay on top of things. I was sure that I could not do everything on that list after the brain dump. Now comes the hard part of choosing what matters to you and choosing those that aligns well with your goals. For the morning routine, I stuck to items from the brain dump that fall under &lsquo;Personal Projects&rsquo; category (as highlighted in the below image).</p>

<p><img  alt="Choosing tasks for morning routine" src="/images/morning_routine_MIT.png"/></p>

<p>These are the items that matter to me and aligns to the short-long term goals that I have. Below is a part of my list.</p>

<pre><code class="text">Start Youtube channel
Become Pluralsight Author
Blogging
Learn Functional Programming
Learn Ruby
Open Source Contribution
Improving Writing Skills and Language
</code></pre>

<blockquote><p><em>The key is not to prioritize what’s on your schedule, but to schedule your priorities.</em></p>

<p><em>– <strong>Stephen Covey</strong></em></p></blockquote>

<p>Progressing towards all of these items on the list at the same time is not possible, as time available each day for achieving them is limited. I usually get around 2-3 hours a day of &lsquo;me time&rsquo;, provided I wake up at 4 in the morning (more on this shortly). The number of hours you have might differ, and you could choose those many items as you think you can fit in. But 3 is a good number to choose, as that helps to mix in a few different goals and gives the flexibility to shuffle around with them on a day. For me, it also means I roughly get around 40-60 minutes daily, for each item.</p>

<p>Currently, the ones that I have in my morning routine are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Blogging</li>
<li>Learn Functional Programming</li>
<li>Open Source Contribution</li>
</ul>


<h3>MITs to Mini Habits</h3>

<p>Having high-level short-long term goals is good, but does not provide anything actionable on a daily basis. It feels overwhelming to approach them because it does not give any sense of direction. So it&rsquo;s important that I have small actionable items that I can work on and progress towards achieving the goal.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Break your goal into the smallest possible task that you can think of so that you don&rsquo;t feel to skip it</em></p></blockquote>

<p>For me, the mini habits look like this</p>

<ul>
<li>Write at least one sentence for the blog</li>
<li>Read at least one line about Functional Programming</li>
<li>Read at least one line of code of an Open Source Project</li>
</ul>


<p>The idea behind keeping it so small is just to start. It&rsquo;s very rare that I have stopped writing after writing a sentence or stopped reading after a line. The trouble is only with getting started - once done you can easily carry on for at least 20-30 minutes. Even if I make 2 out of the 3 of the above tasks, I take it as a success, which gives me some flexibility each day.</p>

<h3>Waking up Tricks</h3>

<p>There are days when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resistance_(creativity">Resistance</a>) beats me to it, and I don&rsquo;t get up to the routine. But I feel low on those days for not able to progress on my goals. So I try hard to have less of such days.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Alarm Phone Inside Pillow:</strong> I use <a href="http://www.bitspin.ch/">Timely</a> on a spare phone to set alarms.  Till a while back I used to keep the phone at the bedside while sleeping. But I noticed that I often ended up snoozing the alarm, at times even without full consciousness. So to make I <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">wake up to the alarm</a>, I now keep the phone buried inside my pillow with just the vibration. The vibration forces me to wake up and also removes the need for any alarm sound - my kid and wife does not get disturbed.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Wear a Sweater:</strong> During winter, at times the cold beat me to it. It&rsquo;s hard to leave all the blankets and wake up to the cold. I started sleeping with the sweater, and I don&rsquo;t feel that cold when I wake up.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Rationalize Against Resistance:</strong> However hard I try not to rationalize on getting up when the alarm sounds off, looking at the snooze button I end up rationalizing. Often I have found that when I try to use the tasks that I can achieve if I wake up, to motivate myself, I end up justifying that it can wait for tomorrow. Because there is no hard deadlines or accountability to anyone - it&rsquo;s just me!. Now I try just the opposite - Think about the resistance that is trying to force me to the bed and reassure myself that I should not fall to it. The &lsquo;me&rsquo; waking up after sleeping in is not going to like it then. So wake up!</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>My Routine</h3>

<ol>
<li><em>Wake at 4 am</em></li>
<li><em>Brush</em></li>
<li><em>Drink Water</em></li>
<li><em>Stretching</em></li>
<li><em>Review the tasks for the day (<a href="https://en.todoist.com/">Todoist</a>)</em></li>
<li><em>Mini Habits (2 or 3)</em></li>
<li><em>Wake up wife at 5:45 am</em></li>
<li><em>Continue Mini Habits (2 or 3)</em></li>
<li><em>Tea</em></li>
<li><em>Wake up Gautham at 7 am</em></li>
</ol>


<p>Having a morning routine has helped me focus more on things that matter and not wander from one task to another. It has also helped set a sense of direction to what I do every day and spent less time in thinking what to do. I find my days starting in gradually and not rushing into it, setting up the pace for the day. Hope this helps you too!</p>

<h4><strong>References</strong></h4>

<div>
      <div class="row">
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://amzn.to/2a3wpUc">
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_powerofhabit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;" >
             </a>
          </div>
        </div>
       <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
          <a href="http://amzn.to/2ahrOcr" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_gtd.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://amzn.to/2aek2R5" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_warofart.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
          </div>
        </div>
     <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://zenhabits.net/" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_zenhabits.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
          </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       </div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding a Job Abroad]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/finding-a-job-abroad/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-25T06:07:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/finding-a-job-abroad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a year since I have moved over to <a href="https://readify.net/">Readify</a> in Sydney, Australia. Like I never believed that one could <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-freelancing-jobs-online/">earn money on the Internet</a>, I never thought that I could easily find a job abroad.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>If you are not a developer this post might not be fully applicable to you. However the things that helped me might help you too.</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Sydney_Opera_house_HDR_Sydney_Australia.jpg">
    <img class="center" alt="How I found a job in Sydney" src="/images/finding_job_abroad.png" />
</a></p>

<p>I was not so keen to move abroad with an on-site opportunity from India, given the overhead of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_delivery_model">onsite-offshore coordination</a> is a pain. Getting a  resident visa for countries like Australia, Canada etc. and finding a job after moving in was another option. I didn&rsquo;t prefer that either, as ending up in a foreign country without a job didn&rsquo;t look great to me, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/life-learnings-after-being-a-parent/">especially with Gautham</a>. So the only option left was to find an employer who recruits internationally and move in with a sponsored work visa. There are a lot of companies that are looking for people across the world and ready to sponsor for the visa . Since there is more money and effort involved in the whole process of recruiting internationally, I have felt that companies look for something more than just passing an interview process. Here are a few things that helped me find such an employer and things that I could have done better.</p>

<h3>The Third Place</h3>

<p>There needs to a place other than <strong>Home</strong> and <strong>Work</strong>,  where you spend time and this is often referred to as a <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/TheDeveloperTheoryOfTheThirdPlace.aspx">Third Place</a>. It could be your <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/blogging/">blog</a>, <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/1948745/rahul-p-nath">stack overflow</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count/">msdn forums</a>, <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath">GitHub</a>, podcast, YouTube channel, social media pages etc. For me primarily it is this blog and then GitHub and a bit of <a href="https://social.msdn.microsoft.com/profile/rahul%20p%20nath?type=forum&amp;referrer=http://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/azure/en-US/home">msdn forums</a>. Having a Third Place increases your chances of landing a job and also acts as a good &lsquo;Resume&rsquo;. I feel a resume is not worthy these days, as you can put whatever you feel like in that and needs to be validated through an interview. A blog, forum profile etc cannot be faked and always speaks about your experience.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>There is no reason to believe in a Resume, it can always be faked - but a history of events, posts or articles is hard to be faked. A resume should self-validate.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>A resume, if at all it needs to be there, should be just a highlight of all your experiences, with relevant links to your &lsquo;Third Place&rsquo;. This also helps keep resume short and clear.</p>

<h3>Using Social Media For The Advantage</h3>

<p>Social media is a really powerful to connect with different people, especially Twitter and LinkedIn. These are good channels to establish relationships with different people from different geographies. It&rsquo;s good to follow and start general conversations with employees of companies that you wish to join. Try to get involved with any tweets, messages, open source projects that they are also involved in . With time, once you become known to them, either you can reach out to them for an opportunity to work together or they themselves might offer you one. Don&rsquo;t try to fake it or overdo this, as it can affect you adversely. Do this only if you are genuinely interested in what they do.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="The Hague - Amsterdam" src="/images/amsterdam_thehague.jpg" title="One day in Amsterdam" /></p>

<p>For me, I landed an interview with <a href="https://www.evision-software.com/">eVision</a>, through one of my Twitter contact, <a href="https://twitter.com/randompunter">Damian Hickey</a>. it just happened that we followed each other and he worked for eVision, and I found the company interesting. Just a message to him and 2 months later I was in Amsterdam attending an interview with them and an offer for employment a week later. But I ended up not joining them because of the visa getting delayed for a long period as I was not fully &lsquo;travel ready&rsquo; (more on this below). But I enjoyed every bit of the time I spend with &lsquo;<em>Team Tigers</em>&rsquo; in eVision.</p>

<h3>Reaching out to Companies Directly</h3>

<p><a href="https://readify.net/">Readify</a> was another company that interested me. The company itself took pride in its employees and values a lot in their Professional development. The different people that were part of the company was another reason that I like Readify - MVPs, Book authors, Pluralsight authors, bloggers, musicians, photographers - name it and there was a person with that interests. It is also one of the <a href="https://readify.net/about-us/awards-recognitions/">best consulting companies</a> in Australia. The recruitment process was straightforward and all started with the <a href="https://knockknock.readify.net/">knock-knock challenge</a>, followed by a <a href="https://readify.net/careers/apply-now/technical-consultants/">series of interviews</a>. Everything just fell in place and on time and I ended up joining them and moving over to Sydney Australia on a work visa. Readify is still hiring and if you are interested and find yourself a match send me your profile (for no reason but to earn me the referral bonus) - if not head off to the knock knock challenge.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Good developers are in great demand and &lsquo;Good&rsquo; is relative - you have a place out there all you need is to reach out!</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Look out for companies in LinkedIn or <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/jobs?location=Sydney%2C%20Australia">StackOverflow Careers</a> who sponsor visa and follow their recruitment process.</p>

<h3>Being Travel Ready</h3>

<p>As I mentioned above one of the reasons not to take up the offer at eVision, was because of the visa getting delayed for a long period. Since all my documents are from India, I had to get all my documents attested and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apostille_Convention">Apostille&rsquo;d</a>, which takes around a month&rsquo;s time. Added to that neither I nor my wife had a birth certificate (as it was not so common thing in my place when I was born). So I had to first get all the documents and then get them apostilled, which was not to happen in at least 2-3 months. Even if you have no interest in moving abroad,get all your travel documents and keep them ready.
Most commonly asked for documents are</p>

<ul>
<li>Passport</li>
<li>Birth certificate</li>
<li>Education certificates</li>
<li>Work Experience certificates</li>
<li>Marriage certificate (if you are married)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Making the Move</h3>

<p>One of the biggest challenges that I faced while making the move, was to get around the currency conversion and to ensure that the same standard of living can be maintained once I move across it. Sites like <a href="https://www.expatistan.com/cost-of-living">Expatistan</a>, <a href="http://www.numbeo.com/cost-of-living/">Numbeo</a> etc. help give an idea on approximate costs. But what&rsquo;s worked for me more is to not use the actual <a href="http://www.xe.com/">currency exchange rate</a>, but to find a &lsquo;<strong>Personal Exchange Rate</strong> (PER)&rsquo; and use that to compare.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Personal Exchange Rate is your Disposable Income in Home Country/Disposable Income in Destination Country. Multiply costs of items in destination country by PER to see how it compares to prices in your country.</em></p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" alt="View from my office, Sydney" src="/images/sydney_work.jpg" title="View from my office" /></p>

<p>I moved over to Sydney last year around the same time. It was difficult to adjust in during the initial days, but soon it all started to fall into the rhythm. It&rsquo;s been a year with Readify and at my client and I am enjoying the new experiences.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Own Your URLs; Nothing Else Really Matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/own-your-urls/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-27T05:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/own-your-urls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past couple of years, I have been successful in motivating a couple of my friends to start a blog and I am happy about that. Every time I discuss starting a blog the most common things that come up are what platform to choose, where to host, where to buy the domain, blogging frequency,will anyone even read my posts, what to blog etc.  These were the same questions that I had when I wanted to start a blog and good reasons to procrastinate on for a long time. Over the years having changed the blog platform a couple of times, changing domain name providers, hosting platform, blogging tools here is what I have learned.</p>

<h3>The Golden Rule of Blogging!</h3>

<p>You should have already guessed that from the   post title - The URL where you blog under - Make sure you own it. Buy one of your choices, from any of the <a href="https://www.google.com.au/search?q=buy+domain">domain providers</a> (more on this later) and blog under that. While it&rsquo;s easy to start blogging under popular services like WordPress.com/Blogspot.com, you actually don&rsquo;t own your domain.</p>

<p><a href="https://i.kinja-img.com/gawker-media/image/upload/pgtqyluoyhr1swo4wrmn.jpg">
<img class="center" alt="Own your URL" src="/images/url.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>I have committed this mistake, of blogging under a URL not owned by me, not <a href="rahulpnath.blogspot.com">once</a> but <a href="https://rahulpnath.wordpress.com">twice</a>,and ended up having to edit the posts to redirect here. (I did not want to pay the providers a monthly fee just for the redirect and didn&rsquo;t have many readers). It&rsquo;s not that these external platforms are bad, but you are just throwing away the flexibility to change platforms (without any extra  charge) when you want to. Owning your URLs allows you to change platforms, hosts, URL formats, redirects anything that you want to and I like to have that flexibility.</p>

<h3>The lesser important things</h3>

<p>Other than the URL that you blog on, other things are not that important and here&rsquo;s why I feel that. If you are completely new to terms like domain, website, hosting etc. check out this article on <a href="http://support.hostgator.com/articles/hosting-guide/what-is-the-difference-between-domains-vs-hosting-vs-website"> the difference between all these</a>.</p>

<h4><strong>Where to buy the domain?</strong></h4>

<p>Choose one and move on with it, even if you do not like it you can change your domain provider anytime. You can <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/1164499/web-apps/how-to-transfer-your-domain-name-between-hosts.html">transfer from one host to another</a> very easily and I have done that. I started off with GoDaddy for the first year as they seemed the cheapest when I started. But at the time of renewal, I learned that it was just for the first year that it was cheap but for renewals, it was costlier. So I moved on to <a href="https://www.namecheap.com/?aff=101935">Namecheap</a>(<em>affiliate</em>) and am with them ever since. Nothing against GoDaddy though, if it works for you get it from there or somewhere - <strong>Get one right now if you don&rsquo;t own a domain!</strong></p>

<h4><strong>Where to host?</strong></h4>

<p>For a website to be accessible to all, it needs to be running somewhere on the internet and accessible to all, and this is what typically a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_hosting_service">hosting service</a> provides. The hosting and domain provider need not be the same entity, so you can get your hosting space anywhere and link it with your domain. Your domain provider will give you some console/website where you can configure this. There are also free hosts like <a href="https://pages.github.com/">Github</a>, <a href="https://www.tumblr.com/">tumblr</a>, <a href="https://support.google.com/blogger/answer/55374?hl=en">Blogger</a> etc., which allows custom domain mapping for free, unlike <a href="https://en.support.wordpress.com/domains/">wordpress.com</a>. Godaddy, Namecheap, Azure, AWS etc are few popular options for hosting, if not Google to find what matches your need. <a href="http://www.webhostingsecretrevealed.net/blog/web-hosting-guides/switching-web-host/">Switching from one web host to another</a> is even easier than transferring domains, so do not spend much time deciding where to host.</p>

<h4><strong>Which blogging platform to choose?</strong></h4>

<p>There are a large number of blogging platforms available today and it is a very difficult choice to decide on one. If all you are planning to put is a blog with static text, then <a href="https://www.staticgen.com/">static site generators</a> are a good choice and it ends up you hosting just plain <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/rahulpnath.com/tree/blog">HTML, Javascript, CSS and images</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/static-generator-is-all-a-blog-needs-moving-to-octopress/">like this one</a> (at time of writing). But this does involve some knowledge of development environments and tools, so ignore it if you are not that person. <a href="https://wordpress.org/">WordPress</a> is easy to start with and is famous for its 5-minute installations. Note that this is not the wordpress.com site which is like a hosting service, but this is the WordPress  platform itself which you can host yourself anywhere you choose to, like <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/azure-web-sites-moving-wordpress-to-cloud/">I did for some time in Azure</a>. WordPress is just one that is popular, but there are a lot of <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/web/gallery/categories.aspx?category=Blogs">similar platforms that you can choose from</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>When starting to blog, choose a platform that makes writing easy and not have the overhead of using the platform stop you from writing</em></p></blockquote>

<h4><strong>Who will read my blog?</strong></h4>

<p>This one was the biggest stopper for me - Who cares about what I write? Maybe no one does, but now I write for myself, it makes me happy as I like to share information with others. Blogging helps me understand and explore topics more deeply. Finally, it&rsquo;s a reference that I can always go back to when I face something similar. If you have faced a particular scenario (which might be totally weird) then it is very likely that it is going to be experienced by somebody else too. And Google makes finding things easy, and it will be found!</p>

<h4><strong>Frequency and commitment</strong></h4>

<p>I have been irregular with my blogging schedules (<a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/archives/">until lately</a>) and used to blog just when motivation strikes. But since the start of this year, I am trying to blog on a schedule. Just experimenting with it and seeing how it goes, so far I am really liking it.It has given a different outlook to work and life in general, as it makes me look more closely for opportunities to generate a blog post. But it&rsquo;s fine even without a commitment and blog irregularly unless you have some expectations of your reader base or generate revenue from the blog. But have a place to go and scribble down whenever you feel to and own that place!</p>

<p><figure><br/>
    <img alt="Blog frequency as on 26-06-2-16 http://www.rahulpnath.com" src="/images/blog_frequency.png" />
    <figcaption><em>Blog frequency as on June,2016 <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com">http://www.rahulpnath.com</a></em></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good idea to have a schedule to blog , so that you don&rsquo;t just end up writing one post and forget about your blog forever. <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/how-to-achieve-ultimate-blog-success-in-one-easy-step/">Pick a schedule that works for you</a> and try to stick with it.</p>

<h4><strong>No Original Content</strong></h4>

<p>It&rsquo;s fine to blog about things that you have not created yourself, the way you learned things or anything you feel to write about, necessarily not even current at the time of writing. For eg., You might be working on Mainframes system and MainFrame is not current and cutting edge now. But that does not mean you should not be blogging about it. Just like you, there are a lot of mainframe developers and it might just help one of them. So don&rsquo;t bother much about the originality of content, it&rsquo;s your experiences and the way you see it- that&rsquo;s always going to be unique.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;A blog is neither a diary nor a journal. Many people think of blogging in relation to those two things, confessional or practical. It is neither but includes elements of both.&rdquo; - Lemn Sissay</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/">Every &lsquo;professional&rsquo; should have a blog</a>, and if you don&rsquo;t yet, now is a good time to start one. Sound off in the comments on what you feel about blogging in general, especially if you bought a domain and set up your blog after reading this. It will prove a point for this post!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Life Learnings After Being a Parent]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/life-learnings-after-being-a-parent/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-14T16:48:25+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/life-learnings-after-being-a-parent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><em>His father asked Ethan in a raspy voice, &ldquo;You spend time with your son?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Much as I can,&rdquo; he’d answered, but his father had caught the lie in his eyes.</em></p>

<p><em>&ldquo;It’ll be your loss, Ethan. Day&rsquo;ll come, when he’s grown and it’s too late, that you&rsquo;d give a kingdom to go back and spend a single hour with your son as a boy. To hold him.Read a book to him. Throw a ball with a person in whose eyes you can do no wrong. He doesn&rsquo;t see your failings yet. He looks at you with pure love and it won&rsquo;t last, so you revel in it while it&rsquo;s here.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><em>Ethan thinks often of that conversation, mostly when he&rsquo;s lying awake in bed at night and everyone else is asleep, and his life screaming past at the speed of light—the weight of bills and the future and his prior failings and all these moments he&rsquo;s missing—all the lost joy—perched like a boulder on his chest.</em></p>

<p>- <strong> <em><a href="http://amzn.to/1YdxuYm">Pines (The Wayward Pines Trilogy, Book 1)</a></em> </strong></p></blockquote>

<p>Every second that I spent with Gautham is a pure joy and I enjoy it to the most. It&rsquo;s true that I have very less time to spend for myself, but then it also made me realized I have not been using all the time I did have before he was born. I have re-arranged all my schedules so that whenever I am home and he is awake, I do nothing else, but be with him! There has been a lot of learnings and realizations that I have had since the last 20 months.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Command Line Application Launcher" src="/images/gautham.jpg" /></p>

<h4><strong>Curiosity is what keeps us going</strong></h4>

<p>Each day is a new day and he learns at least one new thing. Though to us (the &lsquo;grown-ups&rsquo;), it feels that he is doing the same thing over and over again, for him, it&rsquo;s the same thing in a new perspective. He is curious about everything that he sees and happens around. I often felt that my job was boring, mundane and repetitive and often ended up being the same thing every day. But then I understood that it is not about what you do but how you see what you are doing, that matters. Having at least one new thing to learn from whatever you do daily is a good way to stay motivated.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Always try to understand one level below your current level of abstraction - happiness lies there!</em></p></blockquote>

<h4><strong>Making the Complex Simple</strong></h4>

<p>Often when playing with him I realize how overwhelming things are in the world and all that he is yet to learn. But that&rsquo;s just me putting my perspective through his eyes. For him, it&rsquo;s always &lsquo;try try and try again&rsquo;. He tries the best he can do something now and improve on it over the days or months.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>How do you eat an elephant? One bite at a time.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I often get overwhelmed when dealing with something new - learning a new language, buying a car or even planning a vacation. There are innumerable options for everything these days and all that information is available at our fingertips. But then the way to approach these is to break it down into smaller chunks of work and target that individually. Just like writing this blog post is overwhelming for me for all the things that I think I need to write, but then I write section by section or even line by line. Forming <a href="http://amzn.to/1toWtyy">habits</a> to break anything <a href="http://amzn.to/1Xg6biH">complex into smaller pieces</a> and tackling that is a good way to approach tasks.</p>

<h4><strong>Learning to Disconnect</strong></h4>

<p>I certainly do not want Gautham to be entertained with a smartphone, iPad or laptop while I get to do something else. Though it is very much plausible, that&rsquo;s just setting him up the wrong path. It&rsquo;s easy for us to get distracted into all these and not do what matters to us the most - just like all of us hooked into the social media.</p>

<blockquote><p><em><a href="https://medium.com/life-learning/how-to-live-a-life-of-balance-and-high-productivity-bd5434a61c79#.26mh9yvec">Social media is best as planned entertainment rather than unplanned distraction.</a></em></p></blockquote>

<p>The more you stay offline from these &lsquo;addictive&rsquo; social networks the less you will feel the need to check it. Like I do not want my kid to be addicted to these, I do not want it to get in the way of me using that time for something more useful. Staying disconnected from the internet and social network is a good way to get a lot of time for yourself.</p>

<h4><strong>Less is More</strong></h4>

<p>Gautham is happy just with a bottle cap, or a small thread of a shirt and can spend a lot of time playing with it. It&rsquo;s not in what you have but how you see things that you have matters. I was always attracted to the latest and coolest gadgets and often bought them too. Happiness then was directly related to the things I had in possession and how current I was. I have learned to get over that minimize my expense to what matters most. Though it&rsquo;s a bit late , the saying &lsquo;<em>Do not save what is left after spending but spend what is left after saving</em>&rsquo;, starts making a lot of sense. The fact that there is someone who is completely dependent on me(/wife) brings in a lot of responsibility to life which was missing earlier and puts savings in front of expenses.</p>

<h4><strong>Time is Valuable</strong></h4>

<p>One of the most precious things that I have is time. I used to while away time earlier but now I have very limited of it for myself that I try to spend it usefully. Having your <a href="http://zenhabits.net/purpose-your-day-most-important-task/">Most Important Task</a> (MIT) defined is important and helps prioritize your tasks for the day. If you feel a lot of time is getting lost, while sitting down to work (on a laptop for me) use monitoring tools like <a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/">Rescue Time</a> to understand your daily habits and improve on it.</p>

<blockquote><p><em><a href="http://quoteinvestigator.com/2013/10/30/inspire-nine/">Someone once asked</a> Somerset Maugham if he wrote on a schedule or only when struck by inspiration. “I write only when inspiration strikes,” he replied. “Fortunately, it strikes every morning at nine o’clock sharp.”</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Habits decide what we do every day so it&rsquo;s very important that we form good ones. Though it takes effort, it is possible to <a href="http://charlesduhigg.com/how-habits-work/">rewire any of your habits</a> just by giving attention to it.</p>

<h4><strong>Learning from Mistakes</strong></h4>

<p>When you try, you fail and you fail again and again until you succeed. When you don&rsquo;t try you fail - you fail to succeed! <a href="http://www.psychologyinaction.org/2012/11/22/infants-learn-to-walk-by-learning-to-fall/">Infants learn to walk by learning to fall</a>. It&rsquo;s easy to get into a comfort zone and stay there be it in your jobs or elsewhere. Intentionally putting yourself into a position to learn and grow is important. I spent a large part of my time at the workplace. So I try to own up a lot more unfamiliar things and get exposed more - It&rsquo;s Ok to fail!</p>

<p>Parenting is hard but it&rsquo;s also real fun. You get to learn a lot yourself while on the journey and <strong><em>they give back the initial years of your life</em></strong>. Let me wrap this up quickly as he is about to wake up and the last thing I want is to have all the keys pulled off my keyboard!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Make it Easy for the New Person Joining the Team - Have a Project Ramp up Plan]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/make-it-easy-for-the-new-person-joining-your-team-have-a-project-ramp-up-plan/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-18T12:38:24+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/make-it-easy-for-the-new-person-joining-your-team-have-a-project-ramp-up-plan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was in a discussion with my friend/colleague on conducting a few ramp up sessions for the new hires in our team. The discussion went as below,</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Me: We should hold a few sessions to make the new guys in team more comfortable</em></p>

<p><em>Friend: It&rsquo;s too early for it. We should let them find their own way and not &lsquo;spoon-feed&rsquo; them with information.</em></p>

<p><em>Me: But we are not &lsquo;spoon-feeding&rsquo; them, we are just making their learning process faster and giving then an overview on how all the technology fits together in our world of things.</em></p>

<p><em>Friend: But &lsquo;I did not have any ramp up when I joined, and I felt it was better to have learned it on my own, though it took a lot more time.</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.mindtickle.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/new_employee_orientation_business_strategy_research.png" class="center" title="Image, from http://www.mindtickle.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/new_employee_orientation_business_strategy_research.png"><img src="/images\rampup_plan.png" class="center" alt="Rampup Plan"></a></p>

<p>Just like there are company-wide induction/onboarding sessions, I have always felt that project specific onboarding plans are also required and help new hires be part of the team and be more productive with their day-to-day activities faster. As mentioned in this <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3029820/work-smart/infographic-the-real-ways-to-hold-on-to-new-hires/3">article</a>, <em>New hires care more about effective job training and clear guidelines, and it&rsquo;s time you provide that for them.</em> It&rsquo;s best to have a plan in place when you have someone new joining your team and you along with the team are the best people to put that plan together.</p>

<h3>Boy Scout Rule</h3>

<p>The Boy Scouts have a <a href="http://programmer.97things.oreilly.com/wiki/index.php/The_Boy_Scout_Rule">rule</a> - <em>&ldquo;Always leave the campground cleaner than you found it.&rdquo;</em>  New hires are like &lsquo;new camp group&rsquo; at a campground, so it&rsquo;s the duty of the &lsquo;existing team&rsquo; there to make it a good experience for them.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>&lsquo;Refactor&rsquo; your experiences to make it better for the next person who is about to take on the same journey</em></p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s not that my friend was intentionally trying not to pass on any information, but he felt that learning on their own would be better. Even I agree with him that learning on your own is far better than &lsquo;spoon-feeding&rsquo; - but a ramp up plan is not spoon-feeding. A ramp up plan is only to speed up the learning process and to make it more comfortable for someone joining new.</p>

<h3>When to create the plan?</h3>

<p>The need for such a plan is there only when there has been enough progress made on the project, after which there is someone new joining the team. So when a new hire is scheduled to join is a good time to create the &lsquo;draft&rsquo; plan. Once the new hire has gone through it and updated back with his own experiences it could become the first version of the plan, which can then be confidently shared to anyone joining after as it has worked for at least one person.</p>

<h3>What should be there in the plan</h3>

<p><em>It depends!</em></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s totally up to the team to decide what should be there in the plan. Some of the things that I usually have are</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Overview of the project and what problem it is trying to solve</strong></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s really important that everyone on the team knows what the application is trying to solve and have a common goal to work towards. It&rsquo;s not just about the code we write but about the problem we are solving and that needs to be clearly defined. I would record a video, when this is done the first time and share it with anyone joining after that, as most of the core concepts of a project rarely change. There could be a follow-up session post watching the video, to also have a quick walk through and fill any missing gaps.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Introduction to various technologies used in the project and how everything fits together</strong></p>

<p>Technology changes so fast these days that it is nearly impossible to stay updated with all the available options. So a walk through of the different technologies and pointers to resources that worked for you and the team will be of help. If there are any specific libraries, frameworks getting used, an introduction to those should also help.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Release cycle and Release management</strong>
Every project has its own model of delivering the end product and everyone on the team should understand this process well. Having a continuous build is becoming more common these days and helps reduce the complexity of release. An end to end walk-through of the deployment process helps understand the application better and provides exposure to all the moving parts in the system.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Environment/Machine setup</strong>
Software installation is one of the biggest pain when setting up a new machine for a project, especially with having specific versions of the software. Having a documented list of all the project dependencies (hardware and software) makes setting the project environment easy. It&rsquo;s preferable to have these <a href="https://chocolatey.org/">scripted</a>. Have a common place, where you can find links to all the various environments (dev, at,prod etc) and related resources.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Patterns and Conventions</strong>
Every project has its own conventions and certain core patterns that are followed. It&rsquo;s good to have these patterns available for reference so that it helps understand the code better and helps reduce code-review cycles. Than having one big boring document, what I prefer more is to have multiple blog articles targeting each of those. I try to generalize commonly used patterns in the projects that I have worked on and create blog posts. This also helps generate content for <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/">your blog</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tips &amp; Tricks</strong>
This could range from how to easily navigate the code base, scripts to do some commonly occurring task and general things to keep an eye for.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>These are just some of the things I generally try to include in a ramp up plan but as said it totally depends on the team and the project.</p>

<h3>Sharing the plan</h3>

<p>Depending on the plan, if it has confidential information, you could split this into two (or more) different documents and share it at different phases of onboarding. Once a new hire is confirmed it&rsquo;s good to share the parts which do not have any confidential information. Technology stack, conventions used, machine setup (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bring_your_own_device">BYOD</a>) are usually not confidential and can be shared well before actual employment. Once all employment agreements are in place the rest too can be shared. It&rsquo;s also a good idea to have some walk-through of the plan itself to make it easier to follow.</p>

<h3>Iterate and Improve</h3>

<p>Updating back with the experiences of the people using the plan is important to keep it current and valuable. Suggesting improvements and updates should be an item in the plan so that this does not get missed. To make updates manageable, the plan must be accessible to all and preferably version controlled if they are documents.</p>

<p>What are your thoughts on having a ramp up plan?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
