<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-07-04T00:01:46+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Share and Inspire]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/share-and-inspire/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/share-and-inspire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started this blog around nine years back, my only intention was to share technical posts. But over period of time I started writing about a variety of things including <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/">productivity tips</a> that I found useful, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/travelogue/">travelogues</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/">random thoughts</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap/">personal goals</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/blogging/">blogging</a> etc. One of the things that I have noticed is that a lot of people have been inspired by these various posts and photos that I post online and have triggered them to do similar things.</p>

<p><img src="/images/share_and_inspire.jpg" alt="Share and Inspire, Image Source https://www.saylor.org/2015/04/blog-saylor-student-stories/" class="center"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had my own similar inspirations to start the various things that I do today. Like for instance, I started running after being inspired by my friends, <a href="https://twitter.com/SatyKrish">Satish</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/jeyakums">Suresh</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/thirusv">Thiru</a>. I reached out to them for various tips when I started running a year ago. From running I moved on to cycling and a bit of swimming after seeing my friend <a href="https://www.facebook.com/rahul.revikumar477977">Rahul</a>. For travel, my inspiration has been <a href="https://www.facebook.com/arun.sudheendran.1">Arun Sudheendran</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/deepak.suresh">Deepak Suresh</a> who do a fair bit of exploration. I tend to reach out to them for travel ideas and places to visit. Similarly, there have been inspirations from people that I have never met or met just once or twice.</p>

<p>Below is a transcript of a chat with one of my readers whom I have never met. It&rsquo;s a great feeling to wake up to such messages and it boosts your own motivation to continue what you are doing.</p>

<p><img src="/images/share_and_inspire_chat.png" alt="Share and Inspire" class="center"></p>

<p>Social media plays a great role in spreading information these days. When you see people in your own friend&rsquo;s circle start doing things that you have always wanted to, it gives you an extra push to give it a try. There might be some people who feel you are sharing too much of things that don&rsquo;t interest them. For those, there is always an option to un-follow, mute, filter etc. Don&rsquo;t let that thought stop you from sharing things that you do.</p>

<p>Such a small act of sharing, even things that you might have seen someone do could add up and be of big impact to someone else, often referred to as the <a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/TheButterflyEffectOfTechnologyCommunity.aspx">Butterfly Effect</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>The <strong>Butterfly Effect</strong>: This effect grants the power to cause a hurricane in China to a butterfly flapping its wings in New Mexico. It may take a very long time, but the connection is real. If the butterfly had not flapped its wings at just the right point in space/time, the hurricane would not have happened. - <a href="http://fractalfoundation.org/resources/what-is-chaos-theory/">Chaos Theory</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Share things that you do, share positive things and inspire others!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2017: What Went Well, What Didn't and Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" alt="Posts per month - 2016" src="/images/happy_new_year.png"/></p>

<p><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2016-recap/">A year</a> has gone by so fast, and it is again time to do a year review.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>TLDR;</strong></p>

<p>2017 was the transformation year. Regular exercise and healthy eating helped <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">loose around 20 kilos</a>. Lots of travel and blogging made it an excellent year. Reading, Photography and Open source did not go that great. Looking forward to 2018!</p></blockquote>

<h3>What went well</h3>

<h4><strong>Blogging</strong></h4>

<p>It has been both good and a bad year as far as this blog. Including the &lsquo;<a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/">Tip of the Week</a>&rsquo; series I wrote seventy-six posts this year with an average of over six posts per month. This is the good part, as it is well past the goal of a <em>minimum four posts a month</em> goal set last year. But looking at the actual posts per month graph below, it is clear that I have fallen short of it on an actual month by month basis. Up until August, I had a steady stream of posts coming in, from when it started dropping down, with even months (November) with no posts. Mainly it&rsquo;s my laziness to blame, but I can also tell reasons like Vietnam trip, Shifting to Brisbane, etc.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017_postpermonth.png" alt="Posts per month in the year 2017" /></p>

<h4><strong>Running</strong></h4>

<p>I had started running towards the end of December 2016. One of my goals for 2017 was running, and it has had a good improvement. Ran over 750 kilometers including a half marathon. I am yet to participate in any running events and am planning to in the coming year. I have also started cycling, and it is an excellent way to cross train.</p>

<p><a href="https://2017.strava.com/en-us/videos/92aff78b819c502351b85b8ef27e35025cd97adf/">
    <img src="/images/2017_sport.jpg" alt="Year in Sport" />
</a></p>

<h4><strong>Travel</strong></h4>

<p>Did our first international holiday to Vietnam for ten days and was a great experience. Also went around Australia visiting Blue Mountains, Canberra, Port Macquarie, Brisbane and lots of <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/one-day-trips-around-sydney/">one-day trips around Sydney</a>. Mandarin Picking, Strawberry picking and Whale watching were some of the top activities for the year.</p>

<p><img src="/images/strawberyy_picking.jpg" alt="Strawberry Picking, Ricardoes" /></p>

<h3>What didn&rsquo;t go well</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reading</strong> Had set out with a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/challenges/5493-2017-reading-challenge">goal of 21 books</a> but ended up finishing only ten books. Of the books I read liked <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mindset-Psychology-Carol-S-Dweck/dp/0345472322">Mindset</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People/dp/1439167346/">How to Win Friends and Influence People,</a> was the best.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Photography</strong>
One trip every three months and post photos were one another goal. The travel part went good (see above), but my DSLR always remained in the bag. Except for a few pictures on the phone camera, there was not much photography done.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>FSharp</strong>
FSharp was again on and off this year. Apart from a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-template-transformer-transform-tasks-to-x-days-from-now/">small utility that I created for Todoist</a>, I did not do much F# work.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Goals for 2018</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Blogging</strong> Stick to 4 posts a month. Need to get back on schedule.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Running</strong> Attend few running events. Run a marathon.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Swimming</strong> Having started cycling along with running, has got me thinking about a triathlon. The only thing between is swimming, and I have no clue how to swim. Learning to swim is one of the key goals for the upcoming year. Target is to be able to swim one km.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Open Source</strong> Start working on a side project. Need to find a matching project first.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reading</strong> Read 15 books</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Wishing you all a Happy and Prosperous New Year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Start New Habits That Stick]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/start_new_habits_that_stick/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/start_new_habits_that_stick</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><em>The beginning of a good habit is the elimination of an excuse.</em>   <br/>
<em>And The beginning of a bad habit is the finding of an excuse</em></p></blockquote>

<p>The ability to pick on something and to make a habit of it is something that is always helpful. This skill helps to create new habits and also let go off old ones that are not doing any good to you. Part of letting of bad old habits might be creating new ones. When I wrote about <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">Couch to Half Marathon</a>, some of my readers asked how to keep up with the plan. How to do &lsquo;Couch to Street&rsquo;; just getting out there.</p>

<p><a href= "https://quotefancy.com/quote/20375/Jim-Rohn-Motivation-is-what-gets-you-started-Habit-is-what-keeps-you-going">
    <img alt="Motivation is what gets you started. Habit is what keeps you going" src="/images/habit.jpg" class="center" />
</a></p>

<h3>How Habits Work</h3>

<p>To form new habits, it is important that we understand <a href="http://charlesduhigg.com/how-habits-work/">how habits work</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>a simple neurological loop at the core of every habit, a loop that consists of three parts: <strong>A cue, a routine and a reward.</strong></em></p></blockquote>

<p>As Charles Duhigg points out in his book, Power Of Habits (<a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc">recommended read</a>) the formula for changing habits differs from habit and persons. So it is more about using a framework to understand how habits work and experimenting on changing it. Changing a habit does take time and is not an easy one, but with a process in place, it is doable with time and effort.</p>

<p><img src="/images/habit_loop.jpg" class="center" alt="Cue-Routine-Reward Habit Loop" /></p>

<p>To break a bad habit one needs to identify it first. It could be anything from spending too much time on social media, eating unhealthy food, smoking, drinking, etc. Identifying that you have a habit and it&rsquo;s not good for you to continue with it is important. You can only change something once you identify it.</p>

<p>Once you recognize the habit, find out what is the trigger for the habit. Is it a particular place, people, time, etc. It might be hard to find the specific cue that triggers the habit, so note down everything that you find applicable. Then work on to isolate the cue by monitoring the habit over a couple of days. Wire up the cue that triggers the habit to perform some other action. Create that plan in advance and have some way to remind yourself of it. If your cue is time-based or location based, then you can use your smartphone to pop-up a reminder. If not try to find ways to keep yourself reminded to perform the new plan. It feels hard in the beginning but stick to the plan, and in time you will be able to change your habit. I recommend you to read the book <a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc">Power of Habits</a> to understand this subject better.</p>

<h3>Mini Habits and Short Term Goals</h3>

<p>To start creating new habits, I have found setting smaller goals to target daily works better. I began writing at least one line every day to be <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/">consistent in blogging</a>, running at least once a week to establish an exercise routine, eat at least one meal healthy, etc. Time-based cues help to enforce such new behavior. Setting aside a specific time as per the desired frequency to perform the activity makes sure that you do not skip doing it. Also, remember to keep the action as simple as possible so that you do not procrastinate when the time comes.</p>

<p>Like if it is running that you are planning to start it could be -  <em>Every Saturday at 6 am I will wear my running shoes and get out of my house</em>. When the time comes, this is such a simple task that you have set for yourself, and you are more likely to do it. Once you have taken the pain of putting the shoes and getting out of the couch, you are more likely to run for at least five minutes.</p>

<p>Break your goals into small and achievable mini goals. These mini goals are often referred to as <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Most Important Tasks (MIT)</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Big Rocks</a> etc. The key is to break them down into smaller achievable mini-goals and setting a cue to trigger the activity.</p>

<h3>Motivation and Its Role</h3>

<p>Very often we get motivated to start new activities and begin with great enthusiasm. In the beginning, we feel a spike in energy and see things happening. But soon you hit a point where you feel nothing is moving and you feel it a burden to continue. This stage is referred to as <em>plateau - a state of little or no change following a period of activity or progress.</em> You soon see your motivation levels dropping and justifying to yourself how little or no benefit your actions have. Eventually, you find yourself losing entire interest in the activity and start looking for new motivation spikes. This has happened to me many times.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Motivation is what gets you started.Habit is what keeps you going.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I have found this to be entirely true. We need the motivation to help us to get started with new activities and set new goals. But motivation alone cannot help us go all the way and achieve what we want. Before jump-starting with the idea give it a good thought to check if it is worth your time spent. If not park the idea to your <a href="http://gettingthingsdone.com/2010/10/what-goes-on-a-someday-maybe-list/">Someday Maybe list</a> (as referred to in <a href="http://amzn.to/2gsJaed">GTD</a>).</p>

<p>Once you have decided to pursue the idea, break it into smaller pieces and set achievable &lsquo;mini goals.&rsquo; Set dedicated time at regular intervals for achieving these mini-goals. Most important is in having some &lsquo;me time&rsquo; to get towards these goals. Like for me I have found that <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">mornings work best for me</a> and created a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Morning Routine</a>. To make sure that I make the best of my time I try to work in <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Pomodoro&rsquo;s and inspect and adapt the process</a> often.</p>

<h3>Tracking and Feedback</h3>

<p>Tracking is an important part of habit formation. Once you have set your goals and mini habits also find ways to track your progress. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/psm-learnings/">Inspect and Adapt</a> is the fundamental principle behind Agile Processes. Habit formation is nothing but being agile, keeping the end goal in mind, adjusting the way you reach there. Find ways and tools to track progress on the habits that you are trying to form.</p>

<p>I prefer automatic tracking with least manual entry, so the tracking happens in the background. But at times you will have to resort to manual methods as well. Make sure you have a time set aside daily to capture the information. Having a review of the data obtained once every week or two and taking adjustment actions is equally important. Some of the tracking tools that I use are <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/rescue-time-track-your-time/">Rescue Time</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">Garmin Forerunner 630</a> and a few manual ones. I [review my progress every week] and try to incorporate feedback into the upcoming week.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>All it takes to start a new habit is a moment - The moment where you decide on the new habit. The rest is process!</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">Eating Healthy, Exercise</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/">Blogging</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">Waking up Early</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Reducing time spent on Social Media, Reading</a> and <strike><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/recording-my-first-screencast/">Creating Videos</a></strike> (looking to give this up) are some of the habits that I have formed following these techniques. The ability to decide on something and getting it to done is the most important of all. Once you have mastered the skill of forming new habits, it boils down to choosing good habits and wiring that into your life. I have heard about the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jasonselk/2013/04/15/habit-formation-the-21-day-myth/">21-Day rule of habit formation</a> and similar myths. But I think all it takes to start a new habit is a moment - The moment where you decide on the new habit. The rest is process!</p>

<p><strong>References:</strong></p>

<div>
   <div class="row">
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
         <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc" >
            <img alt="Power Of Habit" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_powerofhabit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
         <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://amzn.to/2hmeokB">
            <img alt="Superhuman by Habit" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_superhumanbyhabit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;" >
            </a>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Went From Couch to Half Marathon in Twelve Weeks]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s about three months since I started running. I just completed my first half marathon and thought of putting together on how I have been going on with my running. I had a lot of questions myself when I started running, so hope this helps someone else taking the same journey.</p>

<div class="alert alert-warning">
<strong>DISCLAIMER!</strong> Just to make sure I get it right, I am not a doctor nor a professional runner. The below are just my personal experiences and has worked for me. If you feel you have a medical problem or are in need of professional help, please contact a professional. Always consult a doctor before starting a new diet or exercise program.
</div>


<h3>Tracking</h3>

<p>I started running using the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.runtastic.android&amp;hl=en">Runtastic</a> application on my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/">android phone</a>. The free version app offers most of the required features to start running. I upgraded to their <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/premium-membership">Premium version</a> primarily for <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/results">Runtastic Results</a>(more on it below).</p>

<p>Once I got regular with my runs I wanted better tracking, mainly to monitor heart rate. I was unsure of what a heart rate monitor would provide and if at all there is any value in getting one. I reached out to my runner friends, and all of them had one. Most of them had a Garmin, and a few had Fitbit. Until then I was planning to get the <a href="https://www.fitbit.com/au/charge2">Fitbit Charge 2</a> which comes with <a href="http://www.digitaltrends.com/wearables/whats-inside-fitness-tracker-anyway/#ixzz4cBARwI9q">optical heart rate monitoring</a>. It primarily uses an optical sensor and senses the heart rate from the wrist. The Garmin&rsquo;s make watches that are more <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-AU/AU/cIntoSports-cRunning-p1.html">specific for runners</a>, and since the majority of my friends owned Garmin, I decided on to get one of the Garmin Forerunner series.</p>

<p>One of the shops near to where I live was running a promotional offer on the <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-AU/AU/p/516105">Garmin Forerunner 630 Bundle</a>. But this model comes with a <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-AU/AU/p/530376">Heart Rate Monitor (HRM) Strap</a>. The strap needs to be worn around the chest during the run. Strap v Optical HRM added a new dimension of confusion to the whole tracker story. I reached out to my <a href="https://twitter.com/rahulpnath/status/835320810734694400">runner friends again</a> and surprisingly all of them had models of Garmin that uses an HRM Strap.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.wareable.com/garmin/garmin-forerunner-630-review">
<img alt="Garmin Forerunner 630 Bundle" class="center" src="/images/running_forerunner630.jpg" />
</a></p>

<p>The Garmin Forerunner 630 is a GPS SmartWatch with Advanced Running Metrics. It provides all the data a runner needs (and a lot more than what I need). Paired with HRM monitor it helps measure cadence, vertical oscillation and additional running dynamics like ground contact time balance, stride length and vertical ratio. I still don&rsquo;t understand all the data that it shows but find the GPS tracking, heart rate monitoring and zones, training plans and custom workouts a great help to my runs. Garmin also integrates well with <a href="https://www.strava.com/athletes/rahulpnath">Strava</a> where most of my other friends are there. The watch has a companion app on the phone and also a <a href="http://connect.garmin.com">website</a> which helps visualize the data.</p>

<h3>Exercise</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/results">Runtastic Results</a> provides a 12-week bodyweight training plan with the <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/premium-membership">premium subscription</a>. I am on week five of the training. It took a while for me to get started but now I try not to miss it. The free version of the app has all exercises available as stand-alone exercises. You can use these if you don&rsquo;t want to get the premium subscription.</p>

<p><img alt="Runtastic Results" class="center" src="/images/running_runtastic_results.png" /></p>

<p>I am following a diet to lose weight, and I weigh now 78 (±1) kilos and has been on that for around one month. I was around 95 when I started out with the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">running and diet</a>.</p>

<h3>Training</h3>

<p>During the first few weeks of running, I was mostly doing free runs and trying to cover the maximum distance possible. The tracked information was useful in isolation to a specific run, and I did not do anything to improve. I then started on a beginner training plan with Runtastic
to <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/users/4b76cfab-734e-1658-b5e4-600759a3b066/training-plans/747577">Run 50 min after 6 weeks</a>. This put me into the mode to compare my runs with the previous and work to improve on them. Now and then I wanted to stop the plan and continue with my normal run as I felt the plan wasn&rsquo;t working. But I decided to <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/psm-learnings/">stick to the process</a> until the end. On completion of the training, I was able to run continuously for fifty minutes, and that was a measurable improvement for me.</p>

<p><img alt="Runtastic Training Plan Certificate" src="/images/running_runtastic_certificate.png" /></p>

<p>My friend and colleague <a href="https://www.strava.com/athletes/12340841">Tony</a> is an avid runner. To improve on the pace, he advised starting shorter interval training. To improve pace, fix the pace to what you want to achieve and run for a specified interval (time or distance). Garmin enables you to create a custom workout setting various parameters on the run. The custom workout helps to keep up with your goals during the run.</p>

<p><img alt="Garmin Custom Workout" class="center" src="/images/running_garmin_workout.jpg" /></p>

<p>Running at a constant pace is important to help cover longer distances. Initially, I used to run with all my energy. So my pace often spiked and then fell and then spiked again. If you are training to improve your speed, it&rsquo;s hard to tell whether there is an improvement in speed unless you run at a constant (little variation) in speed. Check out the graph that plots your pace to check the pace variations. Most running applications show this information.</p>

<h3>Breathing</h3>

<p>Proper breathing is one the key things with running. I did not give much importance to breathing at first. I found it very hard to run long distances without stopping in between by following a random breathing pattern. There are different suggestions on breathing style. I found the article <a href="http://www.runnersworld.com/running-tips/running-on-air-breathing-technique">Running On Air: Breathing Technique</a> helpful and try to follow the pattern mentioned there (quoted below).</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The singular point of all rhythmic breathing patterns is this: Exhale on alternate footstrikes as you run. You never want to continually exhale on the same foot. The rhythmic breathing patterns I recommend call for a longer inhale than exhale. Why the longer inhale? Your diaphragm and other breathing muscles contract during inhalation, which brings stability to your core. These same muscles relax during exhalation, decreasing stability. With the goal of injury prevention in mind, it&rsquo;s best to hit the ground more often when your body is at its most stable—during inhalation. Let&rsquo;s start with a 5-count or 3:2 pattern of rhythmic breathing, which will apply to most of your running. Inhale for three steps and exhale for two.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I particularly liked the reference to yoga and meditation in the article. It gave the realization that running is a form of meditation. Establishing a breathing rhythm helped me run longer distances comfortably and without losing breath. If you want to get a deeper understanding of breath and how it affects our life I recommend reading the book <a href="http://amzn.to/2nkIlUQ">Science Of Breath</a>.</p>

<p>I ran my first <a href="https://www.runtastic.com/en/users/4b76cfab-734e-1658-b5e4-600759a3b066/sport-sessions/58d587fdd03a4c443e6d656c">Half Marathon</a> on 25th of March. I did at a casual pace to understand what it takes to run one. I tried to keep my pace between 6:15 - 6:30 min/km and was able to finish it at 6:19 min/km. It took me 2:13:11 hours and I am glad that I did not stop even once. It was more a mental game to stay at it than anything physical, and I am happy that I could finish it successfully! Hope this helps someone else as well starting off with running. Sound off in the comments if this helps you or some tips if you are already a runner!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Problems with Known Exceptions and Ignoring It]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/the-problems-with-known-exception-and-ignoring-it/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/the-problems-with-known-exception-and-ignoring-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;<em>Oh yes! That is an expected error. It is because…</em>&rdquo;.</p>

<p>How many times have you given that explanation yourself or heard the other developer tell that? Known errors or exceptions are common in applications and us developers find ways to live with such errors. At times when the number of such errors grows it becomes a problem directly or indirectly to the business. These known errors could either be exceptions in application logs, failed messages (commands/events) in a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Event-driven_architecture">message based architecture</a>, alert popups in Windows client applications, etc.</p>

<p><img alt="Known Errors" src="/images/known_errors.png" /></p>

<p>We should try and keep known errors and exception count close to zero. Below are some of the problems that can happen by ignoring it over a period.</p>

<h4><strong>Business Value</strong></h4>

<p>Since the errors are known to us, we train ourselves or even the users to ignore them. It is easy to justify that fixing them does not have any business value as there is no direct impact. This assumption need not be true. If a piece of code has no value then why is it there in the first place? Possibly it is not having any visible effects at present but might be having an impact at a later point in time. It could also be that it is not affecting the data consistency of your system, but is a problem for an external system. There can be business flows that are written at a later point of time not being aware of this known error. Some developer time gets lost when glancing over such errors or messages in the log which directly equates to money for the business.</p>

<h4><strong>Important Errors Missed</strong></h4>

<p>If there are a lot of such known errors, it is easy for new or important ones to get missed or ignored. Depending on the frequency of the known error, it can end up flooding the logs. The logs start to get overwhelming to monitor or trace for other issues with lots of such known errors. The natural tendency for people when they find something overwhelming is to ignore it. I worked on a system which had over 250 failed messages coming to the error queue daily. It was overwhelming to monitor them and was soon getting ignored. Important errors were getting missed and often ended up as support requests for the application. Such errors otherwise could have been proactively handled, giving the end user more confidence.</p>

<h4><strong>Lower Perceived Stability</strong></h4>

<p>The overall perceived stability of the system comes down as more and more such errors happen. It is applicable both for the users and developers. When errors no longer get monitored or tracked, critical errors gets ignored. Users have to resort to other means like support requests for the errors they face. For users who are new to the system, it might take a while to get used to the known errors. These errors decrease the trust they have in the system and soon starts suspecting everything as an issue or a problem.</p>

<p>Seeing more and more of such errors does not leave a positive impact on the developers. It&rsquo;s possible that developers loose interest to work on an unstable system and start looking for a change. It is also a challenge when new members join the team. It takes time for them to get used to errors and exceptions and to learn to ignore them.</p>

<h4><strong>Stereotyping Exceptions</strong></h4>

<p>Errors of a particular type can get stereotyped together, and get ignored mistaking it for one that is already known. It is easy for different &lsquo;<em>object null reference exception</em>&rsquo; error messages to be treated as a particular error whereas it could be failing for various reasons. At one of my clients, we had a specific message type failing with the null reference error. We had identified the reason for one such message and found that it is not causing &lsquo;<em>any direct business impact</em>&rsquo; and can be ignored. The message was failing as one of the properties on the message was alphanumeric while the code expected numeric. The simple fix in the code would be to validate it, but since this was not causing any business impact it was ignored, and messages of that type kept piling up. Until later where we found that there were other message formats of the same message type failing which was for a different reason. And those messages were causing a loss of revenue to the business. But since we were stereotyping the error messages of the particular type to the one that we found invalid and not having a business impact all of such messages were ignored. The stereotyping resulted in the important message getting ignored.</p>

<h4><strong>Maintaining a Known Bugs Database</strong></h4>

<p>When having a large number of such errors, it is important to document a list of such errors.It forces us to a new document and also comes with the responsibility of maintaining it. For any new developers or users joining the system, they need to go through the documentation to verify if it is a known error or not. Internalizing these errors might take some time, and critical errors can get missed during this time. Any such document needs to be kept current and up to date as and when new errors are found or more details found for older ones. This is not the best of places where a developers time is spent.</p>

<h4><strong>Count Keeps Increasing</strong></h4>

<p>If the count of such errors is not monitored and not valued for the probability of the number of error messages increasing is higher. New errors getting introduced will not be noticed, and even when noticed it becomes acceptable. <em>We already have a lot of them, so it is fine.</em> It sets a wrong goal for the team and can soon become unmanageable.</p>

<h4><strong>New Business Flow Assuming Exception</strong>s</h4>

<p>Since the exceptions are so used to, it is highly possible that we set that as an expectation. New business flows come up expecting a certain kind of exception to be thrown or assuming a particular type of message will not get processed. Since we are so used to the fact that it happens, we take it for granted and start coding against it. It might be the last thing that happens on a project, but believe me, it happens!. Such code becomes harder to maintain and might not work once the actual exception gets fixed.</p>

<p>Ignoring exceptions and getting around to live with it can be more costly over a longer period. The further we delay action on such errors the higher the cost involved. Even though there is no immediate or direct business value seen from fixing such errors, we saw that on a longer run it could have a great impact. So try not to live with such errors but instead prioritize them with the work your team is doing and get it fixed. A fix might not always be an extra null check or a conditional to avoid the error. It might seem the easier approach to reducing the errors but will soon become a different problem. Understand the business and explore into what is causing the error. Do you have any known exceptions in the application you are working? What are you doing about it?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
