<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-28T05:17:06+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developer Learnings from the IKEA Experience]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/developer-learnings-from-the-ikea-experience/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-16T05:44:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/developer-learnings-from-the-ikea-experience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When we moved over to Sydney, last year, we had to start over with all the home furnishings. Since we were just starting out, didn&rsquo;t want to spent a lot on furnishings, so decided to go with <a href="http://www.ikea.com/au/en/?cid=au|ps|branded|brand|google|ikea_australia">IKEA</a> for its cost effectiveness and value for money.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>IKEA is a multinational group of companies that designs and sells ready-to-assemble furniture (such as beds, chairs and desks), appliances, small motor vehicles and home accessories. <span class="right">Wiki</span></em></p></blockquote>

<p>Right from the in-shop experience to setting it up, I found many similarities with the IKEA experience and Software Development. Visiting IKEA is an experience in itself and totally wow&rsquo;s you. If not for any of the displayed items, the &lsquo;<em>Self Serve Furniture Area</em>&rsquo; surely will. The sheer size and setup there was breath-taking for me and my wife!</p>

<p><figure>
    <img alt="IKEA Self Serve Furniture Area, Ikea Tempe" src="/images/ikea_self_serve_furniture_area.jpg" />
    <figcaption><em>This is just one of the aisle and there were around 35 of them!</em></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<h3>Code Management &amp; Inventory Management</h3>

<p>Throughout the <a href="https://shoutsfromtheabyss.files.wordpress.com/2013/06/ikea-map.jpg">Showroom</a> you see an <em>Aisle number</em> and the <em>Location</em> displayed under the displayed items. For the items interested in, one can note those numbers on paper or use the mobile application to <a href="http://www.ikea.com/ms/en_KR/customer-service/apps/mobile_app_14.html">scan the QR code of the product</a> for reference. In the checkout area, you can find the item at the said aisle/location number. Finding and picking up the item from the aisle is easy and joyful.</p>

<p>Code management is an important aspect in Software development, as code bases can get quite large. Setting up a <a href="https://github.com/">version control</a> to manage code bases have become a norm and is a good practice to follow even on your side projects. Few other things to follow include</p>

<ul>
<li>Maintain a project structure, naming conventions and code conventions.</li>
<li>Code Navigability and discoverability are important for fast and smooth development. Good and descriptive class names allow us to navigate easily based on the application functionality.</li>
<li><a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/893ke618(v=vs.71).aspx">Organizing Namespace</a></li>
<li>Remove unused code and not comment it out. Let the version control system take care of file history.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Manual</h3>

<p>The assembly instructions that comes with each package is clear and expressive. It&rsquo;s mostly <a href="http://www.ikea.com/au/en/assembly_instructions/malm-desk__AA-516949-7_pub.pdf">conveyed through pictures</a> and easy to follow through. The manual is up to date with the packaged product and matched exactly with the contents.</p>

<p>This shows the importance of having a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/README">README</a> file or software manuals or in context help for users to use the application. Feedback messages and keeping the user always connected with the system is also important. Long wait times, unresponsive progress bars, silent suppression of error messages are not acceptable. Error messages are for the application user and the level and kind of details differs based on who the user is:</p>

<ul>
<li>For business/non-technical users, mostly of Front-end applications, Business error messages makes more value than technical errors</li>
<li>For developers consuming an API, detailed technical error messages add value than just returning a &lsquo;500 - Internal Server Error&rsquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>Error messages must be relevant and up to date with the current functionality. Always review messages for appropriateness.</p>

<p>Code comments used for communicating intent mostly gets out of sync with what the code actually does. So it&rsquo;s a better practice to avoid comments in code and break code into descriptive function and classes to convey the intent.</p>

<blockquote><p><em><a href="http://butunclebob.com/ArticleS.TimOttinger.ApologizeIncode">A comment is an apology</a> for not choosing a more clear name or a more reasonable set of parameters, or for the failure to use explanatory variables and explanatory functions.</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>Tools</h3>

<p><img class="left" alt="IKEA Tools" src="/images/ikea_tools.jpg" /></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.ikea.com/us/en/catalog/products/00169254/">FIXA 17-piece tool kit</a>, is all that you need for fitting all the furniture. Some products have an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hex_key">Allen Key</a> packaged along with them, but otherwise, most of the time the FIXA toolkit is all that one needs.</p>

<p>Having the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tools-that-I-use/">right set of tools</a> for assisting in the development and being familiar with it is important.  It&rsquo;s not just about having the best/costliest tools, but about knowing them well. Taking some time out to understand the tools that you use daily is important. By tools, I include keyboard, mouse, programming languages, IDE&rsquo;s and other support software that you use daily.</p>

<div style="clear: both;"></div>


<blockquote><p><em><a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/we-are-typists-first-programmers-second/">We are Typists First, Programmers Second</a>: The keyboard is one of the most important tools for a developer - learn it well</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>Componentization</h3>

<p>The furniture comes as separate pieces that can be easily assembled, with all the screw holes of perfect size. All the different pieces fit perfectly and right even when done by an amateur. Though some of the pieces required two people to fix, I could fix them up myself. It was all cut to perfection with all the holes right in place and fits perfectly the first time.</p>

<p>Having well-defined interfaces that interact with each other seamlessly is important in software development. Any application should be composed of smaller parts that can fit together well. Adhering to good design principles and design patterns helps us to achieve this.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>One of the most important principles while using Object Oriented  languages is <strong><a href="http://butunclebob.com/ArticleS.UncleBob.PrinciplesOfOod">SOLID</a></strong>:   <br/>
  Single Responsibility, Open-Closed, Liskov Substitution, Interface segregation and Dependency Injection</em></p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" alt="IKEA Components" src="/images/ikea_components.jpg" /></p>

<p>Interfaces should be well-defined and not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leaky_abstraction">leak abstractions</a>. The name and parameters(input/return) should completely abstract the &lsquo;how&rsquo; part of the functionality and expose only the &lsquo;what&rsquo;. This helps to build more robust interfaces.</p>

<h3>Packaging and Shipping</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.wsj.com/articles/ikea-cant-stop-obsessing-about-its-packaging-1434533401">IKEA&rsquo;s efficiency in packaging</a> is one of the reasons that enables them to sell at a low-cost and they keep improving at it. Compact and small packages make it easy to handle right from &lsquo;self-checkout&rsquo; to unpacking it at your home. It also helps in optimizing transportation costs for IKEA which in turn enables them to reduce prices.</p>

<p><figure>
    <img alt="IKEA Packaging" src="/images/ikea_packed.jpg"></img>
    <figcaption><em>King size bed frame with storage, extendable dining table and four chairs!</em></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Deployment in software development is a key part and having the entire pipeline automated is essential for a smooth delivery. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/automated-clickonce-deployment-of-a-wpf-application-using-appveyor/">Setting up a build server, automated building, running tests</a> etc are some of the starting points to move towards <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/ContinuousDelivery.html">Continuous Delivery</a>. Deployment needs to be scripted and be possible to deploy to any environment at the click of a button. If it is a distributable software then easily accessible delivery mechanisms should be available and preferably offer multiple options (like distributable media, server hosted images etc like Windows)</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The package has just the right number of screws, nails and other assembly accessories - not one less, not one more!</em></p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" alt="IKEA Components" src="/images/ikea_assembly_accessories.jpg" /></p>

<p>This shows IKEA&rsquo;s confidence in the shipped product and the self-belief of nothing going wrong. For a software product to be shipped with this level of confidence it should be thoroughly tested - preferably automated, which allows verifying each time we make a release and allows us to release more often.</p>

<h3>Cost Effective</h3>

<p>Having always bought pre-assembled furniture I have never had to think about anything - it was always just about the money. But with IKEA being self-assembled, you get the flexibility to choose the components/features that you need for the furniture like you could choose to have a <a href="http://www.ikea.com/au/en/catalog/products/20228714/">headboard for the bed</a> or not, which obviously implies a reduced price. You could choose to self-checkout and pay nothing, but also do a paid checkout, where an IKEA member would get all the items out for you to the billing counter. You could transport it yourself to your home or <a href="http://www.ikea.com/ms/en_AU/customer_service/ikea_services/home_delivery.html">get it delivered</a>. So it&rsquo;s all about giving you the options to choose what you want and really keep the cost low.</p>

<p>Keeping the cost low is an important aspect in software industry too and at various levels</p>

<ul>
<li>Development and Licensing  costs - Try to keep these costs low, by looking for open source alternatives and choosing your technology wisely and not just looking for the &lsquo;cool and latest&rsquo;.</li>
<li>Deployment/Infrastructure costs - Build applications for scale and as independent services so that they can be  turned on and off  as required. <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/">The cloud</a> has greatly reduced the infrastructure setup costs and provides an easy way for setup. Make sure you understand well the pricing models offered by various cloud providers.</li>
<li>Software Costs/Subscription Costs: Give flexibility to your consumers in how they can consume your software. Keeping functionality loosely coupled and pluggable allows to offer various subscription plans or selling model.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Value Added Services</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s not just in the home furnishings and their core business that IKEA has taken great care for. The other <a href="http://www.ikea.com/ms/en_SG/service-offer/">Value Added Services</a> they offer like Delivery, Assembly, Planning Tools, Gift Cards, Children&rsquo;s Services and Return Policy are top-notch.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Users are happy when the expected works, and wowed when it goes beyond expectations.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>The <a href="http://www.ikea.com/au/en/catalog/categories/departments/food/">food at IKEA</a> is worth mentioning (and a picture) - low-priced and tasty! It caters for the needs of all kinds of people and age. The value for money attracts people to IKEA just for the food.</p>

<p><img alt="IKEA Components" src="/images/ikea_food.jpg" /></p>

<p>Any product should deliver what it&rsquo;s supposed to anyways, but it&rsquo;s in providing a bit extra that really matters. Like the few examples below,that gave a better experience to me</p>

<ul>
<li>When you hit Ctrl + V with an image in clipboard on Facebook it automatically uploads the image</li>
<li>When Amazon sent a replacement for my broken Kindle (all the way from the US to India) for free</li>
<li>When Google Now showed the <a href="https://support.google.com/websearch/answer/6015842?hl=en">parking location</a>.</li>
<li>The IKEA Experience!</li>
</ul>


<p>Strive to look for cases where you can delight your customers every time you deliver a product. The IKEA has made me think about delivering products and the need for constantly improving at it. We often need to take a stop, look at what we are doing and correct things and move forward.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The only way to make the deadline—the only way to go fast—is to keep the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0132350882/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0132350882&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-20&amp;linkId=CVCVZFAR5SBYVMJW">code as clean</a> as possible at all times.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Head off to an IKEA store if there is one <a href="http://www.ikea.com/">near you</a> and get wowed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started With Freelancing Jobs Online]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-freelancing-jobs-online/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-01T11:57:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/getting-started-with-freelancing-jobs-online</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Freelancing is a good way to learn new technology, get some hands on experience and not getting limited to the technology stack at your full-time job and of course earn some extra money!. There is a great demand for developers out there, so if its &lsquo;legal&rsquo; (check with your employer, if you already have another full-time job) for you to freelance then give it a try. There are a lot of online freelance platforms(<a href="https://www.upwork.com/">Upwork</a>, <a href="https://www.freelancer.com/">Freelancer</a>) that connects businesses and developers remotely. These platforms enable you as a developer, to start a profile and bid for jobs of your interest. If the business/client finds you as a match for the job, then you get signed up and can start working immediately.</p>

<p>Easy right! Yes absolutely it is, but here are a few things that might help you through the journey, that I have learned from my experiences.</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Freelancer" src="/images/freelancing.jpg" /></p>

<h3><strong>Finding work</strong></h3>

<p>Finding work is just an easy search across on the platforms with your preferred skills. It will be a good idea to stick to one of the platforms so that you can build up a profile and then move on to other platforms. Landing your first job as a freelancer could be tricky as clients have a tendency to look for people with some work record on the platform, which assures them that it is a &lsquo;real human&rsquo; that they are talking to. But this is kind of &lsquo;chicken and egg problem&rsquo;. One of the best way to break into your first job is to sell yourself low - Yes, you heard it right - Really low!</p>

<p>While I started on with the idea of freelancing, I took on it with the perspective of that of an experienced developer(as I had a full-time job, which was paying me decently well). I bid on all projects with a relatively higher amount or at par to that my current job was paying, until I received back the below email from one of the clients.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>You lack test scores, have a small portfolio, and have no <a href="https://www.upwork.com">Odesk</a> history. You should try to underbid and get jobs when you are building up odesk history, get good feedback and then raise your rates later.I see you have good qualifications and don&rsquo;t mean you are not worth what you charge, this is just a way to get more clients in the beginning</em></p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s not always that you get a reply like this and it was an eye-opener for me. So to get the ball rolling, I tried bidding low on a couple of bug fix project which was about 1-2 hours work. Luckily I got one of the jobs and from then followed the exact feedback that I got back - Slowly increase rates and build profile.When bidding lower always make sure that you do on projects of smaller size, so that you don&rsquo;t feel really bad selling yourself low midway through the project (you could always renegotiate, but it might affect the feedback).</p>

<h3><strong>Bidding</strong></h3>

<p>Bidding is an important part of the freelancing cycle. Make sure you put in as much details to put across that you are an ideal candidate. It&rsquo;s where your skills to sell yourself come into play. Make sure you convey through the reasons on the &lsquo;Why&rsquo;,&lsquo;What&rsquo; and &lsquo;How&rsquo; in your bid cover letter.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Approach bidding the same way you would attend an interview with a prospective employer.</em></p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Why</strong> you are interested in the project</li>
<li><strong>What</strong> makes you a good candidate and your experiences. It will be good to have some references to existing projects/applications/blogs to back your claims.</li>
<li><strong>How</strong> you would approach the problem at hand and some questions probing more details.</li>
</ul>


<p>Many a times we have a tendency to copy paste bid cover letters and clients might look for specific references to their project. There are also clients who ask to start/end the bid with specific words or phrases just to make sure you have at least read through the job description.</p>

<h3><strong>Communication</strong></h3>

<p>Communication is the key when working remotely. Keeping your clients/stakeholders up to date on what&rsquo;s happening in the project, calling out any risks associated and clarifying on any issues should be done promptly. Your bid cover letter is the first impression that you leave on the client on your communications skills. So that makes it an added reason to give enough time while sending out your bid.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Missing a deadline is not really a problem, but not communicating it up front is.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good idea to set a rhythm to your updates and also sticking on to an update format, so that client knows how and when to expect for things. This will also allow them to plan for work. If working on hourly jobs, it would also be a good idea to set up repositories to share code or other artifacts that you are working on. <a href="https://github.com">Github</a> (paid for private repositories), <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-team-services-vs.aspx">Visual Studio Online</a> (VSO) or <a href="https://bitbucket.org">Bitbuket</a> (free with limits for private repositories) are good providers that you can use. Using <a href="https://trello.com">Trello</a> boards or <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-team-services-vs.aspx">VSO</a> for managing work/tasks will give enough visibility to clients on the current status at any point in time.</p>

<h3><strong>Hourly vs Fixed Price</strong></h3>

<p>When starting out it might be a good idea to start with an hourly project, so that you get introduced to various aspects of freelancing and get used to it. Once comfortable with the overall life cycle you can try fixed price projects. The challenge with fixed price projects, is in getting the scope fixed and making sure that you have accounted for all possible work. Also in tactfully raising cost variations when the client changes from agreed scope or when you discover work that you had not estimated for. Having cost change costs quite often does not put across a good message, so do that wisely and only when absolutely required. Even on hourly projects, there is nothing wrong in negotiating with the per-hour rate, especially if the project is a long running one.</p>

<p>Understand how the payment terms and conditions associated with the platform works. Some platforms have the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Escrow">escrow</a> model, so the risk of loosing out on money is less. For hourly projects, some platforms have tools that automatically track the amount of time you work on a project and directly bill the clients card once in a week/month, in which case you are sure to receive the payment (unless the client raises a conflict). For cases where none of the above applies, make sure that you have payment milestones set at different phases of the project and you share the code/working product only once you receive payments for milestones. Sharing videos, pictures, live remote sessions could be some alternatives to prove milestone criteria.</p>

<h3><strong>Branding</strong></h3>

<p>Proving your metal is tough if you are just starting out freelancing. Having some experiences to show case is valuable when bidding for projects. When I started off freelancing, my intention was to learn Windows Phone and Windows 8 Modern application development. Since the platform was relatively new then, I started off with a side project <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/store/apps/picfinity/9wzdncrdwxx8">Picfinity</a>, to showcase my capabilities. Building the application also helped me generate a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/tag/500px/">few blog posts</a> around these areas and I used both of above to showcase my ability to build applications for the Windows platform. This also helped me increase my hourly rates at a faster pace.
Branding is an ongoing effort that you need to do when freelancing, which indirectly enables you to increase your rates over time. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/">Writing blogs</a>, creating reusable libraries, contributing on forums, etc. are some of the things that help with this.</p>

<p>From the experiences gained from these freelancing platforms you will soon be able to move to consulting on your own or join premium freelancing platforms like <a href="www.toptal.com">Toptal</a>, <a href="http://x-team.com/">Xteam</a>, etc. You could also stick on with these platforms and learn new technologies while getting paid. At the very least I see that it has helped me generate content for my blogs (as I still struggle with topics to blog about).</p>

<p>Hope this helps you to get started with freelancing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Language Agnostic Books For Every Developer 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/language-agnostic-books-for-every-developer-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-02T22:51:03+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/language-agnostic-books-for-every-developer-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exactly a year back I had <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/language-agnostic-books-for-every-developer/">written about the same topic</a>, and over the time I have picked up a few more books, that I am sharing here. Like the earlier post I will let the books do the talking.</p>

<p><div>
      <div class="row">
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0131495054/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0131495054&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=XR55UAOEPPMVMFK3">
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_xunit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;" >
             </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>xUnit Test Patterns : Refactoring Test Code</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
       <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
          <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321503627/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321503627&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=TR6UCCVP6CMGBBZQ" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_goos.jpeg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Growing Object-Oriented Software, Guided by Tests</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0132350882/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0132350882&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=CVCVZFAR5SBYVMJW" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_cleancode.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Clean Code: A Handbook of Agile Software Craftsmanship</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
     <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0978739213/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0978739213&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=OYRDBB5TR4VHBK6L" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_releaseit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Release It!: Design and Deploy Production-Ready Software</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      <div class="row">
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321200683/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321200683&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=IQV6RX4M6RXKG4O2" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_eip.gif" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Enterprise Integration Patterns: Designing, Building, and Deploying Messaging Solutions</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0201633612/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0201633612&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=JBBJOO5EP4GLYIXG" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_designpatterns.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Design Patterns: Elements of Reusable Object-Oriented Software</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0131177052/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0131177052&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=TTKEEYQLEMTOXPPQ" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_welc.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Working Effectively with Legacy Code</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
    <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321545613/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321545613&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=UZC2I2HABQUNCT2U" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_frameworkdesign.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Framework Design Guidelines: Conventions, Idioms, and Patterns for Reusable .NET Libraries</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div></p>

<p>Have a great year ahead and some good reading.</p>

<p><em>* The links are Amazon Affiliate Links!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Language Agnostic Books For Every Developer]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/language-agnostic-books-for-every-developer/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T00:03:14+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/language-agnostic-books-for-every-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reading is inevitable to keep up to date with the latest technologies and rapid changes happening in the programming world. But technology is nothing but a tool for getting things done. What one has to understand are the concepts and principles underlying these technology and the core principles of development. These are to be gained through <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/an-enterprise-it-project-experience/">our own experiences</a> and also from the learnings and the experiences of others. Books are a great source of such experiences, and this post is a list of those that I have found interesting and helpful. I have not read all these nor was I able to fully understand whatever I have. These books are to be read/referred to multiple times, practiced and adopted into our work. It&rsquo;s also worth referring other books from the same author&rsquo;s or other writings as they are among the pioneers in our industry.</p>

<p>The books would speak for themselves and I don&rsquo;t think I can do justice writing a summary to any of these. So I have decided to just list them down here(in no specific order). It&rsquo;s worth having a personal copy of each one of these in your bookshelves. (mine is still short of some of them).</p>

<p><div>
      <div class="row">
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0735619670/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0735619670&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=6EBVFQ44LVCQC3VW">
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_codecomplete.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;" >
             </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Code Complete</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
       <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
          <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321146530/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321146530&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=UFKBUSTB43PNRS76" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_tdd.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Test Driven Development</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0131489062/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0131489062&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=2IKSKNFHUIXAC3V4" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_applyinguml.jpeg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Applying UML and Patterns</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
     <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321125215/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321125215&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=LGNNMURUNPIQJ22Q" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_ddd.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Domain Driven Design</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      <div class="row">
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0596805829/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0596805829&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=BAC6OAIRWSGB4ZBB" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_restinpractice.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Rest in Practice</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/020161622X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=020161622X&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=I6W7QKVDPXSBR37P" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_pragmaticprogrammer.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>The Pragmatic Programmer</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0201485672/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0201485672&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=VPJIMQDT3AENNVY6" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_refactoring.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Refactoring</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
    <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321193687/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321193687&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=HXUV2APJ7YOHRIZY" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_umldistilled.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>UML Distilled</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div class="row">   <br/>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0201835959/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0201835959&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=HKH5I6Q3Y6IYSCI5" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_mythicalmanmonth.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>The Mythical Man-Month</strong></h5>         <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0262510871/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0262510871&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=7YASXOZAUG7JDUDI" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_sicp.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
             </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Structure and Interpretaion of Computer Programs</strong></h5>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
       <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
           <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0131857258/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0131857258&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=SQ27A44S24WSXQK4" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_agilepatterns.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
           </a>
           <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Agile Principles, Patterns and Practices</strong></h5>      <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
          <div class="thumbnail">
         <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321127420/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0321127420&linkCode=as2&tag=rahulpnath-20&linkId=UR5IBEFV64BK5FYG" >
            <img src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_poeaa.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
          </a>
            <div class="caption">
              <h5><strong>Patterns of Enterprise Application and Architecture</strong></h5>          <br/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>    <br/>
      </div></p>

<p>Hope you start of this year off with some nice readings and gift yourself with some these master pieces. I am sure that I have not covered all of them and there are still more to be &lsquo;chewed and digested&rsquo;. Do drop in with a comment on Which books have helped you be better in programming.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get started with your blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T23:31:58+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/get-started-with-your-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are a programmer and don’t have a blog, then there is no better time than now to start one. <a href="http://channel9.msdn.com/Shows/HanselminutesOn9/Hanselminutes-on-9-Social-Networking-for-Developers-Part-1-Every-Developer-Needs-a-Blog">Every developer should have a blog</a>, for a very simple reason – <strong>Otherwise all your work is just going wasted!.</strong> I can bet that the best of your code or ideas would either be in some old email that you hardly have access to or archived or in some backup hard-disk waiting to be formatted or already formatted and all gone. All the thought, research and creativity that you would have spent would be lying just wasted and with little or no use. Having an online presence has really become a necessity in today&rsquo;s connected world, and a blog is the best place to show your presence. I started off answering <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count/">mdsn forums</a> and then figured that most of the people had similar questions and I was giving the same answers many a times, which gave me the thought of blogging answers and posting links to them. So anytime someone asks you something or you do something awesome blog it, so that your work does not get wasted and more people would find it useful. As with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rule_of_three_(computer_programming">rule of three</a>) for refactoring, with blogging it’s just rule of one – <em><strong>blog it always </strong>(</em>even this blog is because some one asked me after I recently moved on to a self hosted blog<em>).</em>
I have had a taste of blogspot and WordPress blog web hosting service,  before moving on to a self-hosted blog here. I think you would have guessed which one I would suggest you to get if you are starting your blog – a self hosted one. Indeed there is some effort that goes in to maintain the blog, but its worth every effort that you put.</p>

<p>I use WordPress as the blogging software and am running it on a Linux server (had to change over from windows, as there were a lot of compatibility issues that I faced). WordPress is a very popular blogging engine and so has an immense collection of themes, plug-in and add-on that are available to enhance yours and your readers experience. Once you get your wordpress installed on your self hosted domain, which should be as easy as clicking a button, install the below plugin’s.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>The first thing would be to <strong>connect with </strong><a href="http://jetpack.me/"><strong>jetpack</strong></a>. This would give you a lot of features including stats, social integration, publicize options and many more.</p></li>
<li><p>Connect with <a href="http://akismet.com/"><strong>akismet</strong></a> using the <a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/akismet/">plug-in</a> for preventing/moderating spam comments. Akismet provides a free subscription for personal users.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://feedburner.google.com/"><strong>Claim your feed</strong></a> and put it on your blog. You can again use a <a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/feedburner-form/">feedburner-form</a> if you want.</p></li>
<li><p>Integrate with<strong> </strong><a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/"><strong>Google analytics</strong></a>, if you want more detailed statistics than the one provided with jetpack. Once you get your code, you can use the <a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/googleanalytics/">plug-in</a> to integrate with your site. This will add the necessary code in all your pages header.</p></li>
<li><p>Make sure you have a <strong>backup plan</strong>, as you would not want all your data to vanish off if something happens with the hosting server. You could either use vaultpress or use freely available plug-in to back up to popular cloud storage like Dropbox, Skydrive or Google drive.</p></li>
<li><p>Get a <strong>good theme</strong> for your blog, there a lot of free and paid ones out there.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Now that you have most of the things setup, it’s time for you to put up your first page, <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/about/">About me</a>. This is very important as it gives a sense of credibility to your readers, so make sure you have one. For creating content on to your blog, you can either use the online editor or use some offline editor. Personally I use <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/en-in/download/details.aspx?id=8621">Windows live writer</a>. I love using this and all my blogs are written using this. The one plug-in that you would want to get, if you are a developer is <a href="http://precode.codeplex.com/">PreCode</a>, which makes inserting code really easy.
There are a lot more things that your blog would need, you would soon find that out and when you do, please leave a note of it in the comments section below. Happy Blogging!</p>

<p><strong>Edit</strong>: Couple of people were asking about getting started with a free blog. <a href="http://wordpress.com/">Wordpress.com</a> or <a href="https://www.tumblr.com/">Tumblr</a> would be a very good option to start with. Personally I used Wordpress as I felt that better. The advantage with tumblr over wordpress is that you can <a href="http://www.tumblr.com/docs/en/custom_domains">link your custom domain name with tumblr for free</a> while <a href="http://en.support.wordpress.com/domains/map-existing-domain/">worpress charges for linking a custom domain</a>. (You would need to pay for the custom domain in either cases). But then I ended up hosting all myself after moving away from Wordpress.com.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
