<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-01T00:02:55+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2018: What Went Well, What Didn't and Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/2018-recap/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/2018-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" alt="Posts per month - 2016" src="/images/happy_new_year.png"/></p>

<p><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap/">Another year</a> has gone by so fast, and it is again time to do a year review.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>TLDR;</strong></p>

<p>2018 saw most of my time in running, cycling and learning to swim. Regular exercise and healthy eating helped <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">maintain my weight</a>. Lots of travel added to the excitement. Blogging, Reading, Photography and Open source took the back seat and did not go as planned.
Looking forward to 2019!</p></blockquote>

<h3>What went well</h3>

<h4><strong>Running, Cycling and Learning to Swim</strong></h4>

<p>As planned last year I did two half marathon events - <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/1495400703">Brisbane Great South Run</a> and <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/1628202657">Springfield Half Marathon</a>. I could also do a <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/1756881573/overview">Sub 50 10k</a> run after many tries. Even though running a marathon was part of one of the goals it did not happen. Cycling was on and off, and towards the year end, I started commuting to work (around 10k one way). However, it lasted only around 2 months as I changed client, for which I had to commute to Gold Coast (around 70km, once a week). With swimming, I still struggle to do more than two laps at a stretch. The goal was to swim 1km by the end of 2018 but looks like that&rsquo;s a long way to go. I was often lazy and not motivated to go out to the pool to practice.</p>

<p>I can spend all this time on these activities because of the full support from my wife <a href="https://www.facebook.com/parvathy.panicker">Parvathy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://2018.strava.com/en-us/video/92aff78b819c502351b85b8ef27e35025cd97adf">
    <img src="/images/2018_sport.jpg" alt="Year in Sport" />
</a></p>

<h4><strong>Travel</strong></h4>

<p>We covered a couple of major tourist destinations around Australia - Great Barrier Reef (Cairns), <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/ndc-security-2018-overview-and-key-takeaways/">Gold Coast</a>, Frazer Island and Tasmania being the top highlights. We also did a lot of hikes and short trips around Brisbane including Tin Can Bay and Ballina. Snorkeling in the Great Barrier Reef, Penguin Tour in Tasmania, Whale watching, beach highway drive, and 7 seater beach flight in Frazer Island, dolphin feeding at Tin Can Bay, Croc attack show at Hartley&rsquo;s Crocodile Park were some of the new experiences in life and enjoyed it a lot.</p>

<h4><strong>Community</strong></h4>

<p>I did two public talks, one at the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/en-AU/Brisbane-Net-User-Group/events/251639570/">.Net User Group</a> on Azure Key Vault and one at Readify Back2Base on <a href="https://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/ok-i-have-got-https-what-next/">Ok I Have Got HTTPS! What Next?</a>. Two is still a smaller number and is something I want to do more of in the coming years.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2018_talks_ug.jpg" alt="Talk at .Net User Group" class="center" /></p>

<p>I created a youtube pip video on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S7EPrlpPqXw">Key Vault Connected Service</a>, and wanted to do couple more of such videos but did not get prioritized enough over the other things.
The significant open source contribution was to <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/MicrosoftConfigurationBuilders/commits?author=rahulpnath">KeyVault configuration builder</a> that is part of the ASP.Net framework.</p>

<h3>What didn&rsquo;t go well</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Blogging</strong> Blogging took a back seat this year, even though I had set out to do 4 posts a month. I did a total of 29 posts that&rsquo;s roughly over 2 posts a month. Some months I missed out on it completely.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2018_postpermonth.jpg" alt="Posts per month in the year 2018" /></p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reading</strong> <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user_challenges/13036464">20 books</a> was the goal for this year however ended up reading only 6 books. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20821042-80-20-running">80/20 Running</a> helped me a lot with my running.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Open Source</strong> I wanted to involve with one Open Source project actively, but the only thing that happened was some minor contributions.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Learning</strong> Most of the learning was at work, and I did not actively take up learning anything new. I did start with Category Theory and FSharp again, but it did not stick for a long time.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Goals for 2019</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reading</strong> Read 10 books</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Blogging</strong> 2 posts a month and stay consistent all months</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tri Sports</strong> Complete a Marathon, couple of half marathon event, at least one cycling event and 500m swim.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Learning</strong> Become more proficient with JavaScript. Build <a href="https://github.com/rahulpnath/keyvaultexplorer">Azure Key Vault Explorer</a> while learning.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I have been on and off my <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">planning</a> and <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">routines</a>. Looking to get back with this and organize my day-to-day activities a bit more and be more accountable for the goals that I have set.</p>

<p>Wishing you all a Happy and Prosperous New Year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working Effectively Under Constraints]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/working-effectively-under-constraints/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/working-effectively-under-constraints</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At times you might be working in environments where there are a lot of restrictions on the tools that you can use, the process that you need to follow, etc. Under these circumstances, it is essential that we stick to some core and fundamental principles and practices that we as an industry have adopted. We need to make sure that we have that in place no matter what the restrictions imposed are. Below are a few of the restrictions that I along with my team had to face at one of the clients and what we did to keep ourselves on top of it and still deliver at a higher speed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/working_constraints.png" alt="Working under Constraints." title="Working under Constraints. Image Source - https://www.saba.com/blog/how-to-master-employee-engagement-constraints"></p>

<blockquote><p><em>The issues discussed might or might not immediately relate to you, the important thing is your attitude towards such issues and finding ways around your constraints, keeping yourself productive on the long run.</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>No Build Deploy Pipeline</h3>

<p>When I joined the project, it amazed that we were still building/packaging the application from a local developer system and manually deploying this to the various environments (Dev, Test, UAT, and PROD).</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Whenever a release was to be made one of the developers was to pause his current work, switch to the appropriate branch for the release, make sure he had the latest code base, build with the correct configuration to generate a package.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>This might sound an outdated practice (as it did to me) but here I am at a client, in the year 2018 and it&rsquo;s still happening. What surprised me, even more, was that the team did have access to an <a href="https://octopus.com/">Octopus</a> server (backed by a <a href="https://jenkins.io/">Jenkins</a> build server) but since the <strong>deployment server did not have access to UAT/PROD servers</strong> they chose not to use it. You bet this was the first thing I was keen on fixing, as generating a release package from my local system would be the last thing that I want to do.</p>

<p>After a quick chat with the team, we decided on the below.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Set up build/deploy pipeline up to Test environment.</strong> This would allow seamless integration while we are developing features and get it out for testing. Since we had access till the Test environment, this was hardly an hours work to get it all working.</p></li>
<li><p>Since we did not have access to UAT/PROD and the process required us to hand over a deployment package to the concerned team, we <strong>set up a &lsquo;Packaging Project&rsquo; in Octopus.</strong> This project basically unzips the selected build package into our Dev environment server, applies the configuration transforms and zips up the folder into a deployment package. With this, we are now able to create a deployment package for any given build and for any environment. We are also having discussions to enable access to UAT/PROD servers for the deployment servers so that we can deploy automatically, all the way to production.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>No longer was the process dependent on a developer or a developer machine and was completely automated. For those reading this and in a similar situation but who does not have access to a build/deploy system like Jenkins/Octopus I would basically set up a simple script to pull down the source given a commit hash/branch/tfs label and perform a build and package independent of the working directory of the developer. This script could run on a shared server (if you have access to one) or worst on a developer&rsquo;s machine/VM. The fundamental thing that we are trying to achieve is to decouple it from the current working folder on a developer machine and the manual steps involved in generating a package. As long as you have an automated way to create a package irrespective of what tools/systems you use we should be safe and sound.</p>

<h3>Out of Sync SQL and Code Artifacts</h3>

<p>The application is heavily dependent on Stored Procedures for pulling/pushing data out of the SQL Server Database. Yes, you heard it right, Stored Procedures and ones with business logic in them, which is what makes it actually worse. Looking at how the Stored Procedures were maintained I could see that the team started off with good intentions using <a href="https://dbup.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">DbUp</a> but soon moved away from it. When I joined the process was to share SQL artifacts as attachments in the <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">Jira</a> story/bug. The Db Administrator (DBA) would then pull that out and manage them separately in a source control repository that was not the same as the application code base.</p>

<p>There was not much information on why this was the case, but the primary reason that they moved away from DbUp was that there was no visibility of the SQL scripts when running updates as it was an executable file that was the output of the DbUp project. Also, there were poor development/deployment practices that led to the ad-hoc execution of scripts in environments without actually updating the source control. This soon put the DBA out of control, and the only way to gain control back was to maintain it separately.</p>

<p>Again we decided to have a quick chat with the team along with the DBA on how to improve the current process, as it was getting harder to track application package versions and the associated scripts to go with that package.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>DbUp by default embeds the SQL artifacts into the executable which removes all visibility into the actual scripts. However, this behaviour is configurable using <a href="https://dbup.readthedocs.io/en/latest/more-info/script-providers/">ScriptProviders</a>. By using the <strong>FileSystemScriptProvider, we can specify the folder from which to load the SQL scripts</strong>. Configuring the msbuild to copy out all the folder files to the output and including them into the final package was an easy change. This provided the DBA with the actual SQL artifacts, and he could review them quickly. We also started a <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/code-review/">code review</a> process and began including the DBA for any changes related to SQL artifacts. This gave even more visibility to the DBA and helped catch issues right at the time of development.</p></li>
<li><p>With automated build/deploy till Test environment in place, we <strong>no longer had to make ad-hoc changes</strong> to the databases, and everything was pushed through the source control as it was faster and more comfortable.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>With this few tweaks we were now in a much better state, and there was a one to one trackability between source code and SQL artifacts. It all lived as part of one package, traceable all the way to the source code commit tag auto-generated by the build system.</p>

<h3>Not Invented Here Syndrome</h3>

<p>With the kind of restrictions you have seen till now, you can guess the approach towards third party services and off-the-shelf products. Most of the things are still done in-house (including trying to replicate a service bus). The problem with this approach is that there is a limit as to which you can go doing that after which you probably lose out on your team or the code takes over you where you just cannot maintain it. When starting out on a new project and when the code base is still small building your own mechanisms might seem to work well. But once past that point, you no longer want to continue down the path but invest in industry proven tools. These include logging servers, service-bus/queues (if you need one), email services (especially if you want to track and do statistics on top of the emails send out).</p>

<p>Biggest challenge introducing this is mostly not cost related (as there are a lot of really affordable services for every business)it&rsquo;s mostly the fear of unknown and lack of interest to venture out into unfamiliar territory. The reasons might vary for you, but try to understand the core reason that is hindering the change.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>One technique that worked to get over the fear of the unknown was to introduce this slowly into the system, one at a time, giving enough time for people to get used to the change.</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://getseq.net/">Seq</a> was one of the first things that we had proposed and long waiting in the wish list. The team was using <a href="https://serilog.net/">Serilog</a> to log, and all the logs were stored in SQL table making it really hard to query and monitor the logs. The infrastructure team did not want to install Seq as it was all new to them and were not sure about the additional task for managing a Seq instance. So we suggested to them to just have it on the development server and to get familiar with the application first. After a couple of days, the business was seeing a benefit with increased visibility into the logs and infrastructure team was also happy with the increased visibility into the logs. Even before a week, they were happy to install one for the test environment as well. At the time of writing we are looking at getting a Seq instance on the UAT server and soon to have a production instance as well. Getting the interested stakeholders to have a feel of the application and slowly introducing the change is a great way to get buy-in.</p>

<p>Now we are trying to push for a service bus!</p>

<h3>Build Server without NuGet access</h3>

<p>The build server we were using was in-house hosted, and the box that it ran did not have internet access. This meant that you cannot have any external package dependencies that can be pulled at build time. We chose to include the package references along with the source code, which is anyways what <a href="https://rahulpnath.com/blog/checking-in-package-dependencies-into-source-control/">I tend to prefer more</a>. All our third-party libraries were pushed along with the source code repository, so the build machine had all the required dependencies and did not have to have internet connectivity to make a build.</p>

<p>Those are just a subset of the issues that we had to run into and bet you there were so many smaller ones. At times problems are not technical in nature, but more about communication and how effectively you are able to get all the people involved to get along with each other.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Any journey to advancement is about valuing the people around you, understanding them and taking them along with the change. It&rsquo;s a journey that the team needs to make together and not a solo one.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Different people have different experiences, pain points, concerns and targets to check off. So as a team you need to understand what works for everyone and come to a collective agreement. Just getting all of the concerned parties into a room and having a healthy discussion (mainly by not being prescriptive but descriptive of the issues that you are facing) solves most of the problems.</p>

<p>Do you work in a similar environment? What challenges do you face at work? Sound off in the comments!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Share and Inspire]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/share-and-inspire/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/share-and-inspire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started this blog around nine years back, my only intention was to share technical posts. But over period of time I started writing about a variety of things including <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/productivity/">productivity tips</a> that I found useful, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/travelogue/">travelogues</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/thoughts/">random thoughts</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap/">personal goals</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/blogging/">blogging</a> etc. One of the things that I have noticed is that a lot of people have been inspired by these various posts and photos that I post online and have triggered them to do similar things.</p>

<p><img src="/images/share_and_inspire.jpg" alt="Share and Inspire, Image Source https://www.saylor.org/2015/04/blog-saylor-student-stories/" class="center"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had my own similar inspirations to start the various things that I do today. Like for instance, I started running after being inspired by my friends, <a href="https://twitter.com/SatyKrish">Satish</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/jeyakums">Suresh</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/thirusv">Thiru</a>. I reached out to them for various tips when I started running a year ago. From running I moved on to cycling and a bit of swimming after seeing my friend <a href="https://www.facebook.com/rahul.revikumar477977">Rahul</a>. For travel, my inspiration has been <a href="https://www.facebook.com/arun.sudheendran.1">Arun Sudheendran</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/deepak.suresh">Deepak Suresh</a> who do a fair bit of exploration. I tend to reach out to them for travel ideas and places to visit. Similarly, there have been inspirations from people that I have never met or met just once or twice.</p>

<p>Below is a transcript of a chat with one of my readers whom I have never met. It&rsquo;s a great feeling to wake up to such messages and it boosts your own motivation to continue what you are doing.</p>

<p><img src="/images/share_and_inspire_chat.png" alt="Share and Inspire" class="center"></p>

<p>Social media plays a great role in spreading information these days. When you see people in your own friend&rsquo;s circle start doing things that you have always wanted to, it gives you an extra push to give it a try. There might be some people who feel you are sharing too much of things that don&rsquo;t interest them. For those, there is always an option to un-follow, mute, filter etc. Don&rsquo;t let that thought stop you from sharing things that you do.</p>

<p>Such a small act of sharing, even things that you might have seen someone do could add up and be of big impact to someone else, often referred to as the <a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/TheButterflyEffectOfTechnologyCommunity.aspx">Butterfly Effect</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>The <strong>Butterfly Effect</strong>: This effect grants the power to cause a hurricane in China to a butterfly flapping its wings in New Mexico. It may take a very long time, but the connection is real. If the butterfly had not flapped its wings at just the right point in space/time, the hurricane would not have happened. - <a href="http://fractalfoundation.org/resources/what-is-chaos-theory/">Chaos Theory</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Share things that you do, share positive things and inspire others!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2017: What Went Well, What Didn't and Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/2017-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" alt="Posts per month - 2016" src="/images/happy_new_year.png"/></p>

<p><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/2016-recap/">A year</a> has gone by so fast, and it is again time to do a year review.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>TLDR;</strong></p>

<p>2017 was the transformation year. Regular exercise and healthy eating helped <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">loose around 20 kilos</a>. Lots of travel and blogging made it an excellent year. Reading, Photography and Open source did not go that great. Looking forward to 2018!</p></blockquote>

<h3>What went well</h3>

<h4><strong>Blogging</strong></h4>

<p>It has been both good and a bad year as far as this blog. Including the &lsquo;<a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/category/tipow/">Tip of the Week</a>&rsquo; series I wrote seventy-six posts this year with an average of over six posts per month. This is the good part, as it is well past the goal of a <em>minimum four posts a month</em> goal set last year. But looking at the actual posts per month graph below, it is clear that I have fallen short of it on an actual month by month basis. Up until August, I had a steady stream of posts coming in, from when it started dropping down, with even months (November) with no posts. Mainly it&rsquo;s my laziness to blame, but I can also tell reasons like Vietnam trip, Shifting to Brisbane, etc.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017_postpermonth.png" alt="Posts per month in the year 2017" /></p>

<h4><strong>Running</strong></h4>

<p>I had started running towards the end of December 2016. One of my goals for 2017 was running, and it has had a good improvement. Ran over 750 kilometers including a half marathon. I am yet to participate in any running events and am planning to in the coming year. I have also started cycling, and it is an excellent way to cross train.</p>

<p><a href="https://2017.strava.com/en-us/videos/92aff78b819c502351b85b8ef27e35025cd97adf/">
    <img src="/images/2017_sport.jpg" alt="Year in Sport" />
</a></p>

<h4><strong>Travel</strong></h4>

<p>Did our first international holiday to Vietnam for ten days and was a great experience. Also went around Australia visiting Blue Mountains, Canberra, Port Macquarie, Brisbane and lots of <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/one-day-trips-around-sydney/">one-day trips around Sydney</a>. Mandarin Picking, Strawberry picking and Whale watching were some of the top activities for the year.</p>

<p><img src="/images/strawberyy_picking.jpg" alt="Strawberry Picking, Ricardoes" /></p>

<h3>What didn&rsquo;t go well</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reading</strong> Had set out with a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/challenges/5493-2017-reading-challenge">goal of 21 books</a> but ended up finishing only ten books. Of the books I read liked <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mindset-Psychology-Carol-S-Dweck/dp/0345472322">Mindset</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People/dp/1439167346/">How to Win Friends and Influence People,</a> was the best.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Photography</strong>
One trip every three months and post photos were one another goal. The travel part went good (see above), but my DSLR always remained in the bag. Except for a few pictures on the phone camera, there was not much photography done.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>FSharp</strong>
FSharp was again on and off this year. Apart from a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-template-transformer-transform-tasks-to-x-days-from-now/">small utility that I created for Todoist</a>, I did not do much F# work.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Goals for 2018</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Blogging</strong> Stick to 4 posts a month. Need to get back on schedule.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Running</strong> Attend few running events. Run a marathon.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Swimming</strong> Having started cycling along with running, has got me thinking about a triathlon. The only thing between is swimming, and I have no clue how to swim. Learning to swim is one of the key goals for the upcoming year. Target is to be able to swim one km.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Open Source</strong> Start working on a side project. Need to find a matching project first.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reading</strong> Read 15 books</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Wishing you all a Happy and Prosperous New Year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Start New Habits That Stick]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/start_new_habits_that_stick/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/start_new_habits_that_stick</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><em>The beginning of a good habit is the elimination of an excuse.</em>   <br/>
<em>And The beginning of a bad habit is the finding of an excuse</em></p></blockquote>

<p>The ability to pick on something and to make a habit of it is something that is always helpful. This skill helps to create new habits and also let go off old ones that are not doing any good to you. Part of letting of bad old habits might be creating new ones. When I wrote about <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">Couch to Half Marathon</a>, some of my readers asked how to keep up with the plan. How to do &lsquo;Couch to Street&rsquo;; just getting out there.</p>

<p><a href= "https://quotefancy.com/quote/20375/Jim-Rohn-Motivation-is-what-gets-you-started-Habit-is-what-keeps-you-going">
    <img alt="Motivation is what gets you started. Habit is what keeps you going" src="/images/habit.jpg" class="center" />
</a></p>

<h3>How Habits Work</h3>

<p>To form new habits, it is important that we understand <a href="http://charlesduhigg.com/how-habits-work/">how habits work</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>a simple neurological loop at the core of every habit, a loop that consists of three parts: <strong>A cue, a routine and a reward.</strong></em></p></blockquote>

<p>As Charles Duhigg points out in his book, Power Of Habits (<a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc">recommended read</a>) the formula for changing habits differs from habit and persons. So it is more about using a framework to understand how habits work and experimenting on changing it. Changing a habit does take time and is not an easy one, but with a process in place, it is doable with time and effort.</p>

<p><img src="/images/habit_loop.jpg" class="center" alt="Cue-Routine-Reward Habit Loop" /></p>

<p>To break a bad habit one needs to identify it first. It could be anything from spending too much time on social media, eating unhealthy food, smoking, drinking, etc. Identifying that you have a habit and it&rsquo;s not good for you to continue with it is important. You can only change something once you identify it.</p>

<p>Once you recognize the habit, find out what is the trigger for the habit. Is it a particular place, people, time, etc. It might be hard to find the specific cue that triggers the habit, so note down everything that you find applicable. Then work on to isolate the cue by monitoring the habit over a couple of days. Wire up the cue that triggers the habit to perform some other action. Create that plan in advance and have some way to remind yourself of it. If your cue is time-based or location based, then you can use your smartphone to pop-up a reminder. If not try to find ways to keep yourself reminded to perform the new plan. It feels hard in the beginning but stick to the plan, and in time you will be able to change your habit. I recommend you to read the book <a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc">Power of Habits</a> to understand this subject better.</p>

<h3>Mini Habits and Short Term Goals</h3>

<p>To start creating new habits, I have found setting smaller goals to target daily works better. I began writing at least one line every day to be <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/">consistent in blogging</a>, running at least once a week to establish an exercise routine, eat at least one meal healthy, etc. Time-based cues help to enforce such new behavior. Setting aside a specific time as per the desired frequency to perform the activity makes sure that you do not skip doing it. Also, remember to keep the action as simple as possible so that you do not procrastinate when the time comes.</p>

<p>Like if it is running that you are planning to start it could be -  <em>Every Saturday at 6 am I will wear my running shoes and get out of my house</em>. When the time comes, this is such a simple task that you have set for yourself, and you are more likely to do it. Once you have taken the pain of putting the shoes and getting out of the couch, you are more likely to run for at least five minutes.</p>

<p>Break your goals into small and achievable mini goals. These mini goals are often referred to as <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Most Important Tasks (MIT)</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Big Rocks</a> etc. The key is to break them down into smaller achievable mini-goals and setting a cue to trigger the activity.</p>

<h3>Motivation and Its Role</h3>

<p>Very often we get motivated to start new activities and begin with great enthusiasm. In the beginning, we feel a spike in energy and see things happening. But soon you hit a point where you feel nothing is moving and you feel it a burden to continue. This stage is referred to as <em>plateau - a state of little or no change following a period of activity or progress.</em> You soon see your motivation levels dropping and justifying to yourself how little or no benefit your actions have. Eventually, you find yourself losing entire interest in the activity and start looking for new motivation spikes. This has happened to me many times.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Motivation is what gets you started.Habit is what keeps you going.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>I have found this to be entirely true. We need the motivation to help us to get started with new activities and set new goals. But motivation alone cannot help us go all the way and achieve what we want. Before jump-starting with the idea give it a good thought to check if it is worth your time spent. If not park the idea to your <a href="http://gettingthingsdone.com/2010/10/what-goes-on-a-someday-maybe-list/">Someday Maybe list</a> (as referred to in <a href="http://amzn.to/2gsJaed">GTD</a>).</p>

<p>Once you have decided to pursue the idea, break it into smaller pieces and set achievable &lsquo;mini goals.&rsquo; Set dedicated time at regular intervals for achieving these mini-goals. Most important is in having some &lsquo;me time&rsquo; to get towards these goals. Like for me I have found that <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">mornings work best for me</a> and created a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">Morning Routine</a>. To make sure that I make the best of my time I try to work in <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Pomodoro&rsquo;s and inspect and adapt the process</a> often.</p>

<h3>Tracking and Feedback</h3>

<p>Tracking is an important part of habit formation. Once you have set your goals and mini habits also find ways to track your progress. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/psm-learnings/">Inspect and Adapt</a> is the fundamental principle behind Agile Processes. Habit formation is nothing but being agile, keeping the end goal in mind, adjusting the way you reach there. Find ways and tools to track progress on the habits that you are trying to form.</p>

<p>I prefer automatic tracking with least manual entry, so the tracking happens in the background. But at times you will have to resort to manual methods as well. Make sure you have a time set aside daily to capture the information. Having a review of the data obtained once every week or two and taking adjustment actions is equally important. Some of the tracking tools that I use are <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/rescue-time-track-your-time/">Rescue Time</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">Garmin Forerunner 630</a> and a few manual ones. I [review my progress every week] and try to incorporate feedback into the upcoming week.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>All it takes to start a new habit is a moment - The moment where you decide on the new habit. The rest is process!</em></p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-i-lost-13-kilos-in-one-and-half-months/">Eating Healthy, Exercise</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/">Blogging</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/waking-up-early-is-all-about-waking-up-to-an-alarm/">Waking up Early</a>, <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/experimenting-with-pomodoro-technique/">Reducing time spent on Social Media, Reading</a> and <strike><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/recording-my-first-screencast/">Creating Videos</a></strike> (looking to give this up) are some of the habits that I have formed following these techniques. The ability to decide on something and getting it to done is the most important of all. Once you have mastered the skill of forming new habits, it boils down to choosing good habits and wiring that into your life. I have heard about the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jasonselk/2013/04/15/habit-formation-the-21-day-myth/">21-Day rule of habit formation</a> and similar myths. But I think all it takes to start a new habit is a moment - The moment where you decide on the new habit. The rest is process!</p>

<p><strong>References:</strong></p>

<div>
   <div class="row">
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
         <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://amzn.to/2gOYluc" >
            <img alt="Power Of Habit" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_powerofhabit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;">
            </a>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="col-sm-6 col-md-3">
         <div class="thumbnail">
            <a href="http://amzn.to/2hmeokB">
            <img alt="Superhuman by Habit" src="http://rahulpnath.com/images/books_superhumanbyhabit.jpg" data-holder-rendered="true" style="display: block;" >
            </a>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
