<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: review | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-05T19:55:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Pixel, Phone by Google - Made by Google]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-pixel/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-pixel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to mobile phones, I used to be a gadget freak and buy the latest phone as soon as it arrives in the market. But not after I got the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/">Nexus 5</a>. It&rsquo;s been well over three years now and not even once did I want to switch over to something else. The phone never slowed down over these years, and the battery lasted enough for the day. I broke the Nexus screen a couple of months back and was forced to switch over to a new phone. I didn&rsquo;t have to do much market research or phone comparisons this time; as I just knew which one to pick up.</p>

<p><a href="https://madeby.google.com/intl/en_au/phone/">The Pixel, Phone By Google!</a></p>

<p><img src="/images/pixel.png" alt="Pixel" class="center" /></p>

<h4><strong>Key Features</strong></h4>

<p>The Pixel is the first phone in the Google Pixel hardware line and is a successor to the Nexus range of devices. The Pixel runs <a href="https://www.android.com/intl/en_au/versions/nougat-7-0/">Android-Nougat</a> with some features exclusive to it. The Pixel is very much comparable to the Nexus, with improved hardware and latest software. Below are some of the key features that I like about the phone.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Fingerprint sensor</strong> The fingerprint sensor on the back allows you to unlock the phone and specific apps and also authorize purchases. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/password-manager-get-one-if-you-havent-already/">1Password</a> is integrated with the sensor which enables me to unlock it using the sensor. I no longer need to type in my long master password every time I use 1Password.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Camera</strong> <em>Pixel takes brilliant photos in bright light, low light, and any light.</em> The camera is awesome and at times is a good replacement for your <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/photography-learning-to-click/">DSLR</a>. With Pixel, Google also provides unlimited original quality storage for all photos and videos.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Google Assistant</strong> Pixel is the first phone with the <a href="https://assistant.google.com/">Google Assistant</a> built-in. It helps you manage tasks, find content on phone and the internet, perform actions, etc. just like Siri or Cortana. I have not used the assistant much and yet to find some valid use cases.</p></li>
</ul>


<h4><strong>Apps</strong></h4>

<p> Some of the apps that I use regularly are</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/todoist-manage-your-todo-list/">Todoist</a>: My ToDo List</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/feedly-one-stop-reading-place/">Feedly</a>: For all my RSS feeds</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/pocket-offline-reading-made-easy/">Pocket</a>: For offline reading and read later</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/password-manager-get-one-if-you-havent-already/">1Password</a>: Password Manager</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/buffer-smarter-social-sharing/">Buffer</a>: To schedule articles to all social networks</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/rescue-time-track-your-time/">Rescue Time</a>: Automatically tracks where I spent time on mobile</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">Strava, Runtastic &amp; Garmin Connect</a>: Tracking my runs and exercises</li>
<li><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.amazon.kindle">Kindle</a>: Reading kindle books</li>
<li>Twitter, Whatsapp, Messenger, Instagram, Skype &amp; Yammer :Social Networking apps</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/optimizing-octopress-workflow-for-new-posts/">JotterPad</a>: Write articles for blog in markdown format</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/how-to-setup-google-indic-keyboard-on-your-android-phone/">Google Indic Keyboard</a>: Writing in my native language</li>
<li>Gmail &amp; Outlook: Emails</li>
<li>Youtube: Videos</li>
</ul>


<h4><strong>Case </strong></h4>

<p>I am using the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/spigen-awesome-phone-cases/">Spigen Neo Hybrid</a> case for Pixel. It adds extra weight to the phone, but I am used to it from my Nexus as well. The Neo Hybrid provides military grade protection and protects the phone from most falls.</p>

<p>Overall I have found the Pixel a good phone and recommend it to anyone looking out for a new phone now. The Samsung Galaxy S8 is also of the same range (slightly costlier) and worth considering if you are not too particular about having a vanilla Android experience. Which phone do you use?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip of the Week: Spigen - Awesome Phone Cases]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/spigen-awesome-phone-cases/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/spigen-awesome-phone-cases</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are looking to get a case for your phone, then check out cases by <a href="https://www.spigen.com/">Spigen</a>. I have been using Spigen cases for over three years, and I totally recommend it.</p>

<p>Spigen cases are made with premium materials and are slim, sleek and simple. Spigen provides various models that match different needs. The cases provide <a href="https://www.spigen.com/pages/military-grade">Military Grade Protection</a> and protect the phone from most falls.</p>

<p>The first Spigen cases I got was for my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/">Nexus 5</a>. The Neo Hybrid lasted for over three years. With the Spigen cases, the Nexus was well protected. It did fall from my hands many times, and every time the case protected it well enough. A couple of months back the Spigen case broke, and I had been using the phone without a cover since then. Unfortunately, during one of my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/three_months_to_a_half_marathon/">morning runs</a> the phone fell from my hands while slipping it into the armband. Without the Spigen to protect it, the Nexus screen broke at the corners.</p>

<p><img src="/images/spigen_pixel.png" alt="Spigen Neo Hybrid for Pixel" class="center" /></p>

<p>A month back I switched over to Google Pixel as the Nexus was becoming unusable with the broken screen. I got the <a href="https://www.spigen.com/collections/pixel/products/google-pixel-case-neo-hybrid?variant=29248762049">Spigen NeoHybrid for Pixel</a>. The case provides dual layer protection with TCU and PC bumper and comes with fingerprint resistance. The precise cutouts give easy access to all buttons and fingerprint sensor.</p>

<p>If you are looking to a get a case, check out if <a href="https://www.spigen.com/">Spigen</a> has one for your model!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016: What Went Well, What Didn't and Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/2016-recap/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/2016-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.oldlaundrytheatre.co.uk/happy-new-year-from-all-at-the-old-laundry/">
<img class="center" alt="Posts per month - 2016" src="/images/2016_happy_new_year.png"/>
</a></p>

<p>2016 was a great year and I thought sharing some of the things that went well, those that didn&rsquo;t and setting goals for 2017.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>TLDR;</strong></p>

<p><em>2016 was a great year and is the first one where I am writing a &lsquo;year in review&rsquo; post. Blogging, Videos, Open Source and Community contribution are some of the things that went well. FSharp, Reading, Travel, Photography and Exercise did not go that great. Looking forward to 2017 and planning to keep the goodness of 2016 and add some more to it</em></p></blockquote>

<h3>What went well</h3>

<h4><strong>Blogging</strong></h4>

<p>This has been a great year with my blog. On an average, I published four blog posts a month. It started with a self-challenge from March to write every day. I was able to come up with eight posts that month, but then felt it was not something that I could stick with consistently. So I kept a target of four posts per month and stuck to it for the rest of the year. I automated a lot of mundane tasks in my blogging workflow right from <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/optimizing-octopress-workflow-for-new-posts/">creating draft posts</a> to <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/continuos-delivery-of-octopress-blog-using-travisci-and-docker/">deploying posts</a> and <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/automatic_deployment_of_future_posts_with_octopress/">scheduling posts for future deployment</a>. This has saved a lot of time for me and helps me stick just with the writing part of blogging!</p>

<p><img class="center" alt="Posts per month - 2016" src="/images/2016_postspermonth.png"/></p>

<p>Sticking with <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/maintaining-a-blogging-schedule/">publishing posts on a regular interval</a> was more about deciding that I have to write every day. I set a &lsquo;mini habit&rsquo; to write every day - at least one line every day - and stuck to it. This helped me get over the initial inertia of starting to write a post. Having set this goal to myself I had to consistently come with topics to blog about. This very much changed the way that I approached <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/finding-a-job-abroad/">my day job</a>. I always involved in it with the need to find something to share, in a way that I can abstract it out from the business dependencies. Most of the decisions and issues that happened to us (the development team) are now documented here. This acts as a documentation for any new joiners and makes the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/make-it-easy-for-the-new-person-joining-your-team-have-a-project-ramp-up-plan/">ramp up to the project a bit easier</a>. More than anything it definitely helps me find the solution when I come across the same issue again. So if you still don&rsquo;t have a blog of your own, there is no better time than now. Make it a new year resolution. <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/own-your-urls/">Get a URL</a> and start writing. I have also been successful in getting a couple of people (at least four that I personally know of) to blog. Getting started is the biggest hurdle, the rest will fall in the due course of time.</p>

<h4><strong>Youtube Channel</strong></h4>

<p>Starting a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RahulNath">Youtube channel</a> had been something I wanted to do for a long time. I have just got started with it and posted one video. I now understand why people say recording is hard - there is a lot to it and it takes time to be good at it. The only way to get better if something is hard is to do more of it - <em><a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/FrequencyReducesDifficulty.html">Frequency Reduces Difficulty</a></em> I plan to start with one video per month and see how it goes. I have been procrastinating on the second video for a while, <strike>will see if I can get it out before this year!</strike> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JbshGF4ZwGE">Got it out just in time!</a></p>

<h4><strong>Open Source and Forums</strong></h4>

<p>Contributing to Open Source projects is a good way to learn. I have always struggled to find projects/issues to contribute to. But then I learned that it is again just a matter of deciding and committing to. <a href="http://www.firsttimersonly.com/">First Timers only</a> a good way to find issues and projects that one can possible jump right into. I decided to start looking at projects that I use more on a day to day basis - Asmspy and Autofixture were something that interested me. There were a couple of open issues in AsmSpy, that I picked up and <a href="http://mikehadlow.com/">Mike Hadlow</a> was more than happy to merge them in. I also decided to set up <a href="https://github.com/mikehadlow/AsmSpy/issues/14">Chocolatey package for AsmSpy</a>. On Mike&rsquo;s request, I now manage the <a href="https://chocolatey.org/packages/asmspy/">chocolatey package account</a> and am a contributor on AsmSpy project. I automated the <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/automated-deployment-of-asmspy-to-chocolatey-using-appveyor/">deployment pipeline for AsmSpy</a> so that I do not have to worry about deploying the chocolatey package every time a change is made. Also got to <a href="https://github.com/AutoFixture/AutoFixture/issues?q=mentions:rahulpnath+is:closed">contribute to a few issues with AutoFixture</a> which is managed by <a href="http://blog.ploeh.dk/">Mark Seemann (ploeh)</a>. I was also lucky enough to meet him in person at <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/ndc-sydney/">NDC Sydney</a>.</p>

<p>I keep a look at the <a href="https://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/azure/en-US/home?forum=AzureKeyVault">Azure Key Vault MSDN forum</a> and try to help every time a question comes up. Answering questions on forums is also a <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-in-the-learning-loop/">good way to learn</a>, find interesting problems and <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count/">at times rewarding</a>.</p>

<h3>What didn&rsquo;t go well</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>FSharp</strong>: Learning FSharp is something that I really want to, but it&rsquo;s not been happening that well. I am on and off with this and it keeps getting sidelined.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reading</strong>: Compared to <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user_challenges/3539650">2015</a> my reading has been a lot down in <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user_challenges/5380726">2016</a>. Though I have been listening to a lot more podcasts, I think I have to get back on with reading in the coming year.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Travel &amp; Photography</strong>: There&rsquo;s not been much travel except for the long vacation back home and a few local places in Sydney. Though I have been clicking along I was lazy to process them. There are still lying on my camera waiting to be processed.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Exercise</strong>: Getting enough exercise is something that I have really lacked last year and I think I have also put up some weight because of it. Except for the walk up and down from home to station for the office commute, there&rsquo;s not been much of my body moving.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Goals for 2017</h3>

<blockquote><p><em>In preparing for battle I have always found that plans are useless, but planning is indispensable.</em></p>

<p>― Dwight D. Eisenhower</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Blogging</strong>: Stick to at least four posts per month. Try to see if I can get up to 6-8. I will have to improve the time that I take to write a post for this. Handling images for the blog needs to be automated as I spent some time converting and optimizing them.</li>
<li><strong>Videos</strong>: Create a schedule for publishing videos and improve the quality and delivery of the videos.</li>
<li><strong>Reading</strong>: Set up a reading plan and read at least 21 books (1 more than what I did in 2015).</li>
<li><strong>FSharp</strong>: Learn, Contribute and Blog</li>
<li><strong>Travel &amp; Photography</strong>: One trip at least once in 3 months and post photos</li>
<li><strong>Exercise</strong>: Run/Bike at least once a week.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Six Months and Counting - Logitech MX Master]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-six-months-and-counting-logitech-mx-master/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-six-months-and-counting-logitech-mx-master</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been six months with the <a href="http://amzn.to/2ddLmUf">Logitech MX Master</a> mouse and I absolutely love it for daily use. I picked this mouse a week after reading <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/FindingThePerfectMouse.aspx">Hanselman&rsquo;s review</a>. It feels just as it sounded in his review - Perfect!.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/mx-master">
    <img  alt="Logitech MX Master" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster.jpg"/>
</a></p>

<h4><strong>Key Features</strong></h4>

<ul>
<li><p>The mouse fits perfectly into the hand and supports the wrist in a native position. It is suitable for long duration use.</p></li>
<li><p>The battery is rechargeable and the mouse comes with a micro-USB charging cable. After a full charge, the mouse lasts me for 2-3 weeks.   The mouse can be used while charging, so there is no downtime. The LED lights indicate the charge status. If not the software also warns when the battery is low.</p></li>
<li><p>I connect the mouse using the Logitech Unifying Receiver. But the mouse also supports connecting over Bluetooth. This is useful in cases when you want to connect with multiple computers.</p></li>
<li><p>The mouse supports Easy Switch technology.  You can pair up to 3 devices and switch between them using buttons on the bottom side of the mouse. I have not used this feature as I mostly work on just one laptop.</p></li>
<li><p>Darkfield Laser Sensor tracks flawlessly over all surfaces. I use the MX Master across wooden and glass surfaces and find it smooth over both.</p></li>
<li><p>The mouse scroll supports smooth scrolling and &lsquo;Ratchet&rsquo; mode (click, click, click) scroll. It supports automatic and manual mode shifting. So when reading long documents you can be on smooth scrolling and when navigating code or shorter texts you can use Ratchet mode to feel greater control. It also has buttons to</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The mouse has an accompanying software that allows customizations of mouse buttons.</p>

<p><img  alt="Logitech MX Master Software" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster_software.png"/></p>

<p>The software allows setting application specific actions for buttons. For e.g. I have the Gesture button to archive emails in Outlook, &lsquo;Navigate to Definition&rsquo; in Visual Studio, close tab in Chrome etc. You can configure this to any action on applications of your choice (provided it supports keyboard shortcuts that can be linked to).</p>

<p><img  alt="Logitech MX Master Software customizations" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster_customize.png"/></p>

<h4><strong>Issue</strong></h4>

<p>The only issue that I faced so long is with the Mouse scroll mode. The &lsquo;Ratchet&rsquo; mode no longer works for me. It is always in smooth scrolling mode and the mechanical key to shift modes does not work anymore. Google tells me that this is a <a href="https://community.logitech.com/s/question/0D531000051026rCAA">common issue</a> with the mouse .
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KR9fLd_ViYw">This video</a> walks through on how to open up the mouse and fix the mechanical part that clicks in to switch the scroll modes. I have not tried this myself as I don&rsquo;t feel much a problem without the Ratchet mode.</p>

<p>Other than the Ratchet mode issue, I have not found any other issues with the mouse.</p>

<div align="center">
<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:41.712962963% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BC11BabgPpV/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Trying out the logitech mx master mouse. Liking it!</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Rahul P Nath (@rahulpnath) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-03-12T05:22:06+00:00">Mar 11, 2016 at 9:22pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>
<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>
</div>


<p><br />
If you are looking for a new mouse and willing to spend a little more than usual, I recommend the <a href="http://amzn.to/2ddLmUf">Logitech MX Master</a>. What mouse do you use?</p>

<p>* <em>Amazon links are affiliated.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Two Months and Counting - Android and Nexus 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T16:08:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gadgets, especially mobile phones have always been of interest to me and so is it even today. Its been over two months since I have moved over to Android on Nexus 5. I have been a loyal, hardcore Windows phone fan for over 3 years before that and it did take time to get used to the new operating system. There are still things that I like about Windows phone but there are things that I don’t like too, so I though of giving Android a try. <a href="https://www.google.com/nexus/5/">Nexus 5</a> is one powerful device that is worth every penny for its power packed features and there is no reason not to like it. The <a href="http://www.androidpolice.com/2013/10/20/weekend-poll-nexus-5-white-or-black/">White vs Black</a> confusion was there but then I got the White one, as that was the only thing in stock, and after all with a protective cover on, it didn’t matter much.</p>

<p><strong>Things that I love:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Notification</strong> : The one stop place for all notifications is one of the best things that I like moving to Android from Windows phone. A <a href="http://i.msdn.microsoft.com/dynimg/IC619123.png">missed toast</a> is always missed until I next decide to open that app in Windows phone or maybe a lock screen notification. But now it is right there on the notification center. (though I have many notifications turned off as part of <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-organized-finding-a-system-to-manage-it-all/">Staying Organized</a>)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Toggle Settings : <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.painless.pc">Toggling settings</a></strong> like Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, 3G etc is also top on my likes. There is at least 2 steps required for toggling these settings in Windows phone</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Google Now : </strong>I have been googling around for a lot of years and like the way Google Now updates on searches that I have done. Yes I know that we have a privacy problem here, but I have decided to stay on the internet – everything gets tracked here. The <strong>speech recognition</strong> of Google is as best it can get today, best thing being it understands my accent (Indian) pretty much all the time.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Apps: </strong>I have never been a fan of apps and I rarely used them. Windows phone did have all the major apps, but most of them lacked all the features because of which I had to switch to the web app at times. This in fact made me use the web app always. But Android apps mostly has all the features which makes me use them more. Some of the apps that I use regularly are :</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ch.bitspin.timely">Timely</a> : An awesome alarm clock with the cool Smart Rise feature</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.gm">Gmail</a> : With all the features of the web app</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.skype.raider">Skype</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.microsoft.office.lync15">Lync</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.whatsapp">Whatsapp</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.facebook.katana">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.twitter.android">Twitter</a>: Helps me keep connected with my friends, peers and customers</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.giant">Google Analytics</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wordpress.android">Wordpress</a> – For keeping track of my blog</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.authenticator2">Authenticator</a> – for all two-step verification codes</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.microsoft.skydrive">Onedrive</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.dropbox.android">Dropbox</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.github.mobile">GitHub</a> – For managing my cloud storage. GitHub has a lot more to improve on features.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.stitcher.app">Stitcher</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.devhd.feedly">Feedly</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=mobi.beyondpod">BeyondPod</a> – For feeds and podcasts</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.microsoft.office.onenote">OneNote</a> and the native email app - For tracking notes, <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-organized-finding-a-system-to-manage-it-all/">tasks and exchange emails</a>. The native email application has a lot of scope for improvement</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.alienmanfc6.wheresmyandroid">Where&rsquo;s My Droid</a> - Finding a lost phone equivalent on Windows Phone.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.amazon.kindle">Kindle</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.overdrive.mobile.android.mediaconsole">Overdrive</a> - For my kindle books and audio books</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.nurik.roman.dashclock">DashClock Widget</a> - For lock screen notifications</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ro.weednet.contactssync">UberSync</a> – To sync facebook contacts and profile pictures to a contact. This is something that is really good in windows phone. Ability to link all social accounts of a person/contact.</p></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Customization: </strong>The level of customization and control that each application gives is enormous that almost everything is configurable. You can mute/turn off notifications on annoying text promotion messages, different color notifications, auto update settings and a lot more.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Chrome: </strong>This definitely is one another on my top likes. I have been using chrome for a long time and absolutely love the experience even on android. The password sync across devices is cool and so is <a href="https://support.google.com/chrome/answer/2591582?hl=en">Sync tabs across devices</a>. Bookmarks sync and support for <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.delicious">Delicious</a> is also good. IE definitely has a long way to go there. The <a href="https://developers.google.com/chrome-developer-tools/docs/remote-debugging">developer support</a> for chrome on android is also worth mentioning.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Things that I don’t like and miss:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Jumplist: <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/windows-phone-series-jump-lists/">Jumplists</a></strong> really made navigating through large lists a lot easier on Windows phone. Now I always need to hit the search button and type.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>People Hub: </strong>This was one of the best things of Windows phone, having the ability to <a href="http://www.windowsphone.com/en-us/how-to/wp7/people/people-hub?signin=true">link all your social networks</a> into one and have a quick access of all updates.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Nokia Music and Drive: </strong>In fact all the Nokia suite apps were really good and especially these two.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The lists itself explains much of it – <strong>I am liking it a lot. </strong>The android experience on a Nexus device is fast and smooth.</p>

<p><strong>Cases and Covers:</strong></p>

<p>I have been alternating between 2 cases for my Nexus 5 from Spigen and liking them both especially the Neo Hybrid. The white shows of through its transparent back and the overall grip on the phone is very good and comfortable.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.in/gp/product/B00HYA10LC/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3626&amp;creative=24822&amp;creativeASIN=B00HYA10LC&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-21">Spigen Google Nexus 5 Case ULTRA HYBRID</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.in/gp/product/B00EV8Y6QQ/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3626&amp;creative=24822&amp;creativeASIN=B00EV8Y6QQ&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-21">Spigen Google Nexus 5 Case Protective Neo Hybrid</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>The <strong>battery</strong> backup on the device is pretty good and is lasting for me through a day. I have not yet been on any trips with the phone, so can’t comment on the battery in such situations where generally it lasts lesser. But <a href="http://www.ibtimes.com/google-working-nexus-5-battery-drain-fix-affects-all-android-devices-kitkat-qualcomm-chips-1559771">Google has also announced</a> on a battery leak issue for which a fix would be out soon. Hope that would improve it further. I have never been a fan of phone <strong>camera, </strong>since <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/photography-learning-to-click/">I prefer my DSLR</a> for that, but even then for a camera it is pretty decent with lots of options and filters. At times it does come handy and works perfect.</p>

<p>If you are planning to get a new phone and then this is worth considering. If you are already using one then do let know on what you feel about the phone?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
