<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: syncfusion giveaway | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tag/syncfusion-giveaway/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-05T00:02:21+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Giveaway : Get a license of your choice from Syncfusion]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/giveaway-get-a-license-of-your-choice-from-syncfusion/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-25T16:33:08+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/giveaway-get-a-license-of-your-choice-from-syncfusion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Often we run up into the need for third party controls to give your apps/sites that extra edge that all of us are looking for. Syncfusion provides an excellent collection of controls for various platforms, details of which you can find <a href="http://www.syncfusion.com/products?UTM_medium=rahulblogreview">here</a> .
Syncfusion was generous enough to giveaway a license for the readers of this blog. I didn&rsquo;t want to restrict you to get a license for a platform of my choice, so its all yours. You get to choose which platform license you want out of the the 9 different option(ASP.NET, ASP.NET MVC, JavaScript, Mobile MVC, Silverlight, WinForms, Windows Phone, WinRT and WPF) on the site. So who would be that lucky one?</p>

<h2><strong>How to be that lucky one?</strong></h2>

<p>Check out the form below on how.</p>

<p><a class="rafl" id="rc-52158e0" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/52158e0/" rel="nofollow">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a><br />
<script type="text/javascript" src="//d12vno17mo87cx.cloudfront.net/embed/rafl/cptr.js"></script></p>


<p>Once the winner is decided you would be notified via email. Choosing the lucky one would be this blog admins responsibility. Any decision made by the admin would be final.</p>

<p>Hope you are that lucky one !</p>

<p><strong> Edit: </strong>Had a very good response and am really happy to announce the winners. Instead of 1 lucky winner I am planning to make it 3. The lucky 3 would be soon contacted with more details</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
