<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gadgets | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/category/gadgets/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-04T00:05:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Six Months and Counting - Logitech MX Master]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-six-months-and-counting-logitech-mx-master/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-six-months-and-counting-logitech-mx-master</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been six months with the <a href="http://amzn.to/2ddLmUf">Logitech MX Master</a> mouse and I absolutely love it for daily use. I picked this mouse a week after reading <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/FindingThePerfectMouse.aspx">Hanselman&rsquo;s review</a>. It feels just as it sounded in his review - Perfect!.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/mx-master">
    <img  alt="Logitech MX Master" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster.jpg"/>
</a></p>

<h4><strong>Key Features</strong></h4>

<ul>
<li><p>The mouse fits perfectly into the hand and supports the wrist in a native position. It is suitable for long duration use.</p></li>
<li><p>The battery is rechargeable and the mouse comes with a micro-USB charging cable. After a full charge, the mouse lasts me for 2-3 weeks.   The mouse can be used while charging, so there is no downtime. The LED lights indicate the charge status. If not the software also warns when the battery is low.</p></li>
<li><p>I connect the mouse using the Logitech Unifying Receiver. But the mouse also supports connecting over Bluetooth. This is useful in cases when you want to connect with multiple computers.</p></li>
<li><p>The mouse supports Easy Switch technology.  You can pair up to 3 devices and switch between them using buttons on the bottom side of the mouse. I have not used this feature as I mostly work on just one laptop.</p></li>
<li><p>Darkfield Laser Sensor tracks flawlessly over all surfaces. I use the MX Master across wooden and glass surfaces and find it smooth over both.</p></li>
<li><p>The mouse scroll supports smooth scrolling and &lsquo;Ratchet&rsquo; mode (click, click, click) scroll. It supports automatic and manual mode shifting. So when reading long documents you can be on smooth scrolling and when navigating code or shorter texts you can use Ratchet mode to feel greater control. It also has buttons to</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The mouse has an accompanying software that allows customizations of mouse buttons.</p>

<p><img  alt="Logitech MX Master Software" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster_software.png"/></p>

<p>The software allows setting application specific actions for buttons. For e.g. I have the Gesture button to archive emails in Outlook, &lsquo;Navigate to Definition&rsquo; in Visual Studio, close tab in Chrome etc. You can configure this to any action on applications of your choice (provided it supports keyboard shortcuts that can be linked to).</p>

<p><img  alt="Logitech MX Master Software customizations" src="/images/logitech_mxmaster_customize.png"/></p>

<h4><strong>Issue</strong></h4>

<p>The only issue that I faced so long is with the Mouse scroll mode. The &lsquo;Ratchet&rsquo; mode no longer works for me. It is always in smooth scrolling mode and the mechanical key to shift modes does not work anymore. Google tells me that this is a <a href="https://community.logitech.com/s/question/0D531000051026rCAA">common issue</a> with the mouse .
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KR9fLd_ViYw">This video</a> walks through on how to open up the mouse and fix the mechanical part that clicks in to switch the scroll modes. I have not tried this myself as I don&rsquo;t feel much a problem without the Ratchet mode.</p>

<p>Other than the Ratchet mode issue, I have not found any other issues with the mouse.</p>

<div align="center">
<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:41.712962963% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BC11BabgPpV/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Trying out the logitech mx master mouse. Liking it!</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Rahul P Nath (@rahulpnath) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-03-12T05:22:06+00:00">Mar 11, 2016 at 9:22pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>
<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>
</div>


<p><br />
If you are looking for a new mouse and willing to spend a little more than usual, I recommend the <a href="http://amzn.to/2ddLmUf">Logitech MX Master</a>. What mouse do you use?</p>

<p>* <em>Amazon links are affiliated.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Staying Productive Offline]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-productive-offline/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-productive-offline</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last month I was in Trivandrum (Kerala, India) for a month&rsquo;s vacation. This was also my first trip back to India after <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/finding-a-job-abroad/">moving to Sydney</a>. While in India I chose not to have a mobile connection and be offline on the go (at home I had a broadband connection). So while traveling places or moving around I had <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/">my mobile</a> in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airplane_mode">airplane mode</a>. But even then there was time that I resorted to my mobile to spend time. When traveling by bus/train, afternoons in hotels (when everyone rests) etc, I had a lot of &lsquo;me time&rsquo;.</p>

<p><img  alt="Living an offline Life" src="/images/offlinelife.png"/></p>

<p>Below are some of the things that I have my phone geared up for offline mode.</p>

<h4><strong>Blogging</strong></h4>

<p>Blogging is one of the things that I enjoy doing most these days. To keep up with <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">my routine</a>, I try to blog every day to keep up with <a href="/blog/blogging-schedule/">my schedule</a>. I have modified <a href="/blog/optimizing-octopress-workflow-for-new-posts/">my blogging workflow</a> to give the flexibility to blog from any of my devices. Currently, I am writing this blog while on a train and &lsquo;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Online_and_offline">disconnected</a>&rsquo;. When back home and connected, all the offline content synchronizes through Dropbox. The content written while offline is now available for <a href="/blog/continuos-delivery-of-octopress-blog-using-travisci-and-docker/">publishing from my laptop</a>. Making writing accessible from everywhere helps me to stick with my <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">mini habits</a>.</p>

<h4><strong>Reading</strong></h4>

<p>I always have books, articles downloaded and available for offline reading. For books, I use the Kindle application. Most of the time I have my Kindle for reading, if not I use the mobile application. For blog posts and articles I use Pocket. Whenever I am connected and find interesting posts to read later, I <a href="https://getpocket.com/add/?ep=1">Add to Pocket</a>. Pocket&rsquo;s mobile application <a href="https://help.getpocket.com/article/960-using-pocket-offline-on-android">downloads articles</a> and makes them available for offline reading.</p>

<p><img alt="Amazon Kindle and Pocket for offline reading" src="/images/offlinelife_reading.png"/></p>

<h4><strong>Game</strong></h4>

<p>I usually do not have many games on my mobile. But in case I feel bored I play the <a href="http://mashable.com/2014/09/25/chrome-t-rex-game/">game available on Chrome browser</a> (only in offline mode). When offline a T. Rex dinosaur comes up in the browser with the message &lsquo;Unable to connect to the Internet&rsquo;. Tapping on the dinosaur starts the game.</p>

<p><img  alt="Google Chrome offline T Rex game" src="/images/offlinelife_chrome_game.gif"/></p>

<h4><strong>To-Do List</strong></h4>

<p>Offline time is good to manage your To-Do lists and <a href="http://www.rahulpnath.com/blog/morning_routine/">do a brain dump</a>. I use Todoist to manage my tasks and activities. The <a href="https://support.todoist.com/hc/en-us/articles/205383721-Apps">Todoist mobile application</a> stores all tasks offline. It allows adding tasks when disconnected and synchronizes it to the server when connected. I also use OneNote for capturing notes which also has an offline mode.</p>

<h4><strong>Trip Planner</strong></h4>

<p>For short local trips, the recently launched <a href="https://get.google.com/trips/">Google Trips</a> is useful. Google Now already shows trip summaries and alerts on the home page. Google Trips takes this to the next level and allows to manage all trip data at one place. It helps collate all the travel booking in one place and makes it available in offline mode.</p>

<p><img  alt="Google Trips for managing trip data offline" src="/images/offlinelife_trips.png"/></p>

<p>These are the common things that I have my mobile setup for offline mode. I have had this setup while I was in Sydney, as I try to stay disconnected when commuting to work. Staying off the internet helps me get more things done!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Two Months and Counting - Android and Nexus 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T16:08:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/review-two-months-and-counting-android-and-nexus-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gadgets, especially mobile phones have always been of interest to me and so is it even today. Its been over two months since I have moved over to Android on Nexus 5. I have been a loyal, hardcore Windows phone fan for over 3 years before that and it did take time to get used to the new operating system. There are still things that I like about Windows phone but there are things that I don’t like too, so I though of giving Android a try. <a href="https://www.google.com/nexus/5/">Nexus 5</a> is one powerful device that is worth every penny for its power packed features and there is no reason not to like it. The <a href="http://www.androidpolice.com/2013/10/20/weekend-poll-nexus-5-white-or-black/">White vs Black</a> confusion was there but then I got the White one, as that was the only thing in stock, and after all with a protective cover on, it didn’t matter much.</p>

<p><strong>Things that I love:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Notification</strong> : The one stop place for all notifications is one of the best things that I like moving to Android from Windows phone. A <a href="http://i.msdn.microsoft.com/dynimg/IC619123.png">missed toast</a> is always missed until I next decide to open that app in Windows phone or maybe a lock screen notification. But now it is right there on the notification center. (though I have many notifications turned off as part of <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-organized-finding-a-system-to-manage-it-all/">Staying Organized</a>)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Toggle Settings : <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.painless.pc">Toggling settings</a></strong> like Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, 3G etc is also top on my likes. There is at least 2 steps required for toggling these settings in Windows phone</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Google Now : </strong>I have been googling around for a lot of years and like the way Google Now updates on searches that I have done. Yes I know that we have a privacy problem here, but I have decided to stay on the internet – everything gets tracked here. The <strong>speech recognition</strong> of Google is as best it can get today, best thing being it understands my accent (Indian) pretty much all the time.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Apps: </strong>I have never been a fan of apps and I rarely used them. Windows phone did have all the major apps, but most of them lacked all the features because of which I had to switch to the web app at times. This in fact made me use the web app always. But Android apps mostly has all the features which makes me use them more. Some of the apps that I use regularly are :</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ch.bitspin.timely">Timely</a> : An awesome alarm clock with the cool Smart Rise feature</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.gm">Gmail</a> : With all the features of the web app</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.skype.raider">Skype</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.microsoft.office.lync15">Lync</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.whatsapp">Whatsapp</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.facebook.katana">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.twitter.android">Twitter</a>: Helps me keep connected with my friends, peers and customers</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.giant">Google Analytics</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wordpress.android">Wordpress</a> – For keeping track of my blog</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.authenticator2">Authenticator</a> – for all two-step verification codes</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.microsoft.skydrive">Onedrive</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.dropbox.android">Dropbox</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.github.mobile">GitHub</a> – For managing my cloud storage. GitHub has a lot more to improve on features.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.stitcher.app">Stitcher</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.devhd.feedly">Feedly</a>, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=mobi.beyondpod">BeyondPod</a> – For feeds and podcasts</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.microsoft.office.onenote">OneNote</a> and the native email app - For tracking notes, <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/staying-organized-finding-a-system-to-manage-it-all/">tasks and exchange emails</a>. The native email application has a lot of scope for improvement</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.alienmanfc6.wheresmyandroid">Where&rsquo;s My Droid</a> - Finding a lost phone equivalent on Windows Phone.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.amazon.kindle">Kindle</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.overdrive.mobile.android.mediaconsole">Overdrive</a> - For my kindle books and audio books</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.nurik.roman.dashclock">DashClock Widget</a> - For lock screen notifications</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ro.weednet.contactssync">UberSync</a> – To sync facebook contacts and profile pictures to a contact. This is something that is really good in windows phone. Ability to link all social accounts of a person/contact.</p></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Customization: </strong>The level of customization and control that each application gives is enormous that almost everything is configurable. You can mute/turn off notifications on annoying text promotion messages, different color notifications, auto update settings and a lot more.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Chrome: </strong>This definitely is one another on my top likes. I have been using chrome for a long time and absolutely love the experience even on android. The password sync across devices is cool and so is <a href="https://support.google.com/chrome/answer/2591582?hl=en">Sync tabs across devices</a>. Bookmarks sync and support for <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.delicious">Delicious</a> is also good. IE definitely has a long way to go there. The <a href="https://developers.google.com/chrome-developer-tools/docs/remote-debugging">developer support</a> for chrome on android is also worth mentioning.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Things that I don’t like and miss:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Jumplist: <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/windows-phone-series-jump-lists/">Jumplists</a></strong> really made navigating through large lists a lot easier on Windows phone. Now I always need to hit the search button and type.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>People Hub: </strong>This was one of the best things of Windows phone, having the ability to <a href="http://www.windowsphone.com/en-us/how-to/wp7/people/people-hub?signin=true">link all your social networks</a> into one and have a quick access of all updates.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Nokia Music and Drive: </strong>In fact all the Nokia suite apps were really good and especially these two.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The lists itself explains much of it – <strong>I am liking it a lot. </strong>The android experience on a Nexus device is fast and smooth.</p>

<p><strong>Cases and Covers:</strong></p>

<p>I have been alternating between 2 cases for my Nexus 5 from Spigen and liking them both especially the Neo Hybrid. The white shows of through its transparent back and the overall grip on the phone is very good and comfortable.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.in/gp/product/B00HYA10LC/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3626&amp;creative=24822&amp;creativeASIN=B00HYA10LC&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-21">Spigen Google Nexus 5 Case ULTRA HYBRID</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.in/gp/product/B00EV8Y6QQ/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3626&amp;creative=24822&amp;creativeASIN=B00EV8Y6QQ&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=rahulpnath-21">Spigen Google Nexus 5 Case Protective Neo Hybrid</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>The <strong>battery</strong> backup on the device is pretty good and is lasting for me through a day. I have not yet been on any trips with the phone, so can’t comment on the battery in such situations where generally it lasts lesser. But <a href="http://www.ibtimes.com/google-working-nexus-5-battery-drain-fix-affects-all-android-devices-kitkat-qualcomm-chips-1559771">Google has also announced</a> on a battery leak issue for which a fix would be out soon. Hope that would improve it further. I have never been a fan of phone <strong>camera, </strong>since <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/photography-learning-to-click/">I prefer my DSLR</a> for that, but even then for a camera it is pretty decent with lots of options and filters. At times it does come handy and works perfect.</p>

<p>If you are planning to get a new phone and then this is worth considering. If you are already using one then do let know on what you feel about the phone?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What made me choose : Vanguard UP-Rise 45]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/what-made-me-choose-vanguard-up-rise-45/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-05T16:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/what-made-me-choose-vanguard-up-rise-45</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Deciding on a dslr was not so tough a year back, it was either Canon or Nikon and it just happened that i chose Canon since in the beginner level series neither seemed to make a difference, at least for me. I have a <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Canon-550D-Digital-Camera-Body/dp/B0037KM0EY">Canon 550d</a> with a set of beginner level lenses (a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Canon-EF-S-18-55mm-3-5-5-6-II/dp/B000V5K3FG/ref=sr_1_1?s=electronics&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1357390070&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=canon+18-55">18-55mm</a> kit lens, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Canon-50mm-1-8-Camera-Lens/dp/B00007E7JU/ref=sr_1_1?s=electronics&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1357390018&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=canon+50mm+1.8">50mm</a> prime and a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Canon-55-250mm-4-0-5-6-Telephoto-Digital/dp/B0011NVMO8">55-250mm</a> telephoto zoom) and a tripod(1.3 kg ,folded height 460mm).
For over an year I was using the bag that came with my dslr and decided now to upgrade to a better one, as I found it difficult to carry around the camera, lenses and tripod. I was looking for a backpack model and with lots of brands out there choosing one was really a tough thing. At first I did want to have a bag that could take a laptop too, but then decided against it as all those bags that could take a laptop tend to be a bit bulky. Carrying a laptop would be only while I travel and not when I go out for shooting, so then decided against one with a laptop. After some online research I shortlisted a couple of bags.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://products.lowepro.com/product/flipside-300,2083.htm">Lowepro Flipside 300</a></li>
<li><a href="http://products.lowepro.com/product/DSLR-Video%20Fastpack%20250%20AW,2282.htm">Lowepro Video Fastpack 250aw</a></li>
<li><a href="http://products.lowepro.com/product/Pro-Runner-200-AW,2181,14.htm">Lowepro Pro Runner 200AW</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.manfrotto.com/product/0/MB%2BSB390-3BC/_/Veloce_III_Camera_Backpack_for_DSLR_(Bungee_Cord)">Manfrotto Veloce III</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Deciding to drop into a store to see them was the best thing that I did, and I suggest everyone planning to buy a dslr bag to do that. What’s good for me, might not work out for you. Except the flipside one I did see everything else. For me the fastpack 250aw was a bit bulky, the Pro Runner a bit too small and lacking a quick access entry. Manfrotto was decent enough but then my tripod would not go through the tripod strap, since my tripod has all its legs connected to the centre rod.
I happened to see the Vanguard Up-rise 43, which was actually a sling bag but had all the other features I was looking for. It was sleek looking, well padded,had a tripod holder(now this one had a adjustable strap to hold the tripod), a quick access,rain cover.
Back home I did again a bit of research and got to see the Up-rise 45,46 and 48, which is the backpack bags in the up-rise series . Now that was what exactly I was looking for. 48 was way too big for me. Now had to choose between the 46 and 45 the only difference being the former could take a laptop too,and was not that bulky too. Also the models are also different. For Up-rise 46 the bag opening was from the <a href="http://www.premier-ink.co.uk/images/images_big/vg_uprise46_1.jpg">front</a> and for Up-rise 45 the opening was from the <a href="http://img2.blogs.yahoo.co.jp/ybi/1/7a/03/shira_gon/folder/1199363/img_1199363_32950708_2?1268142426">back</a>. The Up-rise 46 had just one problem of having the tripod strap on the opening bag flap, having you to untie the tripod first(if you have used that to tie the tripod. This one also does have a elastic band to the middle of the bag through which you can slide your tripod in, as in manfrotto. But then my tripod had to tied using the strap due to the same problem mentioned above).
So finally I had a choice, <a href="http://www.vanguardworld.com/index.php/en/pv/products/detail-1-1-4-33.html">Vanguard Up-Rise 45</a>, at least for now that I feel might be good for me. Just got it shipped today and planning to take it with me for the next trip.
Below are some snaps of the my bag. I did find a good <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_A4GN5lJhQY">video</a> on youtube which shows all the features, so I didn’t want to do one again.</p>

<div class="wlWriterEditableSmartContent" id="scid:66721397-FF69-4ca6-AEC4-17E6B3208830:a7930e23-e5d9-4bbf-a9d8-0bb834e7717a" style="float: none; margin: 0; display: inline; padding: 0;">
<table style="outline: none; border-style: none; margin: 0; padding: 0; width: 408px; border-collapse: collapse;" border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="outline: none; border-style: none; margin: 0; padding: 5px 0 5px 5px; width: 159px; vertical-align: bottom;" colspan="2"><a style="outline: none; border-style: none; margin: 0; padding: 0;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=play&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3950&amp;parid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=1&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww" target="_blank"> <img style="outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0; margin: 0; border: 0; background: none; background-image: none; vertical-align: bottom;" title="View album" alt="vanguard uprise45 review" src="/images/vanguard_uprise45_review.png" width="159" height="159" border="0" /></a></td>
<td style="vertical-align: middle; margin: 0; padding: 5px 5px 5px 0; outline: none; border-style: none; width: 226px;" colspan="3">
<div style="margin-left: 10px; top: -3%;">
<div style="width: 226px; overflow: visible;"><a style="text-decoration: none;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=browse&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=5&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos" target="_blank"><span style="line-height: 1.26em; padding: 0; width: 226px; font-size: 26pt; font-family: 'Segoe UI', helvetica, arial, sans-serif;">Vanguard Up-Rise 45</span></a></div>
<div style="padding: 10px 0 0; margin: 0;">
<table style="margin: 0; padding: 0; outline: none; border-style: none; border-collapse: collapse; width: auto;" border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="vertical-align: top; outline: none; border-style: none; margin: 0; padding: 10px 15px 6px 0;"><a style="font-family: 'Segoe UI', helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 8pt; outline: none; border-style: none; text-decoration: none; padding: 0; margin: 0;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=play&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=5&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos" target="_blank">VIEW SLIDE SHOW</a></td>
<td style="vertical-align: top; outline: none; border-style: none; margin: 0; padding: 10px 0 6px;"><a style="font-family: 'Segoe UI', helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 8pt; outline: none; border-style: none; text-decoration: none; padding: 0; margin: 0;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=downloadphotos&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=5&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww" target="_blank">DOWNLOAD ALL</a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="vertical-align: bottom; outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0 5px 5px; margin: 0; width: 77px; height: 77px;"><a style="font-family: 'Segoe UI', helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 8pt; outline: none; border-style: none; text-decoration: none; padding: 0; margin: 0;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=play&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3951&amp;parid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=1&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww" target="_blank"><img style="outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0; margin: 0; border: 0; background: none; background-image: none; vertical-align: bottom;" title="View album" alt="vanguard uprise45 review" src="/images/vanguard_uprise45_review_1.png" width="77" height="77" border="0" /></a></td>
<td style="vertical-align: bottom; outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0 5px 5px 0; margin: 0; width: 77px; height: 77px;"><a style="font-family: 'Segoe UI', helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 8pt; outline: none; border-style: none; text-decoration: none; padding: 0; margin: 0;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=play&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3952&amp;parid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=1&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww" target="_blank"><img style="outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0; margin: 0; border: 0; background: none; background-image: none; vertical-align: bottom;" title="View album" alt="vanguard uprise45 review" src="/images/vanguard_uprise45_review_2.png" width="77" height="77" border="0" /></a></td>
<td style="vertical-align: bottom; outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0 5px 5px 0; margin: 0; width: 77px; height: 77px;"><a style="font-family: 'Segoe UI', helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 8pt; outline: none; border-style: none; text-decoration: none; padding: 0; margin: 0;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=play&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3953&amp;parid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=1&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww" target="_blank"><img style="outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0; margin: 0; border: 0; background: none; background-image: none; vertical-align: bottom;" title="View album" alt="vanguard uprise45 review" src="/images/vanguard_uprise45_review_3.png" width="77" height="77" border="0" /></a></td>
<td style="vertical-align: bottom; outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0 5px 5px 0; margin: 0; width: 77px; height: 77px;"><a style="font-family: 'Segoe UI', helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 8pt; outline: none; border-style: none; text-decoration: none; padding: 0; margin: 0;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=play&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3954&amp;parid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=1&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww" target="_blank"><img style="outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0; margin: 0; border: 0; background: none; background-image: none; vertical-align: bottom;" title="View album" alt="vanguard uprise45 review" src="/images/vanguard_uprise45_review_4.png" width="77" height="77" border="0" /></a></td>
<td style="vertical-align: bottom; outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0 5px 5px 0; margin: 0; width: 77px; height: 77px;"><a style="font-family: 'Segoe UI', helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 8pt; outline: none; border-style: none; text-decoration: none; padding: 0; margin: 0;" href="https://skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?cid=d5a8034107adc30c&amp;page=play&amp;resid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3955&amp;parid=D5A8034107ADC30C!3949&amp;type=1&amp;Bsrc=Photomail&amp;Bpub=SDX.Photos&amp;authkey=!ABkuQXjWWoHjsww" target="_blank"><img style="outline: none; border-style: none; padding: 0; margin: 0; border: 0; background: none; background-image: none; vertical-align: bottom;" title="View album" alt="vanguard uprise45 review" src="/images/vanguard_uprise45_review_5.png" width="77" height="77" border="0" /></a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>


<p>In short the main things that made my choose the Vanguard Up-Rise 45</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Shoulder bag with a sleek design</p></li>
<li><p>Quick access  for the camera</p></li>
<li><p>tripod holder,rain cover</p></li>
<li><p>flipside kind of access too, since the opening was in the back</p></li>
<li><p>good cushion paddings(you don’t feel the weight at all)</p></li>
<li><p>sturdy even with the tripod attached and had no issues accessing the quick access</p></li>
<li><p>all straps could be nicely tucked away into appropriate slots, leaving no hanging straps</p></li>
<li><p>a compartment for accessories</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Hope you have a good time choosing your bag !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[the Nokia Monster]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/the-nokia-monster/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-16T11:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/the-nokia-monster</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" alt="nokia n95 review" src="/images/nokia_n95_review.jpg" />
Of all the mobiles I have used till date this one goes top on my rating.With its elegant design,built quality and power packed features,the N95 8GB was worth every penny spent.8GB was not much of an attraction though, but definitely it being internal memory,boosted the performance.No longer I felt the time lag in apps opening,as in the previous models of Nokia.<br/>
Though its been a long time this big monster has been released it demands this piece of space here. <br/>
Not going into the specs of the phone,for there are sites which gives them in and out like this one <a href="http://www.phonearena.com/htmls/Nokia-N95-8GB-phone-p_2344.html">here</a>.<br/>
The 5 mega pixel camera is definitely a lookout feature,for you no more need a dedicated camera,if all you want is a snap of the moment.<br/>
The two way slide feature with dedicated music keys makes it to be on the race with pmp&rsquo;s out in the store,with the battery lasting pretty enough for an average music lover.<br/>
With the wide range of apps available for the symbian os , this definitely was the king of its times&hellip;..Nokia N95 8GB</p>

<p><strong>edit: </strong><a href="http://n95-download.xhost.ro/?p=4">here </a>goes a list of must have apps in the n95</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
