<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: Thoughts | Rahul Nath]]></title>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/tag/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-10T12:07:48+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://rahulpnath.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul Nath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stars Do Count!!!!]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-17T17:33:58+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/stars-do-count</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For all those who are wondering what this stars are,please go through my first <a href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/do-stars-count/">post</a> on this.</p>

<p>Casually browsing through my mails today morning,I found a mail with the subject stating,&lsquo;<em>Your online community contributions have been recognized by Microsoft</em>&rsquo;,informing me that I have won the Microsoft <a href="http://www.microsoftcommunitycontributor.com/">Community Contributor Award</a>.Really excited to have the first award for a technical contribution,and that too from Microsoft.</p>

<p><img src="/mcca_rahulpnath.png" alt="Microsoft Community Contributor Award Certificate for Rahul P Nath" /></p>

<p>I appreciate Microsoft for promoting community contributors and rewarding them.Personally,I enjoy contributing in communities as I find it one another way to learn.I used not just reply to questions that I knew,but often ended up creating a sample application and finding out the solution first,which has helped me a lot in learning.</p>

<p>I would like to thank Microsoft and all the community members and people who would  have nominated me for this award.</p>

<p>Stars Do Count sometimes :)</p>

<p>edit: The award would be retired as now I am an Microsoft employee.I had intimated them on this ,as I guess somehow their records missed that I am their employee :).So got the mail confirmation today..award is retired .Still it&rsquo;s a good feeling in having achieved it at the first place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Attachments in email - a new way]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/attachments-in-email-a-new-way/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-25T13:40:24+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/attachments-in-email-a-new-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a though on a new mail attachment way :).</p>

<p>What if we could attach existing attachments in our mailbox to new mails that we want to send.Forwarding the mail that had the attachment might not be a good solution in many a cases.</p>

<p>The key point here is that attachments should be like a resource,that can be shared across mails,that can be deleted edited or updated.</p>

<p>There could be a small widget showing all attachments that you have in your mailbox,from which you can add whatever you want to your current mail.</p>

<p>I think this would be a cool feature in the present email system.</p>

<p>You would not end up uploading the same file again and again :)</p>

<p>Feel free to comment on this idea ::)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[...Retrospect]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/retrospect/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-11T19:36:05+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/retrospect</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I was migrating my blogs on to wordpress,I just went through all my previous posts.It seems all my posts are just a brief overview ,very brief indeed,on various topics and promising detailed posts in due time.But nothing detailed ever turned up.I guess I have to stick on to the promises and start writing blogs in detail,explore things in detail.</p>

<p>Not this post but&hellip;aaaahh&hellip;.procrastination!!!!!</p>

<p>No definitely not  (atleast to keep myself happy ;)).</p>

<p>But definitely the next post.</p>

<p>Ps: And it feels better to use wordpress :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seek the problem, Not the Solution]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/seek-the-problem-not-the-solution/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-07T11:44:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/seek-the-problem-not-the-solution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s not uncommon to have problems in life, and so in the application/code that you write. I am not being too techie here.
It’s just I am relating my thoughts to something technical.
Being a software engineer, writing code is inevitable in my day-to-day life and so comes bugs :)
I spend  a lot of time sitting on to solve bugs(of late it’s been eating away  my head) and so do I see people  around me,  at my workplace, doing the same.</p>

<p>I always go in seek of the problem that caused the bug, rather than to find a solution for the bug.
Certain others go in seek of the solution for the bug, rather than the problem that caused the bug.
So am I not saying the same thing in two different ways….solving the bug!!!!
But they are not…at least for me :)</p>

<p>Seeking for the problem gives you the solution for the bug and also a better understanding of the code that you have written. You seek for the problem because  you feel the mistake is at your part, maybe a implementation one or a logical one.
Seeking for the solution too solves the bug but does  not give you  a better understanding of that you have done. Mostly the solution might be a workaround to cover up some of your own mistakes, which went unnoticed, as you were too concerned of the solution for the bug and not  the problem for the bug. This might really not solve the bug too, it might just be a temporary fix or a specific scenario fix.</p>

<p>This is just an example.
Same goes in the day to day life. Whenever you go in seek for solutions you are actually creating more problems for yourself.
Maybe a real life example(non technical :)) would do good.
Say you are a spendthrift and you keep spending away all what  you get.
Need money urgently?? Solution is to borrow from your friend. Does it really solve the problem??
Nope !! The problem here is that you are spendthrift. So try to change that and not keep borrowing :).</p>

<p>Don’t be happy with the solution, hunt down the  problem.
Happy hunting :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hero or a Cheat????]]></title>
    <link href="http://rahulpnath.com/blog/hero-or-a-cheat/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-03T11:50:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://rahulpnath.com/blog/hero-or-a-cheat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" alt="suarez_world_cup_2010" src="/images/suarez_world_cup_2010.jpg" />
Luis Suárez&hellip;.that name would be said few more times, at least till Uruguay&rsquo;s fate is decided in FIFA WC 2010.Early Saturday morning(IST),witnessed some <a href="http://www.fifa.com/worldcup/matches/round=249718/match=300061508/index.html#ghana+penalty">dramatic moments</a> of WC 2010.With the game about to be pushed into the shootout,which it did end up eventually,Ghana was to score a goal of substitute Dominic Adiyiah&rsquo;s header which was denied by Suárez with his &lsquo;hands&rsquo;.The drama ended as Asamoah Gyan struck the crossbar for the penalty awarded and the match moved on to shootout,which saw Uruguay through to the best 4&hellip;.shattering the African hopes.<br/>
Is he a Hero or a Cheat????<br/>
Wasn&rsquo;t it something anyone would have done?<br/>
Wasn&rsquo;t that a reaction rather than a response to a situation?<br/>
Ghana could have scored in the penalty awarded.But is just a penalty enough instead of a sure shot goal?</p>

<p>Would it be the next &lsquo;Hand Of God&rsquo;??</p>

<p>Hero Or Cheat,fouls are committed knowingly and unknowingly in any game,as in football,as in this dramatic game.</p>

<p>So the play goes on says referee and so does Uruguay without him into the final 4</p>

<p>edit: Not too far says Netherlands,putting an end to the Uruguay&rsquo;s tale of WC 2010</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
